<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>article on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/article/</link>
    <description>Recent content in article on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 20:03:05 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/article/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🗼 What is this weird tower doing in a San Jose Suburb?</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/longlines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 20:03:05 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/longlines/</guid>
      <description>Hey all! Experimenting with a new format - video! Enjoy this brief walk-through of AT&amp;amp;T&amp;rsquo;s long-lines system!
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🚆 Is DART&#39;s New Transit Line Enough to Save It? (Part 2: Execution)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 11:50:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept2/</guid>
      <description>The Silver Line  DART&amp;rsquo;s new Silver Line crossing Central. (image credit)
  In my first article in this series, I wrote about how DART&amp;rsquo;s well-intentioned but poorly timed bet on park-and-ride led to system-level inefficiencies. But there&amp;rsquo;s good news! The Silver Line fixes a ton of DART&amp;rsquo;s existing issues - let&amp;rsquo;s see how on a map of the line.
 DART Silver Line&amp;rsquo;s right-of-way.
  Previous DART lines had lots of stations at regular intervals - more like beefed-up bus lines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🚆 Is DART&#39;s New Transit Line Enough to Save It? (Part 1: Context)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 11:00:49 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept1/</guid>
      <description>Two trains pulling into the Silver Line station at UTD
  Dallas Area Rapid Transit serves over 50 million people a year. And in five months, if even one of Dallas&#39; twelve suburbs vote to leave DART, we could lose it for good. At the same time, DART just linked these disgruntled suburbs with its newest rail line. Is the state-of-the-art Silver Line enough to placate Plano and Co.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🎧 Why I replaced Spotify with a Playstation Portable for a month</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 18:54:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with my previous essay, you know I have mixed feelings on music streaming. Spotify, with its algorithmic recommendations and &amp;ldquo;gamification&amp;rdquo; of listening hours, seems purpose-built for constant, mindless music consumption. I was sick of it. Would I enjoy music more if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the Spotify ecosystem at all? This October, I set out to answer this question - the hard way. I blocked Spotify for the whole month and moved my music over to&amp;hellip; A Playstation Portable!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏭Why Did My College Campus Look So... Depressing?</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/tamuarch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 22:05:04 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/tamuarch/</guid>
      <description>All-star Brutalist Skyline at Texas A&amp;amp;M
  If you went to college in the US, chances are you&amp;rsquo;ve seen a few depressing buildings like these. Often called &amp;ldquo;Brutalist&amp;rdquo; architecture, maybe you also heard rumors that they were built by the Russians or designed to suppress student riots. I&amp;rsquo;ll take a crack at separating fact from fiction today, as I process what made this style so popular, and why public colleges (of all tenants) seemed to fall in love.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🚫🚆 Writing about everything *but* the trains in Japan</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jptransit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 19:41:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jptransit/</guid>
      <description>Shonan Monorail (image credit)
  As an engineer, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to visit Japan and not be obsessed with its trains. From record-breaking bullet trains to spaghetti-like subway networks, Japan does trains better than anywhere else I&amp;rsquo;ve been. But even the most train-obsessed nations acknowledge that heavy rail isn&amp;rsquo;t a catch-all solution. So as a bit of a curveball, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this transit post about everything but the trains in Japan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🚃 Rating Every Train in San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/sftransit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 10:03:08 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/sftransit/</guid>
      <description>As some may know, I moved to Santa Clara about a year ago. But if a non-Californian asks me where I live, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to skip the geography lesson and just say San Francisco. Despite how often I use this line, I recently realized I haven&amp;rsquo;t really explored San Francisco yet.
Sure, I&amp;rsquo;ve driven in for a few concerts - but that&amp;rsquo;s not exploring. Driving is all point-to-point. Pull up to the destination and park in the least sketchy lot you can find.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏎️ What Genre is Mario Kart Music?</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mariokartmusic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 18:20:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mariokartmusic/</guid>
      <description>Killer debut album cover for Casiopea! (image credit)
  Grab a pair of headphones, because this article has a soundtrack! Check out the first song in this Youtube playlist: does it remind you of anything?
 hint hint (image credit)
  If your formative years were later than 1990, your first thought was likely &amp;ldquo;Mario Kart&amp;rdquo;. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be alone - more and more people seem to be finding (and even writing!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📲 Scope Creep and Personal Projects</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 22:13:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</guid>
      <description>Some viewers (especially programmers) may find the following image disturbing:
 Charitably, software gore
  Ouch. Is that Python or Javascript? And do I spy inline CSS styling? To quote The Talking Heads, &amp;ldquo;How did I get here?&amp;quot; After all, no one ever sets out to write bad code. While bad code can result from laziness or inexperience, I want to spend this article discussing a third source: Scope Creep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏙️ Is Nagoya Boring?</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 19:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</guid>
      <description>Recently, it seems like everyone I talk to is either visiting or returning from Japan. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just my observation - according to multiple sources, Japan&amp;rsquo;s post-covid tourism numbers are through the roof. While many plan their trips around the glitz and glamor of Tokyo or the rich culture of Kyoto, there&amp;rsquo;s another city that I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to see on any itinerary - Nagoya.
Despite being it&amp;rsquo;s third largest metro area, Nagoya is nationally renowned as &amp;ldquo;Japan&amp;rsquo;s most boring city&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
