<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 15:06:31 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Boss Pedal Switching Issues? Try This! (Boss GE-7 Modding)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 15:06:31 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</guid>
      <description>Post-Mod GE-7
The Mod If you just want to skip to the fix, head to this section.
At the advice of Brian Wampler, I caved and bought a minty used Boss GE-7. Imagine my surprise as I realized that moving any of the EQ sliders introduced very noticeable noise! How could you, Boss? Apparently, when the GE-7 was first designed, battery life and price point were more important than audio fidelity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>💡 DIY Connected Lanterns with MQTT, Adafruit Feather</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 19:04:34 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</guid>
      <description>Faced with the tradition of family Christmas gift giving, I was thoroughly stumped. I knew I wanted to do something maker-related: I&amp;rsquo;m the only engineer in the family, which tends to amplify the wow factor of any techncal projects :)
After my fallback plan (a Chemex coffee maker) fell through, I knew I had to build these!
the finished product!
These are long-distance friendship lanterns. The idea is, sometimes you want to let a distant friend or family member know that you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of them, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily want to shoot them a text.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spelling Test Grader [UPDATE]</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 15:36:55 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader-update/</guid>
      <description>One in six children who are not reading proficiently in third grade fail to graduate from high school on time, four times the rate for children with proficient third-grade reading skills. &amp;ndash; &amp;quot;Double Jeopardy&amp;quot;, Annie E. Casey Foundation
Since rolling out my spelling test grader, Catch Up and Read (CAR) has asked for more grading automation! Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick update on the new grader, the Phonics Survey.
What is a Phonics Survey?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MGMT&#39;s Anti-Breakout Album: Congratulations</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 10:20:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</guid>
      <description>We are absolutely dead serious about music-making, and that’s what we want people to understand, that there’s no joke in it. We’re not intentionally trying to f*ck with people, we’re actually making this music that we love and we want people to hear it.1 ~ Ben Goldwasser
You may not be familiar with MGMT, but anyone who had a pulse in the late 2000&amp;rsquo;s has most likely heard their work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏆 MyMirror: a Google-integrated Smart Mirror</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 13:28:52 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</guid>
      <description>Note: More information about myMirror can be found on the project&amp;rsquo;s devpost. Check there for other peoples&amp;rsquo; contributions!
Why myMirror? When I wake up in the morning, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot I know I probably should do. For example, I should probably prepare for the day ahead by checking the weather and my daily calendar. But often times, I just don&amp;rsquo;t. For situations like this, myMirror is here to help.
myMirror solves the above dilemma by integrating this crucial information into your everyday bathroom mirror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spelling Test Auto-Grader for Catch Up and Read</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 18:21:31 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Automation is good, so long as you know exactly where to put the machine.&amp;rdquo;
~ Eliyahu Goldratt
One perk of being a programmer is the ability to automate boring, repetitive tasks to ease my workload. But what&amp;rsquo;s even more rewarding is the opportunity to help non-programmers with their data analysis drudgery. Such is the case with this project.
The Problem My mom works for Catch Up and Read, a Dallas non-profit that helps below-reading-level students catch up before third grade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional CD Crafting with CDRDAO</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 13:55:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</guid>
      <description>All digital music listeners are equal. Acquisition is painless. Taste is irrelevant. It is pointless to boast about your iTunes collection, or the quality of your playlists on a streaming service. Music became data, one more set of 1&amp;rsquo;s and 0&amp;rsquo;s lurking in your hard drive, invisible to see and impossible to touch. Nothing is less cool than data. ~ David Sax
Physical media is back. vinyl and cassette sales are through the roof, and why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t they be?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethan Cope, Briefly</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/aboutme/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 13:58:37 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/aboutme/</guid>
      <description>Hi! I&amp;rsquo;m Ethan Cope, an electrical engineer, multi-instrumentalist, and mac-and-cheese connoisseur.
I currently live in College Station, Texas, where I study electrical engineering and mix live audio.
This site is intended to capture the life cycles of my many side-projects. Most of these projects lie somewhere on the broad spectrum of engineering, from open source software to album reviews to DIY electronics.
So why am I documenting my projects in excruciating detail?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Echo-Matic Deluxe (Part 1): Marantz-based DIY Tape Echo</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 13:07:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</guid>
      <description>Back in 2019, I saw the influential space-rock group Wand live. It was an amazing set of mostly new tunes, but I was a tad distracted by their lead guitarist. He was fiddling with a battered green box for the whole set, and doing so sent his guitar part soaring over the rest of the band in the most atmospheric, gooey wash imaginable. This was my first introduction to the weird, wonderful world of tape echo, and I wanted one!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buswarn: RasPi-based Transit Bus Tracking</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 12:53:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</guid>
      <description>Public transportation is like a magnifying glass that shows you civilization up close. ~ Chris Gethard
What is Buswarn? During the COVID year, I moved off-campus. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize at the time, but my only lifeline to my in-person classes, study rooms, and meals would be the Texas A&amp;amp;M Bus Transit System. Problems manifested themselves quickly. Buses ran at seemingly random intervals, and the website that displayed the schedule often had errors rendering on my mobile phone.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
