<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 16:32:24 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🚝 Exploring Las Colinas&#39; Mothballed Monorail</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 16:32:24 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</guid>
      <description>Sign at the entrance of the APT&#xA;On the surface, Dallas looks like just another cookie-cutter commuter city. Compared to Austin&amp;rsquo;s booming tech industry and laid-back vibe, Dallas&amp;rsquo; historic hyperfocus on sprawling office parks has always felt a bit clinical. But the combination of this all-work all-the-time culture and a early 80&amp;rsquo;s real-estate boom led to some crazy planning experiments, and none were as crazy as the Irving&amp;rsquo;s Las Colinas district.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Personal Projects and Giving Up (Echo-Matic Deluxe Update)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 15:39:53 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</guid>
      <description>Personal projects often feel like a weird limbo between work and play. Starting a project motivated by nothing but passion and a willingness to learn is great. Even if the initial enthusiasm fades, it&amp;rsquo;s still worth it to power through. A finished project is often its own satisfaction. But when all personal interest in the project evaporates, even the most simple tasks become tedious. Every time I think about my gutted Marantz tape deck project, I find myself caring less and less.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Japan&#39;s Early-2000&#39;s Architectural Nostalgia</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 01:00:07 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</guid>
      <description>The architectural definition of &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;1 has always been a moving target. Every year, once &amp;ldquo;stylistically cutting-edge&amp;rdquo; buildings slip into the realm of &amp;ldquo;dated&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cliche&amp;rdquo;. And the other day, I finally stumbled on across a building that proved this point. Nagoya&amp;rsquo;s Sasashima-Ribu station is totally representative of a particular architectural style; one that, at the time of it&amp;rsquo;s construction, was synonymous with &amp;ldquo;modern architecture&amp;rdquo;. But a quarter of a century has separated innovation from trend, revealing a slew of early 2000&amp;rsquo;s quintessential quirks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Japan&#39;s Most Iconic Model Cars Come Out Of Vending Machines</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 01:00:15 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</guid>
      <description>Remember those 25-cent gumball machines? The ones where you could trade a quarter for a gumball older than the dotcom crash? Imagine that, but instead of a chunk of crusty candy, you win a random 1/64th scale model car. That&amp;rsquo;s essentially Gachapon!&#xA;Bandai Namco&amp;rsquo;s toy vending machines are addictively simple. Insert cash (1), twist dial (2), and collect model (3). Since the 1970&amp;rsquo;s, Gachapon machines have dispensed billions of anime figurines, sushi keychains, and (most notably), tiny scale vehicles.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>🏆 Battery Recycling: The Dark Side of an All-EV Future (2nd place, Problems Worth Solving Competition 2023)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 17:30:30 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;ve got to start with the customer experience and work back toward the technology, not the other way around. ~ Steve Jobs&#xA;Last weekend I had the opportunity to participate in Problems Worth Solving: Texas A&amp;amp;M&amp;rsquo;s first and only entrepreneurship competition that outright bans solutions.&#xA;Great businesses arise from an intimate understanding of your customers&amp;rsquo; needs. PWS emphasizes this critical step of entrepreneurship by focusing entrepreneurs on the problem, not the solution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A sane mini-tutorial for the Jenkins Javascript API</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jenkinsapi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 14:51:34 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jenkinsapi/</guid>
      <description>Holy moly, the Jenkins documentation is bad. At the very least, it isn&amp;rsquo;t very user-friendly, especially for beginners. For someone who has little-to-no experience in web development, doing something as simple as getting some job data from a Node program is the equivalent of pulling teeth. After spending hours in rabbit holes, I finally stumbled on a configuration that works. This mini-writeup will hopefully help those webdev-challenged folks such as myself in the quest for Jenkins API usage.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boss Pedal Switching Issues? Try This! (Boss GE-7 Modding)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 15:06:31 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</guid>
      <description>Post-Mod GE-7&#xA;The Mod If you just want to skip to the fix, head to this section.&#xA;At the advice of Brian Wampler, I caved and bought a minty used Boss GE-7. Imagine my surprise after moving any of the EQ sliders introduced very noticeable noise! How could you, Boss? Apparently, when the GE-7 was first designed, battery life and price point were more important considerations than audio fidelity. As a result, any GE-7s made from 1981 to 2017 use the TL022 dual op-amp chips.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>💡 SignalBox: DIY Connected Lanterns with MQTT, Adafruit Feather</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 19:04:34 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</guid>
      <description>Faced with the tradition of family Christmas gift giving, I was thoroughly stumped. I knew I wanted to do something maker-related: I&amp;rsquo;m the only engineer in the family, which tends to amplify the wow factor of any techncal projects :)&#xA;After my fallback plan (a Chemex coffee maker) fell through, I knew I had to build these!&#xA;the finished product!&#xA;These are long-distance friendship lanterns. The idea is, sometimes you want to let a distant friend or family member know that you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of them, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily want to shoot them a text.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spelling Test Grader [UPDATE]</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 15:36:55 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader-update/</guid>
      <description>One in six children who are not reading proficiently in third grade fail to graduate from high school on time, four times the rate for children with proficient third-grade reading skills. &amp;ndash; &amp;quot;Double Jeopardy&amp;quot;, Annie E. Casey Foundation&#xA;Since rolling out my spelling test grader, Catch Up and Read (CAR) has asked for more grading automation! Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick update on the new grader, the Phonics Survey.&#xA;What is a Phonics Survey?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MGMT&#39;s Anti-Breakout Album: Congratulations</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 10:20:53 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</guid>
      <description>We are absolutely dead serious about music-making, and that’s what we want people to understand, that there’s no joke in it. We’re not intentionally trying to f*ck with people, we’re actually making this music that we love and we want people to hear it.1 ~ Ben Goldwasser&#xA;You may not be familiar with MGMT, but anyone who had a pulse in the late 2000&amp;rsquo;s has most likely heard their work.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
