<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 22:13:38 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>📲 Scope Creep and Personal Projects</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 22:13:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</guid>
      <description>Some viewers (especially programmers) may find the following image disturbing:
 Charitably, software gore
  Ouch. Is that Python or Javascript? And do I spy inline CSS styling? To quote The Talking Heads, &amp;ldquo;How did I get here?&amp;quot; After all, no one ever sets out to write bad code. While bad code can result from laziness or inexperience, I want to spend this article discussing a third source: Scope Creep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏙️ Is Nagoya Boring?</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 19:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</guid>
      <description>Recently, it seems like everyone I talk to is either visiting or returning from Japan. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just my observation - according to multiple sources, Japan&amp;rsquo;s post-covid tourism numbers are through the roof. While many plan their trips around the glitz and glamor of Tokyo or the rich culture of Kyoto, there&amp;rsquo;s another city that I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to see on any itinerary - Nagoya.
Despite being it&amp;rsquo;s third largest metro area, Nagoya is nationally renowned as &amp;ldquo;Japan&amp;rsquo;s most boring city&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>☕ Introducing CafeMatrix</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cafematrix/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 21:55:31 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cafematrix/</guid>
      <description>The internet has undoubtedly anxiously awaited this next installment of my personal blog. Having revolutionized the spheres of architecture and education alike, what worlds are left to conquer? The answer is the flashy, cutthroat realm of restaurant ranking. A world that as of December 28, 2024, will never be the same. Introducing the new, paradigm-shifting CafeMatrix!
Note: please read the above paragraph with a heavy dose of sarcasm
The Problem  Sweet Eugene&amp;rsquo;s (image from Yelp)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🚝 Exploring Las Colinas&#39; Mothballed Monorail</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 16:32:24 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</guid>
      <description>Sign at the entrance of the APT
  On the surface, Dallas looks like just another cookie-cutter commuter city. Compared to Austin&amp;rsquo;s booming tech industry and laid-back vibe, Dallas&#39; historic hyperfocus on sprawling office parks has always felt a bit clinical. But the combination of this all-work all-the-time culture and a early 80&amp;rsquo;s real-estate boom led to some crazy planning experiments, and none were as crazy as the Irving&amp;rsquo;s Las Colinas district.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Personal Projects and Giving Up (Echo-Matic Deluxe Update)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 15:39:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</guid>
      <description>Personal projects often feel like a weird limbo between work and play. Starting a project motivated by nothing but passion and a willingness to learn is great. Even if the initial enthusiasm fades, it&amp;rsquo;s still worth it to power through. A finished project is often its own satisfaction. But when all personal interest in the project evaporates, even the most simple tasks become tedious. Every time I think about my gutted Marantz tape deck project, I find myself caring less and less.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Japan&#39;s Early-2000&#39;s Architectural Nostalgia</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 01:00:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</guid>
      <description>The architectural definition of &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;1 has always been a moving target. Every year, once &amp;ldquo;stylistically cutting-edge&amp;rdquo; buildings slip into the realm of &amp;ldquo;dated&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cliche&amp;rdquo;. And the other day, I finally stumbled on across a building that proved this point. Nagoya&amp;rsquo;s Sasashima-Ribu station is totally representative of a particular architectural style; one that, at the time of it&amp;rsquo;s construction, was synonymous with &amp;ldquo;modern architecture&amp;rdquo;. But a quarter of a century has separated innovation from trend, revealing a slew of early 2000&amp;rsquo;s quintessential quirks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Japan&#39;s Most Iconic Model Cars Come Out Of Vending Machines</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 01:00:15 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</guid>
      <description>Remember those 25-cent gumball machines? The ones where you could trade a quarter for a gumball older than the dotcom crash? Imagine that, but instead of a chunk of crusty candy, you win a random 1/64th scale model car. That&amp;rsquo;s essentially Gachapon!
 Bandai Namco&amp;rsquo;s toy vending machines are addictively simple. Insert cash (1), twist dial (2), and collect model (3). Since the 1970&amp;rsquo;s, Gachapon machines have dispensed billions of anime figurines, sushi keychains, and (most notably), tiny scale vehicles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏆 Battery Recycling: The Dark Side of an All-EV Future (2nd place, Problems Worth Solving Competition 2023)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 17:30:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;ve got to start with the customer experience and work back toward the technology, not the other way around. ~ Steve Jobs
 Last weekend I had the opportunity to participate in Problems Worth Solving: Texas A&amp;amp;M&amp;rsquo;s first and only entrepreneurship competition that outright bans solutions.
Great businesses arise from an intimate understanding of your customers&#39; needs. PWS emphasizes this critical step of entrepreneurship by focusing entrepreneurs on the problem, not the solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A sane mini-tutorial for the Jenkins Javascript API</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jenkinsapi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 14:51:34 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jenkinsapi/</guid>
      <description>Holy moly, the Jenkins documentation is bad. At the very least, it isn&amp;rsquo;t very user-friendly, especially for beginners. For someone who has little-to-no experience in web development, doing something as simple as getting some job data from a Node program is the equivalent of pulling teeth. After spending hours in rabbit holes, I finally stumbled on a configuration that works. This mini-writeup will hopefully help those webdev-challenged folks such as myself in the quest for Jenkins API usage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boss Pedal Switching Issues? Try This! (Boss GE-7 Modding)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 15:06:31 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</guid>
      <description>Post-Mod GE-7
  The Mod If you just want to skip to the fix, head to this section.
At the advice of Brian Wampler, I caved and bought a minty used Boss GE-7. Imagine my surprise after moving any of the EQ sliders introduced very noticeable noise! How could you, Boss? Apparently, when the GE-7 was first designed, battery life and price point were more important considerations than audio fidelity.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
