<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 13:28:52 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🏆 MyMirror: a Google-integrated Smart Mirror</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 13:28:52 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</guid>
      <description>Note: More information about myMirror can be found on the project&amp;rsquo;s devpost. Check there for other peoples&amp;rsquo; contributions!
Why myMirror? When I wake up in the morning, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot I know I probably should do. For example, I should probably prepare for the day ahead by checking the weather and my daily calendar. But often times, I just don&amp;rsquo;t. For situations like this, myMirror is here to help.
myMirror solves the above dilemma by integrating this crucial information into your everyday bathroom mirror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spelling Test Auto-Grader for Catch Up and Read</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 18:21:31 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Automation is good, so long as you know exactly where to put the machine.&amp;rdquo;
~ Eliyahu Goldratt
 One perk of being a programmer is my ability to automate boring, repetitive tasks I do daily. But what&amp;rsquo;s even more rewarding is the opportunity to help non-programmers with their data analysis drudgery. Such is the case with this project.
The Problem The problem in question is that of third-grade spelling tests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional CD Crafting with CDRDAO</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 13:55:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</guid>
      <description>All digital music listeners are equal. Acquisition is painless. Taste is irrelevant. It is pointless to boast about your iTunes collection, or the quality of your playlists on a streaming service. Music became data, one more set of 1&amp;rsquo;s and 0&amp;rsquo;s lurking in your hard drive, invisible to see and impossible to touch. Nothing is less cool than data. ~ David Sax
 Physical media is back. vinyl and cassette sales are through the roof, and why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t they be?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethan Cope, Briefly</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/aboutme/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 13:58:37 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/aboutme/</guid>
      <description>Hi! I&amp;rsquo;m Ethan Cope, an electrical engineer, multi-instrumentalist, and mac-and-cheese connoisseur.
I currently live in College Station, Texas, where I study electrical engineering and mix live audio.
This site is intended to capture the life cycles of my many side-projects. Most of these projects lie somewhere on the broad spectrum of engineering, from open source software to album reviews to DIY electronics.
So why am I documenting my projects in excruciating detail?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Echo-Matic Deluxe (Part 1): Marantz-based DIY Tape Echo</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 13:07:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</guid>
      <description>Back in 2019, I saw the influential space-rock group Wand live. It was an amazing set of mostly new tunes, but I was a tad distracted by their lead guitarist. He was fiddling with a battered green box for the whole set, and doing so sent his guitar part soaring over the rest of the band in the most atmospheric, gooey wash imaginable. This was my first introduction to the weird, wonderful world of tape echo, and I wanted one!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buswarn: RasPi-based Transit Bus Tracking</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 12:53:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</guid>
      <description>Public transportation is like a magnifying glass that shows you civilization up close. ~ Chris Gethard
 What is Buswarn? During the COVID year, I moved off-campus. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize at the time, but my only lifeline to my in-person classes, study rooms, and meals would be the Texas A&amp;amp;M Bus Transit System. Problems manifested themselves quickly. Buses ran at seemingly random intervals, and the website that displayed the schedule often had errors rendering on my mobile phone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Hugo</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/about-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/about-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Hugo is the world’s fastest framework for building websites. It is written in Go.
It makes use of a variety of open source projects including:
 https://github.com/russross/blackfriday https://github.com/alecthomas/chroma https://github.com/muesli/smartcrop https://github.com/spf13/cobra https://github.com/spf13/viper  Learn more and contribute on GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
