<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>embeddedSystems on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/embeddedsystems/</link>
    <description>Recent content in embeddedSystems on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 18:52:38 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/embeddedsystems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🍅⏰ Using the Pomodoro Technique to make a Pomodoro Timer (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pomodorotimer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 18:52:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pomodorotimer/</guid>
      <description>first prototype!
  Using the Pomodoro Technique to make a Pomodoro Timer (Part 1) A famous Henry Ford quote goes: &amp;ldquo;Nothing is particularly hard, if you divide it into small [enough] jobs&amp;rdquo;. One popular way to practically implement this advice is something called the &amp;ldquo;Pomodoro Technique&amp;rdquo;. 1
The Pomodoro Technique aims to divide the day into bite-sized, productive time chunks. The idea is to set some kind of timer for 25 minutes before you start working.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>💡 SignalBox: DIY Connected Lanterns with MQTT, Adafruit Feather</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 19:04:34 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</guid>
      <description>Faced with the tradition of family Christmas gift giving, I was thoroughly stumped. I knew I wanted to do something maker-related: I&amp;rsquo;m the only engineer in the family, which tends to amplify the wow factor of any techncal projects :)
After my fallback plan (a Chemex coffee maker) fell through, I knew I had to build these!
 the finished product!
  These are long-distance friendship lanterns. The idea is, sometimes you want to let a distant friend or family member know that you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of them, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily want to shoot them a text.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buswarn: RasPi-based Transit Bus Tracking</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 12:53:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</guid>
      <description>Public transportation is like a magnifying glass that shows you civilization up close. ~ Chris Gethard
 What is Buswarn? During the COVID year, I moved off-campus. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize at the time, but my only lifeline to my in-person classes, study rooms, and meals would be the Texas A&amp;amp;M Bus Transit System. Problems manifested themselves quickly. Buses ran at seemingly random intervals, and the website that displayed the schedule often had errors rendering on my mobile phone.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
