<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 13:55:04 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Professional CD Crafting with CDRDAO</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 13:55:04 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</guid>
      <description>All digital music listeners are equal. Acquisition is painless. Taste is irrelevant. It is pointless to boast about your iTunes collection, or the quality of your playlists on a streaming service. Music became data, one more set of 1&amp;rsquo;s and 0&amp;rsquo;s lurking in your hard drive, invisible to see and impossible to touch. Nothing is less cool than data. ~ David Sax&#xA;Physical media is back. vinyl and cassette sales are through the roof, and why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t they be?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Buswarn: RasPi-based Transit Bus Tracking</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 12:53:34 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</guid>
      <description>Public transportation is like a magnifying glass that shows you civilization up close. ~ Chris Gethard&#xA;What is Buswarn? During the COVID year, I moved off-campus. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize at the time, but my only lifeline to my in-person classes, study rooms, and meals would be the Texas A&amp;amp;M Bus Transit System. Problems manifested themselves quickly. Buses ran at seemingly random intervals, and the website that displayed the schedule often had errors rendering on my mobile phone.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
