<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>audio on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/audio/</link>
    <description>Recent content in audio on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 18:54:22 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/audio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🎧 Why I replaced Spotify with a Playstation Portable for a month</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 18:54:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with my previous essay, you know I have mixed feelings on music streaming. Spotify, with its algorithmic recommendations and &amp;ldquo;gamification&amp;rdquo; of listening hours, seems purpose-built for constant, mindless music consumption. I was sick of it. Would I enjoy music more if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the Spotify ecosystem at all? This October, I set out to answer this question - the hard way. I blocked Spotify for the whole month and moved my music over to&amp;hellip; A Playstation Portable!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🎶Losing Focus: Some Thoughts on the State of Music Streaming</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 09:13:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</guid>
      <description>When Steve Jobs first announced the iPhone in 2007, the reception was far from glowing. Compared to cell phones of the time, the iPhone made a lot of confusing design decisions. Keyboard loyalists decried the lack of physical buttons, and the extra features like email or internet were seen as wasteful or pointless. Who would really want to carry a computer in their pocket?
I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone is asking this in 2025.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏎️ What Genre is Mario Kart Music?</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mariokartmusic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 18:20:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mariokartmusic/</guid>
      <description>Killer debut album cover for Casiopea! (image credit)
  Grab a pair of headphones, because this article has a soundtrack! Check out the first song in this Youtube playlist: does it remind you of anything?
 hint hint (image credit)
  If your formative years were later than 1990, your first thought was likely &amp;ldquo;Mario Kart&amp;rdquo;. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be alone - more and more people seem to be finding (and even writing!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Personal Projects and Giving Up (Echo-Matic Deluxe Update)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 15:39:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</guid>
      <description>Personal projects often feel like a weird limbo between work and play. Starting a project motivated by nothing but passion and a willingness to learn is great. Even if the initial enthusiasm fades, it&amp;rsquo;s still worth it to power through. A finished project is often its own satisfaction. But when all personal interest in the project evaporates, even the most simple tasks become tedious. Every time I think about my gutted Marantz tape deck project, I find myself caring less and less.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boss Pedal Switching Issues? Try This! (Boss GE-7 Modding)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 15:06:31 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</guid>
      <description>Post-Mod GE-7
  The Mod If you just want to skip to the fix, head to this section.
At the advice of Brian Wampler, I caved and bought a minty used Boss GE-7. Imagine my surprise after moving any of the EQ sliders introduced very noticeable noise! How could you, Boss? Apparently, when the GE-7 was first designed, battery life and price point were more important considerations than audio fidelity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MGMT&#39;s Anti-Breakout Album: Congratulations</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 10:20:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</guid>
      <description>We are absolutely dead serious about music-making, and that’s what we want people to understand, that there’s no joke in it. We’re not intentionally trying to f*ck with people, we’re actually making this music that we love and we want people to hear it.1 ~ Ben Goldwasser
 You may not be familiar with MGMT, but anyone who had a pulse in the late 2000&amp;rsquo;s has most likely heard their work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional CD Crafting with CDRDAO</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 13:55:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</guid>
      <description>All digital music listeners are equal. Acquisition is painless. Taste is irrelevant. It is pointless to boast about your iTunes collection, or the quality of your playlists on a streaming service. Music became data, one more set of 1&amp;rsquo;s and 0&amp;rsquo;s lurking in your hard drive, invisible to see and impossible to touch. Nothing is less cool than data. ~ David Sax
 Physical media is back. vinyl and cassette sales are through the roof, and why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t they be?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Echo-Matic Deluxe (Part 1): Marantz-based DIY Tape Echo</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 13:07:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</guid>
      <description>Back in 2019, I saw the influential space-rock group Wand live. It was an amazing set of mostly new tunes, but I was a tad distracted by their lead guitarist. He was fiddling with a battered green box for the whole set, and doing so sent his guitar part soaring over the rest of the band in the most atmospheric, gooey wash imaginable. This was my first introduction to the weird, wonderful world of tape echo, and I wanted one!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
