<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Transportation on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/transportation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Transportation on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 16:32:24 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/transportation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🚝 Exploring Las Colinas&#39; Mothballed Monorail</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 16:32:24 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</guid>
      <description>Sign at the entrance of the APT&#xA;On the surface, Dallas looks like just another cookie-cutter commuter city. Compared to Austin&amp;rsquo;s booming tech industry and laid-back vibe, Dallas&amp;rsquo; historic hyperfocus on sprawling office parks has always felt a bit clinical. But the combination of this all-work all-the-time culture and a early 80&amp;rsquo;s real-estate boom led to some crazy planning experiments, and none were as crazy as the Irving&amp;rsquo;s Las Colinas community.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Japan&#39;s Most Iconic Model Cars Come Out Of Vending Machines</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 01:00:15 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</guid>
      <description>Remember those 25-cent gumball machines? The ones where you could trade a quarter for a gumball older than the dotcom crash? Imagine that, but instead of a chunk of crusty candy, you win a random 1/64th scale model car. That&amp;rsquo;s essentially Gachapon!&#xA;Bandai Namco&amp;rsquo;s toy vending machines are addictively simple. Insert cash (1), twist dial (2), and collect model (3). Since the 1970&amp;rsquo;s, Gachapon machines have dispensed billions of anime figurines, sushi keychains, and (most notably), tiny scale vehicles.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>🏆 Battery Recycling: The Dark Side of an All-EV Future (2nd place, Problems Worth Solving Competition 2023)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 17:30:30 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;ve got to start with the customer experience and work back toward the technology, not the other way around. ~ Steve Jobs&#xA;Last weekend I had the opportunity to participate in Problems Worth Solving: Texas A&amp;amp;M&amp;rsquo;s first and only entrepreneurship competition that outright bans solutions.&#xA;Great businesses arise from an intimate understanding of your customers&amp;rsquo; needs. PWS emphasizes this critical step of entrepreneurship by focusing entrepreneurs on the problem, not the solution.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
