<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>musings on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/musings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in musings on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 09:13:51 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/musings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🎶Losing Focus: Some Thoughts on the State of Music Streaming</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 09:13:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</guid>
      <description>When Steve Jobs first announced the iPhone in 2007, the reception was far from glowing. Compared to cell phones of the time, the iPhone made a lot of confusing design decisions. Keyboard loyalists decried the lack of physical buttons, and the extra features like email or internet were seen as wasteful or pointless. Who would really want to carry a computer in their pocket?
I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone is asking this in 2025.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🚃 Rating Every Train in San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/sftransit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 10:03:08 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/sftransit/</guid>
      <description>As some may know, I moved to Santa Clara about a year ago. But if a non-Californian asks me where I live, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to skip the geography lesson and just say San Francisco. Despite how often I use this line, I recently realized I haven&amp;rsquo;t really explored San Francisco yet.
Sure, I&amp;rsquo;ve driven in for a few concerts - but that&amp;rsquo;s not exploring. Driving is all point-to-point. Pull up to the destination and park in the least sketchy lot you can find.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📲 Scope Creep and Personal Projects</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 22:13:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</guid>
      <description>Some viewers (especially programmers) may find the following image disturbing:
 Charitably, software gore
  Ouch. Is that Python or Javascript? And do I spy inline CSS styling? To quote The Talking Heads, &amp;ldquo;How did I get here?&amp;quot; After all, no one ever sets out to write bad code. While bad code can result from laziness or inexperience, I want to spend this article discussing a third source: Scope Creep.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
