<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>essay on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/essay/</link>
    <description>Recent content in essay on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 11:00:49 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/essay/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🚆 Is DART&#39;s New Transit Line Enough to Save It? (Part 1: Context)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 11:00:49 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept1/</guid>
      <description>Two trains pulling into the Silver Line station at UTD
  Dallas Area Rapid Transit serves over 50 million people a year. And in five months, if even one of Dallas&#39; twelve suburbs vote to leave DART, we could lose it for good. At the same time, DART just linked these disgruntled suburbs with its newest rail line. Is the state-of-the-art Silver Line enough to placate Plano and Co.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🎶Losing Focus: Some Thoughts on the State of Music Streaming</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 09:13:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</guid>
      <description>When Steve Jobs first announced the iPhone in 2007, the reception was far from glowing. Compared to cell phones of the time, the iPhone made a lot of confusing design decisions. Keyboard loyalists decried the lack of physical buttons, and the extra features like email or internet were seen as wasteful or pointless. Who would really want to carry a computer in their pocket?
I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone is asking this in 2025.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
