<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Posts on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
		<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/</link>
		<description>Recent content in Posts on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
		<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 11:00:49 -0800</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
		<item>
			<title>🚆 Is DART&#39;s New Transit Line Enough to Save It? (Part 1: Context)</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept1/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 11:00:49 -0800</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/silverlinept1/</guid>
			<description>Two trains pulling into the Silver Line station at UTD
  Dallas Area Rapid Transit serves over 50 million people a year. And in five months, if even one of Dallas&#39; twelve suburbs vote to leave DART, we could lose it for good. At the same time, DART just linked these disgruntled suburbs with its newest rail line. Is the state-of-the-art Silver Line enough to placate Plano and Co.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="big"><img src="images/silverTrain2SCALED.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Two trains pulling into the Silver Line station at UTD</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Dallas Area Rapid Transit serves over 50 million people a year. And <a href="https://www.governing.com/transportation/voter-revolt-could-reshape-public-transit-in-north-texas">in five months</a>, if even one of Dallas' twelve suburbs vote to leave DART, we could lose it for good. At the same time, DART <em>just</em> linked these disgruntled suburbs with its newest rail line. Is the state-of-the-art Silver Line enough to placate Plano and Co. - and thereby save DART as we know it?
Join me in this two-part article as I review the Silver Line, and why it&rsquo;s a critical inflection point for Dallas transit.</p>
<h2 id="the-origins-of-dart">The Origins of DART</h2>
<p>Today, no one would argue that DART is efficient. But was it always this way?
To find out, let&rsquo;s take a look at the unique problem DART had to solve.
By the 90&rsquo;s, millions and millions of Dallasites were commuting downtown every day.
Dallas knew that if growth trends continued, rail transit would be the only long-term solution.
But Dallas is really, really spread out. However you sliced it, people were going to be too far from train stations.</p>
<figure><img src="images/dartToday.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>DART&rsquo;s current extent, circa December 2025 (<a href="https://dartorgcmsblob.dart.org/prod/docs/default-source/dart-maps/dart-current-and-future-services-map.pdf?sfvrsn=76b4ab16_6">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>To tackle this problem, DART designed their rail lines around an untested but promising &ldquo;Park-and-Ride&rdquo; model.
The idea was that commuters would drive their own cars to the closest DART station, park there, and take the train downtown.
Some Park-and-Rides have seen success in the US, <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> but nothing of this scale had ever been attempted.
Undeterred, DART began scooping up abandoned freight rail lines (for pennies on the dollar) and converting them to passenger rail. By 1996, DART unveiled its first passenger rail lines in Dallas.</p>
<figure><img src="images/dartEvolution.gif"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Really cool animation of DART&rsquo;s evolution (not including the Silver Line) (<a href="https://transitmap.net/dart-timeline-mcelroy/">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="darts-fatal-flaw">Dart&rsquo;s Fatal Flaw</h2>
<p>DART was built around two assumptions: that commuters would always need to get downtown, and that increasing freeway traffic would soon make these trips untenable.
But even before DART started construction, these assumptions had begun to unravel.
Instead of growing, downtowns across the U.S. declined as companies relocated to suburban &ldquo;corporate campuses&rdquo;.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>
The Internet and COVID only accelerated this trend, and an increasing number of companies today are eschewing office space altogether.
As a result, commuter congestion in Dallas never hit the critical mass planners were expecting.
Without this anticipated traffic apocalypse, DART park-and-ride wasn&rsquo;t any faster than driving.</p>
<figure><img src="images/dartDowntown.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Because of this trendy &ldquo;transit mall&rdquo;, DART has to crawl through Downtown. (<a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g55711-d10537055-Reviews-DART_Rail_System-Dallas_Texas.html">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The failure of park-and-ride kneecapped DART&rsquo;s usefulness in other areas, too.
It&rsquo;s common sense to put stations in high-density, walkable locations.
Main Street Richardson and Dallas' historic Chinatown fit this description, and both have the Red Line at their front door.
But in both cases, the closest stations are a ~20 minute walk away! <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>
This decision made sense at the time. Stations in lower-density areas could fit more commuters into larger parking lots.
But today, these useless stations are just baggage from DART&rsquo;s well-meaning but misguided Park-and-Ride obsession.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/chinaTownRailSCALED.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/richardsonRailSCALED.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>DART to Chinatown - 17 minute walk</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>DART to Main Street Richardson - 18 minute walk</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The way I see it, 1990&rsquo;s DART was future-proof up until the future changed.
Designed around an obsolete regional migration pattern, DART now has a dilemma.
Most existing stations are in low-density locations, no one works downtown, and everyone with a car still drives to work.
So how can DART provide effective transit, both for now and the future?
Stay tuned for Part 2, where I&rsquo;ll talk about how the Silver Line addresses these concerns and more!</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Chicago&rsquo;s <a href="https://subwaynut.com/chicago/yellow_line/index.php">Skokie Swift</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This trend also birthed Irving&rsquo;s ill-fated APT monorail, <a href="/posts/irvingapt/">which I wrote about here</a>!&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Also bear in mind - Dallas had <a href="https://www.extremeweatherwatch.com/cities/dallas/yearly-days-of-90-degrees">116 days over 90 F (32 C)</a> last year.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🎧 Why I replaced Spotify with a Playstation Portable for a month</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 18:54:22 -0700</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</guid>
			<description>If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with my previous essay, you know I have mixed feelings on music streaming. Spotify, with its algorithmic recommendations and &amp;ldquo;gamification&amp;rdquo; of listening hours, seems purpose-built for constant, mindless music consumption. I was sick of it. Would I enjoy music more if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the Spotify ecosystem at all? This October, I set out to answer this question - the hard way. I blocked Spotify for the whole month and moved my music over to&amp;hellip; A Playstation Portable!</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re familiar with <a href="/posts/essay1streamingservices/">my previous essay</a>, you know I have mixed feelings on music streaming. Spotify, with its algorithmic recommendations and <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/how-to-boost-spotify-listening-hours-spotify-wrapped/">&ldquo;gamification&rdquo; of listening hours</a>, seems purpose-built for constant, mindless music consumption. I was sick of it. Would I enjoy music more if I wasn&rsquo;t in the Spotify ecosystem at all? This October, I set out to answer this question - the hard way. I blocked Spotify for the whole month and moved my music over to&hellip; A Playstation Portable!</p>
<figure class="big"><img src="images/psp.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>A PSP 3000, similar to the one used for this article. (<a href="https://consolevariations.com/database/sony-psp-x000-series?activeSortLabel=rarity_score&amp;order=asc">image source</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-setup">The Setup</h2>
<p>If you resonated with at least some of my first paragraph, your next question is likely &ldquo;Why a PSP?&rdquo;. Many don&rsquo;t know this, but the PSP isn&rsquo;t just a game console - it was also a .mp3 player!
This was a weird time for Sony.
Once the top dogs in the portable tape and CD player markets, Sony was seeing the iPod eat away their longstanding dominance.
But could your iPod play Gran Turismo? Or God of War, or Metal Gear Solid?
That was the PSP pitch: one device to <a href="https://www.cnet.com/culture/psp-no-one-trick-pony/">replace your Game Boy, your MP3 player, even your DVD player</a>!</p>
<p>The PSP was Sony at its innovative peak - my expectations for sound quality and user experience were high.
Plus I had one lying around!
With the .mp3 player chosen, the next challenge was loading my tunes onto the device.</p>
<figure><img src="images/UMD.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Sony developed an adorably small custom disk just for the PSP! It took some crazy engineering to cram a fully functional optical drive into a portable device! (<a href="https://www.theverge.com/2011/11/11/2553875/ps-vita-umd-passport-announcement-release-date">image source</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-transition">The Transition</h2>
<p>How hard was it to load music onto to a PSP? It&rsquo;s definitely not as seamless as the iTunes / iPod ecosystem I grew up with. First off, the PSP uses a proprietary memory stick - you&rsquo;ll need a third-party <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Funturbo-MagicGate-Playstation-Portable-Handycam/dp/B07F68FCHD">microSD &lt;&gt; memory stick adapter</a> to hook the card up to a modern PC. There&rsquo;s another catch - many modern audio file formats are <a href="https://manuals.playstation.net/document//en/psp/current/music/filetypes.html">unsupported by the PSP</a>. If your music collection is a mixture of CDs, vinyl, and .wav files from Bandcamp, there&rsquo;s more work to be done to load these up.</p>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/microSDAdapter.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>One of the many micro-SD adapters for the PSP. (<a href="https://www.skroutz.gr/s/10230007/Memory-Stick-Pro-Duo-Adapter-to-micro-SD-Metatropeas-male-se-female-1tmch.html">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><em>Note - if you don&rsquo;t care about converting between audio formats, (Hi, Mom!) feel free to skip to the next section.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>CDs: Probably the easiest to convert. Nearly every laptop with a disc drive can (legally!) copy your CD library to a variety of file formats. I&rsquo;ve had good luck with iTunes, which even extracts track and album names. Some standalone CD players also have this functionality. I used my roommate&rsquo;s Sony CDP-500, but regretted the device&rsquo;s 176 kb bitrate which sounded super tinny. I&rsquo;d stick with iTunes or something!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Vinyl: This one is tough. Music on vinyl is analog, meaning it&rsquo;s extra work to convert to a computer-readable file. To start, you&rsquo;ll need to play the whole album end-to-end, and record the record player&rsquo;s audio output on your laptop.
Some record players (see: AT-LP120) hook up directly to your laptop over USB, letting you record with software like Audacity.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>
Once done, you&rsquo;ll have one ~20-minute audio file for each side of the album. From here, It&rsquo;s on you to <a href="https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/label_tracks.html">split it into tracks</a> and export them as individual songs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Other digital files: Open Source Software to the rescue! <a href="https://www.ffmpeg.org/">FFMPEG</a> is a completely free library to convert from nearly any encoding to .MP3. I wrote a quick script to iterate through a folder, converting each song to .MP3 and numbering them correctly - try it out!</p>
</li>
</ul>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>#NOTE: need to set paths and extension of source file here
path=&quot;/mnt/c/Users/ethan/Music/Ryo Fukui/SCENERY&quot;
extension=&quot;flac&quot;
echo converting files in &quot;$path&quot; from &quot;$extension&quot; to mp3.

for songpath in &quot;$path&quot;/*; do
	# https://kevinboone.me/clh_tags.html
    # great resource for mp3 tagging 
	# update - need to quote variables in bash. i keep forgetting!
	#echo $(ffprobe -i $song 2&gt;&amp;1 | grep track*)

	# basename command makes this a lot easier! taking slashdot out of filename
	song=&quot;$(basename &quot;$songpath&quot;)&quot;

	# extract track number from metadata, add leading zero
	tracknum=$(ffprobe -i &quot;$songpath&quot; 2&gt;&amp;1 | grep track* | awk '{ print $3}')
	if [[ ${#tracknum} -eq &quot;1&quot; ]]; then
		tracknum=0&quot;$tracknum&quot;
	fi
	echo $tracknum

	#some songs already have track number baked into the song title
	#for this, just set track number to empty string
	#tracknum=&quot;&quot;

	sourcefile=&quot;${path}/${song}&quot;
	destfile=&quot;${path}/${tracknum} ${song%%&quot;$extension&quot;}mp3&quot;
	echo Creating: $destfile
	#echo &quot;ffmpeg -i ${sourcefile} -acodec libmp3lame -b:a 320k ${destfile}&quot;
	ffmpeg -i &quot;${sourcefile}&quot; -acodec libmp3lame -b:a 320k &quot;${destfile}&quot;
done

</code></pre><p>Once you&rsquo;ve got your tracks, it&rsquo;s relatively simple. Put all of the songs in a folder named after the album title, the put these albums in another folder named after the artist. Dump these artist folders into <code>[MUSIC]</code> folder on the microSD, pop it into your PSP and voila! You&rsquo;ve got 32 gigs of songs in your pocket!</p>
<h2 id="jamming-like-its-2005">Jamming like it&rsquo;s 2005</h2>
<p>First and foremost, the PSP is a game console. As a result, there are some quirks that make it a bit of a pain to use as a .mp3 player.</p>
<ol>
<li>There are no dedicated play / pause buttons.</li>
<li>Volume controls are tiny, and nearly impossible to adjust from your pocket.</li>
<li>On the other hand the track skip buttons are massive, and frustratingly easy to fat-finger. Sony attempts to mitigate this with the &ldquo;input lock&rdquo; switch, preventing any button presses from registering on the PSP.
But even this is clunky.</li>
<li>That same input lock switch is shared with the power switch, meaning there&rsquo;s a 50/50 chance you accidentally reboot your PSP instead of cranking up the tunes.</li>
</ol>
<figure><img src="images/powerHoldSwitch.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>If the PSP is already in input lock (setting C) and you try to unlock (re-centering the switch) you&rsquo;ll probably reboot it by accident (setting A). From the <a href="https://archive.org/details/sony-psp-3000/page/n9/mode/2up">PSP user&rsquo;s manual.</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Sound quality wasn&rsquo;t life-changing. Frequency response was flat and consistent through my Moondrop Kato IEMs. High-end clarity left the most to be desired, though. It&rsquo;s easy to point the finger at the .mp3 encoding - after all, these files were only 44100 kHz @ 320 kb/s. Since these same files sounded fine on my laptop, I suspect the PSP&rsquo;s audio chip. Sony developed a bunch of custom chips for the PSP, including a GPU (CXD1876) and CPU (CXD2962). But there&rsquo;s no Sony secret-sauce for audio; they instead opted for an off-the-shelf Wolfson codec.</p>
<figure><img src="images/wolfsonCodec.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Datasheet block diagram for the Wolfson Codec found in the PSP3000 (<a href="https://www.alldatasheet.com/datasheet-pdf/download/837353/WOLFSON/WM8973L.html">image source</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The WM8973G (<a href="https://www.alldatasheet.com/datasheet-pdf/download/837353/WOLFSON/WM8973L.html">datasheet</a>) pitches itself as a &ldquo;low-power integrated codec&rdquo; and&hellip; yeah. Trade-offs were definitely made with sound quality here. I can&rsquo;t say I&rsquo;m surprised. The PSP was, first and foremost, a game console. Gamers likely wouldn&rsquo;t have valued higher quality audio if it killed their battery life. Nowadays we&rsquo;re spoiled by <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/News/8448/apple-audio-adapter-teardown">tiny DACs</a> that far outperform audiophile equipment from twenty years ago. Overall, the PSP sound quality isn&rsquo;t great, but to my ears it&rsquo;s definitely enough for portable listening.</p>
<figure><img src="images/pspSystemArchitecture.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>If you&rsquo;re interested in how Sony put the PSP together, Rodrigo Copetti put together a <a href="https://www.copetti.org/writings/consoles/playstation-portable/">masterclass on the subject</a>. Vector Processing, Memory Mapping, Silicon part numbers - no stone went unturned. Highly recommend!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Side note - an original goal for this article was to upgrade the PSP&rsquo;s audio capability like I did for the <a href="/posts/ge7/">Boss GE-7 a few years ago</a> I was going to blue-wire a newer codec like the <a href="https://www.ti.com/product/TAC5112">TAC5112</a> and A/B test the audio performance. Unfortunately I couldn&rsquo;t find any newer devices that are pin-compatible with the Wolfson codec - if anyone has ideas I&rsquo;d be happy to hear them though!</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Dang, Ethan! Loading songs are a pain, it doesn&rsquo;t sound great, and the user interface is clunky at best. Sounds like you hated this month with the PSP. Nope! In fact, this month away from Spotify <em>utterly changed</em> the way I listen to music. I think it boils down to this.</p>
<p>When you stream music, the music itself is almost never the focus. Most people, myself included, seem to use Spotify as a &ldquo;background noise generator&rdquo;. We need a constant stream of non-intrusive <em>something</em>, never really caring what that something is.</p>
<p>But with the PSP, that all changes. A .mp3 player won&rsquo;t force-feed you the same 50 songs until you&rsquo;ve listened them to death. You couldn&rsquo;t doomscroll on a .mp3 player if you tried. These aren&rsquo;t limitations, they&rsquo;re opportunities! Using a .mp3 player forces you to engage with the music, because there&rsquo;s nothing else you CAN be doing! Something funny happened while writing this article. As far as hours listened, I probably heard less music this October. But without Spotify, I definitely <em>listened</em> to more.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>There have been some debates of late about whether Audacity is spyware. Not going to take a stance here, but since it&rsquo;s the only processing software I&rsquo;m fluent with I&rsquo;m going to stick with it for now. <a href="https://github.com/audacity/audacity">Form your own opinion from the public git repo here:</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🍅⏰ Using the Pomodoro Technique to make a Pomodoro Timer (Part 1)</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pomodorotimer/</link>
			<pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 18:52:38 -0700</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pomodorotimer/</guid>
			<description>first prototype!
  Using the Pomodoro Technique to make a Pomodoro Timer (Part 1) A famous Henry Ford quote goes: &amp;ldquo;Nothing is particularly hard, if you divide it into small [enough] jobs&amp;rdquo;. One popular way to practically implement this advice is something called the &amp;ldquo;Pomodoro Technique&amp;rdquo;. 1
The Pomodoro Technique aims to divide the day into bite-sized, productive time chunks. The idea is to set some kind of timer for 25 minutes before you start working.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="images/prototype.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>first prototype!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="using-the-pomodoro-technique-to-make-a-pomodoro-timer-part-1">Using the Pomodoro Technique to make a Pomodoro Timer (Part 1)</h3>
<p>A famous Henry Ford quote goes: &ldquo;Nothing is particularly hard, if you divide it into small [enough] jobs&rdquo;.
One popular way to practically implement this advice is something called the &ldquo;Pomodoro Technique&rdquo;. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p>The Pomodoro Technique aims to divide the day into bite-sized, productive time chunks.
The idea is to set some kind of timer for 25 minutes before you start working. Once you start work, (i.e. while the timer is running) you can&rsquo;t check your email, look at your phone, or otherwise get distracted.
Don&rsquo;t worry! At the end of those 25 minutes, you&rsquo;ll take a 5 minute break where you can do all of those things. Then it&rsquo;s time to get started on the next 25 minute chunk.</p>
<figure><img src="images/pomodoroExplanation.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>A pictorial explanation of the pomodoro timer. <a href="https://www.educba.com/pomodoro-technique/">image credit</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Intrigued, I wanted to test whether the pomodoro method actually worked.
But I still needed a benchmark project to apply this method to. What to do?
Then suddenly came a bolt of inspiration. What if I used the pomodoro technique&hellip; <em><strong>to make a pomodoro timer?</strong></em></p>
<p>While this may seem less ambitious than some of my <a href="/posts/thinking-of-you/">previous embedded projects</a>, I think it may turn out to be harder.
For firmware, I wanted to break out of the walled garden of Arduino and use a real microcontroller this time around.
More than that, I wanted this to be my first time taking a DIY design from concept all the way to production. <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>
This means firmware and prototyping (this article, part 1), but also PCB design and assembly (next article, part 2)
I&rsquo;ve done each of these steps in isolation, but combining them together in one project will be the real challenge!</p>
<p>Finally, since I used a (website-based) pomodoro timer throughout development, I&rsquo;ll break down how using this technique helped this project move along. Let&rsquo;s get started!</p>
<h2 id="the-concept">The Concept</h2>
<p>There isn&rsquo;t much that goes into a pomodoro timer. You just need a way to visualize how much time you have left, and a way to reset the timer once it goes off.
For visualization, I decided to use five LEDs to show the status of the timer. Each LED maps to 5 minutes of the timer&rsquo;s period. So if 10 minutes remain, 2/5 LEDs will be lit. The microcontroller will count down from 25 minutes, turning off each LED in sequence until 25 minutes have passed and all LEDs are off. I made a quick state diagram to clarify below.</p>
<figure><img src="images/pomodoroStateDiagram.png"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>See the LEDs with the red outline? The LED at the end of the sequence is what I call the &ldquo;active LED&rdquo;. I wanted these to slowly pulse to add some extra flair to the project. This ended up having some pretty serious implications on implementation. more on that later&hellip;</p>
<p>Finally, how to reset the timer? After kicking around a few ideas (slider with inductive encoding? Adapting a motorized fader from a mixing board?), I settled with the humble button. No need to make more trouble for myself!</p>
<p>What would the timer look like? My original idea was to make it in the same form factor as an expansion card slot on the <a href="">Framework Laptop</a>. It would be cool to always have access to a pomodoro timer, but I landed on a different idea later in development. But I&rsquo;m saving that as a secret for part 2 ;)</p>
<h2 id="the-execution">The Execution</h2>
<p><em>Note: Skip to the conclusion if you don&rsquo;t care about programming / implementation specifics!</em></p>
<p>Like I mentioned, one of my goals was to use a real MCU. Picking an MCU is no easy feat. I settled on TI&rsquo;s MSPM0G3507 - I happened to have a few lying around and wanted to see if CCS&rsquo;s quirkiness carried over to the new VSCode (technically Theia) CCS IDE.</p>
<p>One of my biggest gripes with previous-gen (eclipse) CCS was the difficulty of git integration. I always seemed to pollute my repositories with half of an SDK that I didn&rsquo;t need. It looks like this is better in new CCS - following <a href="https://software-dl.ti.com/ccs/esd/documents/sdto_ccs_source-control.html">this &ldquo;list of things to not check in&rdquo;</a> led to a bloat-less repo. CCS&rsquo;s shows its VsCode bones in the super helpful source control tab, too. The jury is still out on whether it will survive a git clone, but for now it seems to be working ok.</p>
<figure><img src="images/newCCS.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>CCS' new, VSCode/Theia coat of paint.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On to the project, where the first thing to implement was the timer logic itself. We set a hardware timer to trigger an interrupt once every second, checking if five minutes have passed. If so, we do a few things:</p>
<ol>
<li>Check to see if the full 25 minutes have passed. If they have, kill the timer.</li>
<li>Turn off the currently active LED</li>
<li>Make the next LED in the sequence the active LED</li>
<li>Continue</li>
</ol>
<p>That&rsquo;s really all there is to it! On the other hand, making the active LED pulsing look pretty was more difficult. Pulse Width Modulation (PWM) is the default way to control LED brightness - but PWM percentage and brightness aren&rsquo;t a linear relationship. 50% duty cycle on the LED is actually closer to 75% of the LED&rsquo;s potential brightness, making changes in LED brightness look &ldquo;one-sided&rdquo; or &ldquo;choppy&rdquo;. As <a href="http://www.pyroelectro.com/tutorials/fading_led_pwm/theory2.html">this blog post maintains</a>, LED brightness is closer to a logarithmic curve than a linear one. I used a quick python script to generate a log_10 table from 0 to 256 (my max PWM period value). One lookup table later, and the LEDs pulsed evenly as intended! The video at time <strong>4:06</strong> shows the difference between compensated and non-compensated brightness values.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1fKH5PU9eck?t=246" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>I was originally going to tie each LED to an individual PWM, but I soon realized there was no need to. The other LEDs don&rsquo;t have to pulse, so they&rsquo;re just set high (100% brightness). If I want to add variable brightness this may have to change, but at this point it&rsquo;s OK. (As a side note, I always seem to forget simple things like enabling interrupts! For this, the <a href="https://dev.ti.com/tirex/explore/node?node=A__AeBsSdJZWfmG963nj3KU1Q__MSPM0-ACADEMY__2f1Egw1__LATEST">M0 academies</a> were really helpful in giving golden reference code and reasoning behind what each line is doing. The <a href="">SDK documentation itself</a> was super helpful too.)</p>
<p>For the physical prototype, I slapped a few LEDs and resistors onto a breadboard left over from college. (Thanks Dr. Silva!) I was tearing my hair out when two of the LEDs didn&rsquo;t work, before I realized that PA10/11 were jumpered to the external debug probe rather than the GPIO breakout on the devkit. <a href="https://www.ti.com/lit/ug/slau873d/slau873d.pdf?ts=1756612576403">Some schematics</a> quickly showed me the error of my ways.</p>
<p>Adding the timer reset button was the final step. Annoyingly, I couldn&rsquo;t find a documented list of interrupt handlers in the SDK. Some kind soul on the e2e forum <a href="https://e2e.ti.com/support/microcontrollers/arm-based-microcontrollers-group/arm-based-microcontrollers/f/arm-based-microcontrollers-forum/1396629/mspm0l1105-digital-input-interrupt-to-wake-device">posted a massive list</a>, but I&rsquo;d appreciate more insight on where these handler methods come from / are defined.</p>
<h2 id="the-conclusion">The Conclusion</h2>
<p>It works! I even used the prototype while writing this article! See the video below, (note that the time is set to 5 seconds per period, not 5 minutes as it would in production).</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JLuG-Xfg7Ic" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>What&rsquo;s the verdict on the pomodoro method? It&rsquo;s helpful, but not for the reason you may have guessed. You see, I have a lot of difficulty in not getting distracted. This timer soon became my favorite way of handling distractions while working - whenever I felt distracted, I would look at the timer and remind myself I only had to focus for a few more minutes. Filing those thoughts away until I was done with the pomodoro period made me work way more efficiently!</p>
<p>The pomodoro helped with one other thing, too. Once I focused on a problem, I often went way over the 25 minute period trying to solve it. I see this is a good thing - why interrupt being in &ldquo;the zone&rdquo; because of some arbitrary time constraint? I was originally going to add some flashing lights to the end of the timer period, but found I worked a lot better when the timer unobtrusively fades out. So in a way, the timer is useful because it forces you to just start something, regardless of how long it takes you to finish.</p>
<p>Overall, I&rsquo;m a fan. What a relief - imagine putting in all of this this effort if I ended up hating it! Next article, I&rsquo;m going to start on my second PCB design ever! You&rsquo;ll hear more about this in part two (coming hopefully before December). See you back here then!</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>The guy who popularized this technique originally used tomato shaped timer, and Pomodoro is just Italian for Tomato. The more you know!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Brutally honest note: last time I tried this, <a href="/posts/echo-matic_special2/">I gave up.</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🏭Why Did My College Campus Look So... Depressing?</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/tamuarch/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 22:05:04 -0700</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/tamuarch/</guid>
			<description>All-star Brutalist Skyline at Texas A&amp;amp;M
  If you went to college in the US, chances are you&amp;rsquo;ve seen a few depressing buildings like these. Often called &amp;ldquo;Brutalist&amp;rdquo; architecture, maybe you also heard rumors that they were built by the Russians or designed to suppress student riots. I&amp;rsquo;ll take a crack at separating fact from fiction today, as I process what made this style so popular, and why public colleges (of all tenants) seemed to fall in love.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="big"><img src="images/cainExt.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>All-star Brutalist Skyline at Texas A&amp;M</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>If you went to college in the US, chances are you&rsquo;ve seen a few depressing buildings like these.
Often called &ldquo;Brutalist&rdquo; architecture, maybe you also heard rumors that they were built by the Russians or <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2024-05-05/did-college-protests-lead-to-brutalist-campus-architecture">designed to suppress student riots</a>.
I&rsquo;ll take a crack at separating fact from fiction today, as I process what made this style so popular, and why public colleges (of all tenants) seemed to fall in love.
And as a bonus, all of the pictures in this article are from my belovedly brutalist alma mater, Texas A&amp;M!</p>
<p><em>Architectural article disclaimer: I have zero formal training in architecture - just a big fan! Please bear with any amateur mistakes here.</em></p>
<h1 id="a-brief-anecdotal-history-of-brutalist-architecture">A Brief, Anecdotal History of Brutalist Architecture</h1>
<p>Let&rsquo;s get that burning question out of the way.
Why was this style so popular? Did people really want their workplaces to be <em>more</em> depressing?
To answer that question, we have to cross the Atlantic (and go back in time). After being relentlessly bombed in World War II, Britain needed to replace a lot of buildings very quickly.
The question was: how?
Previous architectural styles like Art Deco and Beaux-Arts ornamentalism (see the Academic Building, below) were expensive and (by this point) unpopular.
Prewar apartments were also dingy and cramped - think West Side Story brownstones.
An entirely new way of building large-scale, clean housing at a low cost was needed, and fast.</p>
<figure><img src="images/academicBldg.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>TAMU&rsquo;s Beaux-arts / Classical Revival Academic Building (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EHAQHCkruz4">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>British architects Alison and Peter Smithson saw this as an opportunity to try something new.
They observed how low-income neighborhoods often formed tight communities - what if they could foster this style of community in massive, low-cost apartment projects?
To counteract &ldquo;apartment isolation&rdquo;, The Smithsons promised to bring neighborhoods to renters' front doors.
Inspired by fellow architect Le Corbusier&rsquo;s &ldquo;<a href="https://www.architectural-review.com/archive/notopia-archive/notopia-the-fall-of-streets-in-the-sky">Streets in the Sky</a>&rdquo; concept, they gave their projects massive open-air hallways to act as common spaces. Children could play in the &ldquo;street&rdquo; and residents could pass the time on the shared balconies.
Green spaces and fresh air were prioritized, in direct contrast to older, cramped apartment complexes.
Because of these considerations, one architect is quoted &ldquo;<a href="https://municipaldreams.wordpress.com/2013/04/16/the-park-hill-estate-sheffield-streets-in-the-sky/">We didn&rsquo;t think we were &lsquo;Brutalists&rsquo;. We thought we were quite nice guys</a>&rdquo;.
For first few years, Brutalist projects were decently successful!
Unfortunately as buildings started aging, cracks (literal and metaphorical) began to show.</p>
<figure><img src="images/hebExterior.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>TAMU has its own &ldquo;Streets in the Sky&rdquo; thing going, too!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>First off, lofty concepts like &ldquo;streets in the sky&rdquo; didn&rsquo;t pan out. In reality, these dimly-lit, easily accessible hallways attracted vandals and criminals.
Plus, Brutalism&rsquo;s namesake material (<em>&ldquo;beton brut&rdquo;</em>, meaning bare concrete) easily crumbled, causing structural problems that were cost-prohibitive to fix.
There was an underlying cause to these functional failings: Brutalist residential projects were just too optimistic.
New building techniques and public health breakthroughs were supposed to finally solve the housing crisis with &ldquo;bigger and better&rdquo; homes for the masses.
But as time went on, it became obvious that there were <a href="https://www.cnu.org/our-projects/hud-hope-vi">problems endemic to public housing</a> that mere architecture couldn&rsquo;t fix.
Thinking that technology was the only solution created a future that was less Star Trek and more Blade Runner.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>
Now, the buildings of Brutalism remain as a testament to this well-intentioned but ultimately doomed planning philosophy.</p>
<figure><img src="images/exteriorPlaza.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Even outdoor plazas aren&rsquo;t safe from brick and slab concrete!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="images/chemBldg.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>The Chemistry building mixes it up with <em>wood</em> accents on the top floor. Weird!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="brutalist-architecture-on-the-college-campus">Brutalist Architecture on the College Campus</h1>
<p>Nowhere did the tenets of Brutalism apply more than to student housing.
Most students are flexible to minimalist accommodations (read: poor), and are naturally inclined to be social in community spaces.
And as universities soon learned, the style of monolithic, slab concrete worked just as well for offices and lecture halls as it did for dorms.
Low construction costs and heavy government investment in academic research (especially aerospace and defense) ensured that cold war colleges built brutalist.</p>
<p>My alma mater is no exception, and <a href="https://abpa.tamu.edu/getattachment/d341b8a7-7925-46b2-9602-6a10ad79cb13/Overall_Enrollment_Historical.pdf">enrollment history tells the story</a>. In 1965, A&amp;M still had under 10k students on campus - by 1985, that number had more than tripled to 35k! Of course, these students needed new lecture halls, dorm rooms, and dining halls. And as far as I can tell, every new construction from this period had some sort of Brutalist bent.
But it&rsquo;s probably easier to show than tell - let&rsquo;s finish off the article with a short &ldquo;Brutalist Tour of Texas A&amp;M&rdquo;!</p>
<figure><img src="images/blocker.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>TAMU&rsquo;s most depressing building: Blocker</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/blockerPlaque.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/blockerView.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/blockerInterior.jpeg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Blocker building, erected in 1976</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>View of the surrounding area</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Blocker&rsquo;s take on &ldquo;Streets in the Sky&rdquo;</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<figure><img src="images/langfordExteriorfacade.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>If you can believe it, this is the architecture department building!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="images/langfordInterior.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>For what it&rsquo;s worth, I love the Langford building&rsquo;s interior.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>That&rsquo;s a wrap for this article - thanks for sticking around! Next time you visit your home university, you&rsquo;ll know a bit more about why these quirky buildings got built!<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
<figure><img src="images/dallas.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>City hall, or evil lair?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I couldn&rsquo;t find a way to shoehorn this detail into the article, but it&rsquo;s too cool to leave out. When Dallas' Brutalist Dallas City Hall was built (above), it was the pride of the city. Architect I.M. Pei is quoted: <em>&ldquo;When you do a city hall, it has to convey an image of the people, and this had to represent the people of Dallas &hellip; The people I met - rich and poor, powerful and not so powerful - were all very proud of their city. They felt that Dallas was the greatest city there was, and I could not disappoint them.&quot;</em> But a few years later, Dallas City Hall was cast as <a href="https://gov.texas.gov/film/trail/dallas-city-hall">sinister corporation &ldquo;Omni Consumer Products'&rdquo; headquarters</a> in 1982&rsquo;s Robocop. Movies like these and aforementioned Blade Runner definitely helped solidify Brutalism&rsquo;s image as the architecture of monopolistic mega-corporations.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Further reading - it seems like Seoul is having a bit of a <a href="https://www.archdaily.com/869385/korean-curiosity-is-seoul-experiencing-a-neo-brutalist-revival">Neo-Brutalist revival</a>. If I ever make my way out there, I may have to write a part 2 for this article!&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🚫🚆 Writing about everything *but* the trains in Japan</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jptransit/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 19:41:09 -0700</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jptransit/</guid>
			<description>Shonan Monorail (image credit)
  As an engineer, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to visit Japan and not be obsessed with its trains. From record-breaking bullet trains to spaghetti-like subway networks, Japan does trains better than anywhere else I&amp;rsquo;ve been. But even the most train-obsessed nations acknowledge that heavy rail isn&amp;rsquo;t a catch-all solution. So as a bit of a curveball, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this transit post about everything but the trains in Japan.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="big"><img src="images/Shonanmonorail5000.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Shonan Monorail (<a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sh%C5%8Dnan_Monorail">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As an engineer, it&rsquo;s impossible to visit Japan and not be obsessed with its trains. From record-breaking bullet trains to spaghetti-like subway networks, Japan does trains better than anywhere else I&rsquo;ve been.
But even the most train-obsessed nations acknowledge that heavy rail isn&rsquo;t a catch-all solution. So as a bit of a curveball, I&rsquo;m writing this transit post about everything <em>but</em> the trains in Japan.</p>
<h2 id="trams">Trams</h2>
<figure><img src="images/osakaTramRailsBig.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Osaka&rsquo;s Hankai Tram line - it&rsquo;s seen better days</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Right out of the gate, we&rsquo;ll start with something train-adjacent: Trams. These overgrown rails (above) are all that remain of Osaka&rsquo;s once sprawling suburban tram network. In the early 20th century, gas-powered buses could only carry a few people at a time. Short of a real train, trams like these were really the only solution for urban transit. Trams were once <em>everywhere</em> - take a peek at this ~1920s map of Osaka, and try to find a major road <em>without</em> a tram line!</p>
<figure><img src="images/osaka1920sMap.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Part of a 1920&rsquo;s map of Osaka: the black lines in the middle of the roads are trams! (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/papertowns/comments/qkal5d/japan_detailed_map_of_osaka_in_the_1920s/">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Osaka may have had miles of tram lines, but it wouldn&rsquo;t last long.
Buses became more and more efficient, and they didn&rsquo;t require expensive rails or electricity lines like trams did.
As buses continued to grow in popularity, Osaka&rsquo;s (and indeed, Japan&rsquo;s) tram lines began closing for business.
Just like <a href="/posts/sftransit/">San Francisco</a>, the only lines that survived were the ones that couldn&rsquo;t be converted into high-density streets.</p>
<figure><img src="images/osakaTram.png"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>So it was with Osaka&rsquo;s only remaining tram line, the Hankai line. The Hankai doesn&rsquo;t even reach downtown Osaka anymore. Not a problem - most commuters would favor the faster subway lines a stone&rsquo;s throw away. Now, its purpose is more local - connecting the entertainment district of Shinsekai, the ancient Sumiyoshi Taisha shrine, and any requested stops in between.</p>
<p>To me, this is exactly where trams shine. Buses are efficient, but communities don&rsquo;t spring up around bus stops. Conversely, tram lines historically become the backbone of tight-knit &ldquo;streetcar suburbs&rdquo;.
&ldquo;Community&rdquo; may be a tough sell to cash-strapped public transit agencies.
But with smaller cities in Japan (Hiroshima, Fukuoka, Nagasaki) opting to invest further in trams over subways, maybe trams will have their long-delayed resurgence after all.</p>
<figure><img src="images/enodenTram.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Another tram line, the Eno-Den. This line was so popular with tourists it was re-converted to run full-size trains through the resort town of Enoshima.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="monorails">Monorails</h2>
<p>By the 1970s, most people saw trains as dingy, outdated anachronisms. Why travel by rail if a jet can get you there faster, and in style?
However, one form of transit still captured the public&rsquo;s imagination: <em>The Monorail</em>.
At one point, Washington DC and LA were actively considering futuristic monorails for their brand new public transit networks.
The future was now!</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/tokyoMonorail.png" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/maglevVertical.png" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Tokyo&rsquo;s (normal, non-suspended) monorail</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Nagoya&rsquo;s Maglev (though this train technically levitates, making it a zero-rail?)</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>And what&rsquo;s not to like? Monorails are undoubtedly futuristic, and elevated tracks take up less space and block less sunlight in dense cities.
Unfortunately, that&rsquo;s where the list of upsides end.
Monorails are much more complicated than normal trains - switching tracks means moving massive blocks of concrete. Monorail tunnels actually need to be <em>taller</em> than the equivalent train tunnel, since the tracks themselves are taller. Finally, if you&rsquo;re running a transit agency, you can&rsquo;t swap the cars between standard rail or vice versa - they&rsquo;re monorail or nothing.
Because of this, most monorails of this era were essentially vanity projects for municipalities with money to burn. Think Disney World, Las Vegas, and&hellip; 1980s Japan. After Tokyo&rsquo;s first monorail (In 1964!), they began popping up all over: in Fukuoka (1985), Chiba (1988), Osaka (1990) and Tokyo again (1998). But of Japan&rsquo;s monorails, the coolest is undoubtedly Mitsubishi Electric&rsquo;s Suspended <em>Shonan Monorail</em>.</p>
<figure><img src="images/Shonanmonorail5000.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Shonan Monorail (<a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sh%C5%8Dnan_Monorail">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure class="right"><img src="images/shonanExterior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>View from the front of the Shonan Monorail</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Americans may know Mitsubishi as the producer of America&rsquo;s cheapest car and not much else. But in Japan, Mitsubishi Industries is a household name for air conditioners, aircraft, and construction equipment. And in the 1970s, they were at the top of their game. What would be a better symbol of their technological prowess than a hyper-complicated suspended monorail running past their front door? (Like I mentioned earlier - vanity project!) The Shonan Monorail cars dangle below an elevated track, giving a phenomenal (if a tad scary) view of the scenery below. This also means the cars swing outwards around the bends, just like a theme park ride. The crazy thing is, normal people still ride this every day to get to work! I&rsquo;m definitely not the only fan - when I rode, a whole crowd of people were lined up to take pictures and videos at the front of the train. As far as I can tell, there&rsquo;s no practical reason for the Shonan line to be a hanging monorail - it&rsquo;s just cool!</p>
<figure><img src="images/shonanMonorailBoarding.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Terminus for the Shonan Monorail. Lots of people actually use this as transit!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="cars-specifically-2012-toyota-spade">Cars (Specifically ~2012 Toyota Spade)</h2>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/keiCar.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>A tiny kei-car, in sports coupe guise. That&rsquo;s a normal-sized Toyota SUV right behind it!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I know what you&rsquo;re thinking - Ethan, Japan is the land of public transit! Why are you writing about cars here? Also, haven&rsquo;t you <a href="">written an entire article</a> about Japanese cars before? Correct on both counts - here I want to break down how cars fit into Japan&rsquo;s transit landscape, and how that differs from the States.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not like owning a car is cheap in Japan. The second you buy a car, you&rsquo;re immediately hit with a bevy of one-time and yearly taxes. Yearly taxes include a tax on engine size (displacement) and vehicle weight. One-time taxes are based off of how &ldquo;eco-friendly&rdquo; the car is and the sale price of the car (consumption tax). As an example, buying a Toyota RAV4 (currently the most popular car in the US) would would be taxed ~$2500 (consumption tax) + $1000 (environmental tax) off the bat. Then, you&rsquo;d owe an additional $305 (displacement tax) + $105 (weight tax) + $500 inspection yearly.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Oh, and the car only cost $31,000 begin with! Finally, gas is taxed at $.40 a gallon and every highway is a toll road. Ouch.</p>
<figure><img src="images/toyotaSpade.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>My friend&rsquo;s whip of choice - the Toyota Spade. The name is apparently a portmanteau of the words <em>Space</em> and <em>Wide</em>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Unsurprisingly, nearly every Japanese market car is built to dodge as many taxes as possible. Case in point, my friend&rsquo;s Toyota Spade. It only weighs 2400 lbs, nearly half that of the RAV4. With a tiny 1.3L engine, it&rsquo;s taxed at only 2/3s what a RAV4 costs.
Of course, building a usable car this light requires ingenuity, which the Spade has - well - in spades. The Spade is like a two-door, but the passenger door slides open like a minivan! This helps six-footers like my friend access the (surprisingly large) backseat with ease. The tax metagaming can go even deeper. If my friend wasn&rsquo;t so tall, he could opt for an even smaller, lighter <em>kei-car</em> for maximum tax optimization!</p>
<figure><img src="images/mitsuoka.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>If you want big car styling for small car money, Mitsuoka has you covered. You can buy a 3/4 size Challenger right off of the lot!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Why would someone in Japan bother jumping through these hoops in the first place? Just like in the US, geography plays a big role. Trains and buses may be less frequent in the suburbs, and in rural areas they may not exist at all. If you own a business, you&rsquo;re not going to deliver your goods by train. So for many, owning a car may be less of a luxury and more a way of life. Finally, road trips are just as popular in Japan as they are in the States. Not surprising to me - if you live in a city of 37 million, sometimes you need to get away from it all. For locals and tourists alike, cars are the still the best way to explore non-urban Japan.</p>
<h3 id="conculsion">Conculsion</h3>
<p>That&rsquo;s about it for this transit roundup! There were a few options I didn&rsquo;t get to try on my most recent trip (overnight ferry, cable car) and one I&rsquo;ve already written about (<a href="/posts/twodaysinnagoya/">Maglev</a>). Thanks for tuning in, and let me know if there any other forms of transit I should check out on my next visit!</p>
<p><em>Note: Of course, I still saw did a ton of train-related stuff on this trip. See the below pics from the Bullet Train museum in Nagoya!</em></p>
<p><figure><img src="images/ethanShinkansen.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Yours truly in front of the world&rsquo;s first bullet train!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="images/drYellow.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>&ldquo;Dr. Yellow&rdquo;, the bullet train used to diagnose tracks after earthquakes and the like</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="images/shinkansenTickets.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Retro computers once used to process bullet train tickets</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Even worse, most of these taxes <strong>increase</strong> the older the vehicle gets. No wonder Japan makes so many cars! (Tax #s calculated from <a href="https://tgmjapan.com/life-in-japan/finance/jp-taxes-vehicle-taxes/">this site</a>)&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🎶Losing Focus: Some Thoughts on the State of Music Streaming</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 09:13:51 -0700</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/essay1streamingservices/</guid>
			<description>When Steve Jobs first announced the iPhone in 2007, the reception was far from glowing. Compared to cell phones of the time, the iPhone made a lot of confusing design decisions. Keyboard loyalists decried the lack of physical buttons, and the extra features like email or internet were seen as wasteful or pointless. Who would really want to carry a computer in their pocket?
I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone is asking this in 2025.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When Steve Jobs first announced the iPhone in 2007, the reception was far from glowing. Compared to cell phones of the time, the iPhone made a lot of confusing design decisions. Keyboard loyalists decried the lack of physical buttons, and the extra features like email or internet were seen as wasteful or pointless. <a href="https://suckbusters2.blogspot.com/2007/06/apple-iphone-debut-to-flop-product-to.html">Who would really want to carry a computer in their pocket?</a></p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think anyone is asking this in 2025. From mapping to banking, what hasn&rsquo;t been streamlined by our ever-present pocket-computers? When it comes to music, smartphones and streaming are certainly cheaper and less labor-intensive than mp3s or CDs. But does this relentless focus on efficiency and optimization truly make music streaming a <em>better</em> listening experience? Today I want to examine something it seems like we&rsquo;ve lost in the streaming revolution: Focus.</p>
<figure><img src="AlbumCovers.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Album Covers from some records I recently sold.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="fostering-focus-positive-limitations-and-purposeful-interaction">Fostering Focus: Positive Limitations and Purposeful Interaction</h2>
<p>Despite being a <a href="/posts/cdrdao/">physical media die-hard</a>, I&rsquo;ll spare you the misty-eyed tales of &ldquo;simpler times&rdquo;. I think there&rsquo;s an objective benefit to physical media, which is the power of purposeful interaction.</p>
<p>But first, let&rsquo;s take a look at how most of the world consumes music: streaming. Spotify can serve you the exact song you want in 2 seconds flat. Don&rsquo;t like the current song? No problem! Just skip to the next track on the album, or pick something else from the entire breadth of human musical output. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, this freedom is awesome! But I and many others have developed a hair-trigger Spotify skip button. The second I&rsquo;m not feeling a song, I mash &ldquo;skip&rdquo; with no hesitation, in the hopes that the next track will scratch this invisible itch. To me, this freedom is actually a downside. You can&rsquo;t just sit and listen, because in parallel you&rsquo;re always asking yourself <em>&ldquo;Is this what I <strong>should</strong> be listening to?&quot;</em></p>
<figure><img src="SalesStats.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Music revenue by media format through 2021 - research by Statista (<a href="https://www.statista.com/chart/17244/us-music-revenue-by-format/">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Let&rsquo;s contrast this with the most convenient form of physical media: CDs. If you want to listen to music on CD, you have to make multiple purposeful decisions. Picking out an album means scanning through your collection, cracking open the case, and popping it into the player. These actions aren&rsquo;t difficult, but they are <em>committal</em>. The album you <em>should</em> to be listening to is the album <em>you</em> chose. Physical media even introduces barriers to non-committal listening habits. There&rsquo;s the physical inconvenience of swapping out discs, and even then your album alternatives are limited to whatever else is in your collection. The process of picking and playing a physical album means greater investment in and focus on the music itself.</p>
<p>Plus, how often are our kneejerk &ldquo;skip&rdquo; reactions really right? On first listen, I thought Yes' landmark album <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gka_km9gb5c"><em>Close To The Edge</em></a> was unfocused garbage. But around the tenth listen, I started to hear the talent and musicianship that went into it. And after it clicked, I couldn&rsquo;t stop listening. Was the album bad the first nine times? Of course not - I just needed time to warm up to it! If I hadn&rsquo;t bought Close to the Edge, I don&rsquo;t think I would have given Yes that chance, giving up on what is now one of my favorite albums.</p>

<iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/252LyflX4wUeISSzgL392F"
    width="100%"
    height="400"
    frameborder="0"
    allowtransparency="true"
    allow="encrypted-media"></iframe>


<h2 id="losing-focus-media-consumption-without-media-ownership">Losing Focus: Media Consumption without Media Ownership</h2>
<p>At this point, you may be thinking: &ldquo;But Ethan, Spotify <em>does</em> have a method for you to own your music. It&rsquo;s called pre-saving, where you can download any album to your local files and listen offline!&rdquo; Well, sort of. One obvious difference is that Spotify can remove songs from its platform at any time. Don&rsquo;t believe me? <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/0nMwuMpdqQZB7Ls5OOJAvB?nd=1&amp;dlsi=7f0b08690c4349e2">This album (also below)</a> used to be one of my favorites, now it&rsquo;s a &ldquo;ghost album&rdquo;.
<a href="https://community.spotify.com/t5/Your-Library/Liked-songs-being-removed/td-p/5460137">Spotify&rsquo;s thoughts on this phenomenon</a> are as follows: &ldquo;If you can&rsquo;t find the songs on Spotify at all, this could mean that they&rsquo;ve been made unavailable due to licensing reasons&rdquo;. Translating from Legal-ese to English, &ldquo;If we can&rsquo;t be bothered to re-up our licensing agreements, we can permanently delete songs from your library&rdquo;. I&rsquo;m not advocating for streaming services to forge licenses to keep songs on the platform. My point is, unlike physical media, streaming companies don&rsquo;t owe you access to anything. Your favorite songs could be gone tomorrow, and that would be the end of it.</p>

<iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/0nMwuMpdqQZB7Ls5OOJAvB"
    width="100%"
    height="400"
    frameborder="0"
    allowtransparency="true"
    allow="encrypted-media"></iframe>


<p>For most people, the convenience of music streaming more than makes up for losing a few songs here and there.
But streaming services themselves seem increasingly disinterested in their core music-listening experience. I hate to pick on Spotify again, (I still think it&rsquo;s a great service!), but it&rsquo;s pretty notorious for this. Spotify has a long-standing tradition of &ldquo;<a href="https://community.spotify.com/t5/iOS-iPhone-iPad/Disable-In-App-Suggestion-Pop-Ups/td-p/4595428">pop-up suggestions</a>&rdquo; - un-cancellable <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> advertisements for Spotify&rsquo;s less-used features.
Even paying, ad-free users get these interruptive pop-ups. Why could that be the case? Well, their CEO recently announced a <a href="https://www.pymnts.com/earnings/2024/spotify-dubs-2024-year-of-monetization-as-subscribers-surge-14percent-in-q1/">podcast and audiobook-driven &ldquo;year of monetization&rdquo;</a>. For the millions of paying users, Spotify&rsquo;s only path to further monetization is to sell them on new, <a href="https://community.spotify.com/t5/Subscriptions/Paid-podcast-not-included-in-premium-subscription/td-p/5245772">additional-cost</a> content. Spotify has little incentive to improve their core music experience - they&rsquo;re focused on converting more users into their exclusive podcasts and audiobooks. This loss in focus, this disconnect between what services prioritize and what consumers actually ask for is my biggest beef with music streaming today.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>On a cold winter morning in 1983, the head of Sony&rsquo;s Audio Division assembled his best and brightest engineers. He passed around a block of wood, roughly the size of 4 CD cases stacked vertically. His claim: &ldquo;We&rsquo;re going to commercialize a CD player of this size. I don&rsquo;t care how you do it, or whether you decide to put cicadas or grasshoppers in it, <a href="https://www.sony.com/en/SonyInfo/CorporateInfo/History/SonyHistory/2-09.html">but just make this produce sound.</a>&rdquo; The entire room laughed - at the time, Sony&rsquo;s CD players were bigger than cereal boxes. But a year later, Sony released the D-50 - a CD player smaller than that original block of wood - to resounding success. The D-50&rsquo;s success wasn&rsquo;t complicated - Sony just made a great, innovative product people wanted to buy.</p>
<figure class="right"><img src="SonyD50.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Sony&rsquo;s D50 CD player, first released in 1984 (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ObsoleteSony/comments/1fucrh4/the_1984_sony_d50_the_worlds_first_portable_cd/?tl=pl#lightbox">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>At first, music streaming was a similar, objective upgrade over the preceding mp3 / player ecosystem. But now, streaming has tied your media (music, podcasts, etc.) with the method of access (Spotify, Tidal, etc.) For many, this makes switching platforms unthinkable - you&rsquo;d lose all of your playlists and liked songs. Instead of the &ldquo;carrot&rdquo; of boundary-pushing features, streaming services would rather use the &ldquo;stick&rdquo; of vendor lock-in. Sony made money on the D-50 because it was a better product - streaming services make money by impeding users' ability choose better services.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t want to come off like a Luddite here - streaming has unquestionably democratized music. But where do we go from here? In the era of vendor lock-in and declining media ownership, do established streaming services even have an incentive to innovate further? I&rsquo;d love to think there&rsquo;s an upstart company with a disruptive feature right around the corner. In 2025, the most convenient way to listen to music seems to be simultaneously mindless and increasingly unfocused on the music itself.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> Whether convenient and best are synonymous is up to you.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Yes, I know Spotify claims it&rsquo;s &ldquo;<a href="https://community.spotify.com/t5/Implemented-Ideas/Remove-Pop-Up-Suggestions/idi-p/5571419#comments">fixed</a>&rdquo;. Others are <a href="https://community.spotify.com/t5/Implemented-Ideas/Remove-Pop-Up-Suggestions/idi-p/5571419/page/8#comments">mysteriously unable to find the unsubscribe button</a> two years later.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>And for artists under the 1M streams mark, arguably exploitative. But people smarter than me have spilled lots of ink on this topic - you don&rsquo;t need my take here.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🚃 Rating Every Train in San Francisco</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/sftransit/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 10:03:08 -0700</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/sftransit/</guid>
			<description>As some may know, I moved to Santa Clara about a year ago. But if a non-Californian asks me where I live, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to skip the geography lesson and just say San Francisco. Despite how often I use this line, I recently realized I haven&amp;rsquo;t really explored San Francisco yet.
Sure, I&amp;rsquo;ve driven in for a few concerts - but that&amp;rsquo;s not exploring. Driving is all point-to-point. Pull up to the destination and park in the least sketchy lot you can find.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As some may know, I moved to Santa Clara about a year ago. But if a non-Californian asks me where I live, I&rsquo;ve learned to skip the geography lesson and just say San Francisco. Despite how often I use this line, I recently realized I haven&rsquo;t really explored San Francisco yet.</p>
<p>Sure, I&rsquo;ve driven in for a few concerts - but that&rsquo;s not exploring. Driving is all point-to-point. Pull up to the destination and park in the least sketchy lot you can find. Event ends, then drive home. So on my next company holiday, I knew what I wanted to do - explore San Francisco by riding and ranking every train in the city!</p>
<h2 id="caltrain">Caltrain</h2>
<figure><img src="images/caltrain.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>New Electrified Caltrain!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For the first leg of this trip, I had to get from Santa Clara to San Francisco. Other parts of the Bay are served by the BART, but in Silicon Valley we have Caltrain. Caltrain is regional rail - its main goal is to funnel people from one city center to another. Observationally, most Caltrain riders are commuters plugging away at laptops on their way to the city. (At least, those riding at 10:00 AM on a Friday morning).</p>
<figure><img src="images/caltrainRoute.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Caltrain route from San Jose to San Francisco - Total time: 1:18</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The trains themselves are pretty nice! Caltrain just finished up a major effort to electrify the entire line, replacing the aging diesel locomotives with <a href="https://sanjosespotlight.com/silicon-valley-riders-all-in-on-caltrain-electrification/">state-of-the-art electric trains</a>. These are double-decker trains, with bike areas below and passenger cabins with tons of seating room above. They&rsquo;re definitely more modern, but I think I preferred the more spacious, less plastic-y passenger cabins from the pre-electric cars.</p>
<figure><img src="images/caltrainInterior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Caltrain&rsquo;s Interior. Lots of seating!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Caltrain was originally a passenger route operated by California&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.foundsf.org/The_Octopus_and_the_Big_Four">favorite railroad monopoly</a>, Southern Pacific. This got my hopes up - surely a city as important as San Francisco would have a historic terminal (perhaps à la Grand Central in New York?) Pulling into the station, my hopes were immediately dashed. At one point, SP had a beautiful Mission Revival-style terminal building (left), but it was torn down in favor of the nothing-burger 4th and Townsend station in the 70&rsquo;s. (right) What a shame.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/spterminal.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/newterminal.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Southern Pacific&rsquo;s previous terminal, demolished in 1978</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Caltrain&rsquo;s uninspired replacement terminal</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>All in all, a trip from San Jose to SF on Caltrain will take you an hour thirty, and cost a fat $9.50. This is kinda pricey, but considering how much I&rsquo;ve paid to park in SF it&rsquo;s not horrible. Trains run every 30 minutes on weekdays and hourly on weekends, so you do have schedule around timetables more than other options. But all in all, Caltrain is great if you want to tune out for an hour and wake up in San Francisco.</p>
<p><strong>Ratings: Caltrain</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center">Frequency</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Cost</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Comfort/Cleanliness</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">2/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">2/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">5/5 (Diesel 6/5!)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="muni-metro-streetcars--trams">Muni Metro (Streetcars / Trams)</h2>
<figure><img src="images/muni/muni_exterior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Muni&rsquo;s modern, street-running trollies</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Now that we&rsquo;ve made it to SF, how do we get around? If you&rsquo;re a local, you likely use the nation&rsquo;s oldest publicly-owned transit system, Muni Metro! At one point in San Francisco&rsquo;s history, up to ten transit companies operated cable cars and electric trollies. When a company called United Railways began buying up rail lines to form a monopoly, citizens revolted and founded Muni Metro - <a href="https://www.sfmta.com/getting-around/muni/muni-history">a city-owned and operated transit department</a>. Muni&rsquo;s streetcar lines started dwindling after the 1950s as buses replaced surface lines. However, purpose-built streetcar infrastructure like the Twin Peaks Tunnel saved the trams from total destruction. This is actually why Muni&rsquo;s alphabetical line names start at the letter J: Lines A-H existed, but were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_defunct_San_Francisco_Municipal_Railway_lines#Defunct_streetcar_routes">removed long ago and never replaced</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/muni/belt_line_portal.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Some remnants of the E line&rsquo;s industrial past</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Today, Muni has both pros and cons. First off, $2.75 per ride isn&rsquo;t cheap (though there is a free transfer window to other Muni services). Despite dedicated right-of-ways, street running sections of Muni are slow and often stop for traffic signals. The stop request system hypothetically saves time, but nearly every station has someone to pick up / drop off so it&rsquo;s not super effective. But things speed up underground - my T-line train maxed out at 28 MPH in the Central Subway tunnel. Trains are also modern and frequent, offsetting these travel time hiccups. It&rsquo;d be fair to call the Muni streetcars a mixed bag.</p>
<figure><img src="images/muni/retro_muni_exterior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Muni&rsquo;s adorable retro trollies!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well, <em>some</em> trains are modern. All of Muni&rsquo;s downsides turn into upsides once you step onto an E-Embarcadero train. The historic trolleycars are loud, cramped and slow - but this just adds to their charm! As a bonus, a ton of tourist destinations are along the E line. You can hit the Ferry Building, swing by Coit Tower, and end up in North Beach in one straight shot.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/muni/muni_interior.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/muni/retro_muni_interior.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Interior of a modern Muni train</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Interior of a retro Muni train</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in the route I took&hellip;</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/muni/muni_route1_scaled.png" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/muni/muni_route2_scaled.png" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Muni from Caltrain Station to the Ferry Building - Total time ~15 min.</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Muni from the Ferry Building to North Beach</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Ratings: Muni Metro</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center">Frequency</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Cost</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Comfort/Cleanliness</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">5/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">2/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">3/5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="cable-cars">Cable Cars</h2>
<figure><img src="images/bartCableCar/cable_exterior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>San Francisco&rsquo;s iconic cable car!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>No, not that kind of cable car. San Francisco&rsquo;s most quintessential mode of transit is may look like a streetcar, but that&rsquo;s where the similarities end. 19th century engineers quickly learned that underpowered streetcars and hills don&rsquo;t mix. In 1873, British entrepreneur Andrew Smith Hallidie was the first inventor with a solution. His innovation was simple - cable cars would be pulled up hills by a constantly-moving wire under the roadbed. By using a clutch (similar to a manual transmission), cable cars could &ldquo;latch onto&rdquo; the wire for acceleration up a hill <em>or</em> braking down the hill. Genius!</p>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/bartCableCar/cable_interior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Cable car &ldquo;interior&rdquo; on a steep grade</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This system is really cool, but has a few quirks. For one, the car can&rsquo;t travel faster than the cable&rsquo;s constant 9.5 MPH. Cables are great at pulling in a straight line but curves are much more complicated. As a result, cars sometimes have build up enough speed on a downhill to coast through corners without cable assistance. Since runaway cable cars are bad news, they have <em>three</em> redundant braking systems! I could write at least three more paragraphs about how these work, but instead I&rsquo;ll just recommend the <a href="https://www.cablecarmuseum.org/">SF Cable Car Museum</a> on the corner of Mason and Washington. Here, you&rsquo;ll get to see the beating heart of the cable car system, and it&rsquo;s completely free!</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/bartCableCar/museum_exterior.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/bartCableCar/museum_interior.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>SF Cable Car Museum</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Cable room for San Francisco&rsquo;s entire cable car system!</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The Cable Car Museum&rsquo;s website proclaims: &ldquo;<a href="https://www.cablecarmuseum.org/heritage.html">Tourists don&rsquo;t come to San Francisco to ride the buses</a>&rdquo;. Fair point - but do cable cars' tourist popularity impact their transit usefulness? Eh, yes and no. Prices are steep (get it?) at $8.00 one-way. Wait times are long in touristy parts, especially at the North Beach turnaround. But there are two easy ways to mitigate this. First, skip the line by hiking a few stations down from the main terminal. Even if &ldquo;full&rdquo;, the car will nearly always stop and let you hop on. This normally gets you the coveted &ldquo;hanging off the side&rdquo; spot, too. Second, show the conductor your clipper card (the Bay Area&rsquo;s transit payment system), and there&rsquo;s a high likelihood they won&rsquo;t charge you. (Maybe because you&rsquo;ll look like a local?)</p>
<figure><img src="images/bartCableCar/cableCarRoute.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Cable Car route from North Beach to Powell St.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>Ratings: Cable Car</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center">Frequency</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Cost</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Comfort/Cleanliness</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">3/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">3/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">Who cares? Weeeeeeee!</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="bart">BART</h2>
<figure><img src="images/bartCableCar/bart_exterior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>BART&rsquo;s newer rolling stock</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Rounding out this article is the Bay Area&rsquo;s regional rail system, BART. While Caltrain and Muni have to tradeoff high speed with local stops, BART is laser focused on getting commuters into the metro area as fast as possible. Overall, I was surprised by how normal BART was. From the safety perspective, BART does have a bit of a reputation. As recently as 2023, <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2023/05/09/increasing-security-and-kicking-off-unruly-passengers-could-bring-back-bart-riders-poll-shows/">46% of BART riders have personally witnessed crime on the system</a>. My ride from Powell Street to Millbrae was downright boring - chalk it up to either <a href="https://www.bart.gov/about/projects/fare-gate">security improvements</a> or the fact that it was 17:30 on a Friday.</p>
<figure><img src="images/bartCableCar/bartAd.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>A slide from BART&rsquo;s 1960&rsquo;s retro-futuristic pitch deck (<a href="https://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Planning_and_Selling_BART">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Normal can be a double edged sword, though. During its inception, BART branded itself as the &ldquo;transportation of the future&rdquo; to coax commuters out of their cars. This meant a seats for every passenger, star-trek styled trains, and (unthinkable for a subway today), <a href="https://www.bart.gov/50years/stories/5">carpeted floors</a>! Quirkiness went beyond style - BART made clever use of wider, broad-gauge track to better stabilize trains in San Francisco&rsquo;s cutting wind. Today, the original luxury fleet is gone. The tracks are still weird, but now BART just feels like every other subway, which seems a little wrong for the consistently quirky Bay Area.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/bartCableCar/BART_interior.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/bartCableCar/bart_station.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>BART interior - lots of standing room</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Hmm&hellip; This station reminds me of <a href="/posts/japanarch/">another article</a>&hellip;</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Since BART doesn&rsquo;t continue into south bay, I had to transfer back to Caltrain at the SF Airport. Total cost: $5.80 - considering how smooth and well-connected BART was, this price feels alright to me.</p>
<figure><img src="images/bartCableCar/bartroute.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>BART from Powell to Millbrae - Total time, ~40 min</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>Ratings: BART</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center">Frequency</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Cost</th>
<th style="text-align:center">Comfort/Cleanliness</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center">4/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">4/5</td>
<td style="text-align:center">3/5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h2>
<p>On the Caltrain back to my place, I was struck by how many of my interactions with the city were shaped by public transit. Case in point, Coit Tower. If I were driving from the Ferry Building to North Beach, I probably wouldn&rsquo;t have stopped by Coit Tower. Parking is expensive, which makes it committal. It&rsquo;s hard to leave room for surprises or exploration with a parking meter ticking down in the back of your head. But taking the streetcar from the Ferry Building to North Beach is an entirely different story. Streetcars run every 15 minutes, so you might as well explore some stops along the way! As a tourist, public transit turns &ldquo;is this really worth my time?&rdquo; into &ldquo;while I&rsquo;m here&hellip;&rdquo; So next time you travel, try the train! Your next favorite spot may only be a station away.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Sorry for the Wikipedia citation. I couldn&rsquo;t find a more digestible way to visualize how much Muni was gutted in the 50&rsquo;s!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🏎️ What Genre is Mario Kart Music?</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mariokartmusic/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 18:20:02 -0700</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mariokartmusic/</guid>
			<description>Killer debut album cover for Casiopea! (image credit)
  Grab a pair of headphones, because this article has a soundtrack! Check out the first song in this Youtube playlist: does it remind you of anything?
 hint hint (image credit)
  If your formative years were later than 1990, your first thought was likely &amp;ldquo;Mario Kart&amp;rdquo;. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be alone - more and more people seem to be finding (and even writing!</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="images/casiopea.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Killer debut album cover for Casiopea! (<a href="https://tsquareplaza.blogspot.com/2020/04/casiopea-1979.html">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Grab a pair of headphones, because this article has a soundtrack! Check out the first song in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9PFOkv3a0KY&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=1">this Youtube playlist</a>: does it remind you of anything?</p>
<figure><img src="images/marioKartHeader.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>hint hint (<a href="https://www.eurogamer.net/mario-kart-8-guide-tips-tricks-shortcuts-deluxe">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>If your formative years were later than 1990, your first thought was likely &ldquo;Mario Kart&rdquo;. You wouldn&rsquo;t be alone - more and more people seem to be <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@joeyontheair/video/7330431532294982958">finding</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZX3DHsJ2-08">and even writing!</a>) music they can only describe as &ldquo;Mario Kart Music&rdquo;. But why? How does a single game seemingly define an entire genre? And what makes &ldquo;Mario Kart Music&rdquo; different from established genres like Jazz or Funk? Well, I and my three nonconsecutive semesters of Jazz Performance 201 have a theory. So buckle up as I tackle yet another universal question: &ldquo;What Genre is Mario Kart Music?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>Note: I realized about halfway through writing this that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ixNebosI3j8">some really talented people have already discussed this topic</a>. I wanted to do my own thing here, so I&rsquo;ve decided not to watch that video before publishing this article. Maybe we ended up with the same conclusions? Who knows!</em></p>
<h2 id="quantifying-mario-kart-music-history">Quantifying Mario Kart Music: History</h2>
<p>To get the full picture, we need to contrast the evolution of Jazz Fusion in Japan vs. the United States.</p>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/tSquareTruth.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>T-Square&rsquo;s hit album Truth (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth_(T-Square_album)">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Fusion (the musical genre) has existed in some form since at least the 1960&rsquo;s. I&rsquo;d broadly define Fusion as music combining elements of Rock and Funk (energetic, driving rhythm) with Jazz (extended instrumental solos, more complex melodies and chords). But once the 70&rsquo;s rolled around, Fusion had competition: Disco. Fusion pioneers in the U.S. saw Disco&rsquo;s pitch-perfect recordings as &ldquo;pre-fabricated&rdquo; or &ldquo;soulless&rdquo;, and in response pushed their music in a less commercial direction. Herbie Hancock&rsquo;s 1973 album <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xDSdxOM-dI0"><em>Sextant</em></a> is a textbook example of this. Herbie is a legend, but it&rsquo;s not something I&rsquo;d put on at a party. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Across the Pacific, however, this stigma didn&rsquo;t seem to hold. In Japanese Fusion bands, seriously talented Jazz musicians embraced Disco&rsquo;s dance-able rhythms and accessibility, creating an entirely new genre in the process.</p>
<p>But to reach worldwide audiences, Japanese Fusion (<em>J-Fusion</em>) would need some help from Japan&rsquo;s other major entertainment industry - Video Games. According to Nintendo&rsquo;s first in-house composer (Koji Kondo), J-Fusion and Video Games have been linked since the beginning. Kondo often cited J-Fusion bands like T-Square and Casiopea as his major influences. Give <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RgdMDDfHrIQ">T-Square&rsquo;s 1983 hit Sister Marian</a> a listen and see if a certain plumber comes to mind! It wasn&rsquo;t just Nintendo, either. Throughout the late 80s, J-Fusion (and its mellower cousin genre, City Pop) became a sort of &ldquo;tonal lingua franca&rdquo; for Japanese video game music. Once Nintendo and Sega exploded in popularity, millions of people labeled this new genre not as &ldquo;Fusion&rdquo; or &ldquo;Pop&rdquo;, but by their method of introduction: &ldquo;Video Game Music&rdquo;. Or, (if we substitute a chart-topping franchise), &ldquo;Mario Kart Music&rdquo;!</p>
<p>OK, enough history - what actually makes certain songs sound so Mario Kart-y? I think there are 2 main components: Energy and Instrumentation.</p>
<h2 id="quantifying-mario-kart-music-energy-through-rhythm">Quantifying Mario Kart Music: Energy through Rhythm</h2>
<p>Do you remember the first song in this article&rsquo;s playlist, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9PFOkv3a0KY&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=1">(<em>Time Limit</em> by Casiopea</a>)? Go ahead and compare it to Mario Kart Wii&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m_0pV67tbOg&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=2"><em>Moonview Highway - City Theme</em></a>, paying special attention to the rhythm.</p>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/casiopeaBandPic.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Casiopea committed to the bit - note the racing gear used in their debut album&rsquo;s photoshoot (<a href="https://www.redbubble.com/i/art-board-print/Casiopea-band-photo-album-by-zidanezues/152031545.TR477">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Even though the instruments differ, the rhythms here are actually pretty similar. No time for melody here - instead, both songs are built around short, high-speed riffs. (Listen for the trumpets / horns in Time Limit, or the sax in Moonview Highway). The bass and drums are just as loud as these riffs, both seeming to compete for center stage. The result is a song that eggs you on, pushing you to step on the gas - perfect for Mario Kart!</p>
<p>OK, one more example from the same album. Give 1:03-2:00 of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AHU74oGbXzU&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=3"><em>Space Road</em></a> a quick listen. Notice how the tension just keeps building and building? In this case, tension comes from a musical technique called a <em>key change</em>. A <em>key</em> is just a specific set of notes that sound good together - every song is written with one in mind. While most songs only use notes in one key, some composers shift to another key mid-song to create tension. So when Casiopea shift keys not one, but <em>five</em> times (!!!), we the listeners naturally feel a heightened urgency. And so it is in Mario Kart - the soundtrack (famously) increases the pressure on the final lap by shifting keys and speeding up the music. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4b0mZ0CbMUo&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=4">You can hear this fanfare</a> which is essentially a key change that signals the start of the lap.</p>
<h2 id="quantifying-mario-kart-music-instrumentation">Quantifying Mario Kart Music: Instrumentation</h2>
<p>Energy is only one piece of the puzzle, though. Metal music is energetic, but hardly screams Mario Kart. What is our formula still missing?</p>
<p>Instruments are definitely part of the picture. In a video game, it&rsquo;s common to base different levels on different biomes. Whether swamp, desert or anything in between, the level&rsquo;s music has to match the theme. Instrumentation is the traditional way to do this (i.e. banjo music for the swamp, Egyptian-style music in the desert, etc). But the challenge of video game music is taking all of these different instruments and themes and making them feel like part of a cohesive whole.</p>
<figure><img src="images/takanakaSurfboardGuitar.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Takanaka sometimes shredded on a surfboard guitar, too. What a legend. (<a href="https://www.guitarworld.com/features/masayoshi-takanaka-surfboard-guitar-shred">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This is where Fusion comes in. Even before video games were invented, artists were using J-Fusion to introduce unfamiliar genres in a familiar way. Case in point: guitar virtuoso Masayoshi Takanaka. Despite his jazz-rock roots, Takanaka used his solo project to explore the crossroads of J-Fusion and Brazilian Samba. At a certain point, Takanaka even began <a href="https://popfantasma.com.br/sambao-de-star-wars-com-masayoshi-takanaka/">traveling to Brazil</a> just to cut his records! Takanaka was successful, too; combined with J-Fusion&rsquo;s infectious grooves, Samba and Mambo became wildly popular a hemisphere away from home. Mario Kart music is actually pretty similar! While most Mario Kart songs are based on Fusion rhythm and structure, each track has its own instrumentation and identity. This makes each song sound &ldquo;Mario Kart&rdquo;, despite the wide range of instrumental and genre-level influences.</p>
<p>Now for some examples! Takanaka&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ah96ejVKmJM&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=5">phenomenal cover of Mambo No. 5</a> is essentially a piano-driven Mambo track with some J-Fusion sprinkled in. Even if the rest of this song differs, Takanaka&rsquo;s cover has an intro that screams <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cscuCIzItZQ&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=6">Mario Kart Wii&rsquo;s Coconut Mall</a>. For a more clear A/B , I&rsquo;d compare Takanaka&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nQZKe9zla2U&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=7">Ready to Fly</a> with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1K7W5Fq1zjs&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=8">GBA Shy Guy Beach from Mario Kart Wii</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-present">The Present</h2>
<figure><img src="images/bigBlueRecording.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Session musicians laying down a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=16Zq8EMCdZ4">new track for MarioKart 8</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Of course, none of this is hard and fast rule. The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I-VUuq7zItM">soundtrack for the upcoming Mario Kart World</a> sounds more Lynyrd Skynyrd than Herbie Hancock. Even the games I grew up with broke this mold: Tracks like the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jZyfmSUnd-A&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=9">Nintendo WFC Menu</a> were equal parts <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JjPIILmXRRY&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=10">Brecker-style Fusion</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FeHdIDeUsEY&amp;list=PL6F62lSLKUcEtpnECP0_FuoV520Q1hBrk&amp;index=11">Stereolab breakbeat drumming</a>. But regardless of how Mario Kart evolves, I think the energy and experimentation of Japanese Jazz Fusion will continue to be a major influence on Mario Kart soundtracks for years to come.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>One exception to this claim is saxophonist Michael Brecker. Another Jazz Fusion great, his American group Steps Ahead embraced a more commercial sound than his contemporaries. But Steps Ahead was always more popular in Japan than in the US, and Brecker even recorded with Japanese Fusion bands like Casiopea and T-Square. So his work is arguably more representative of Japanese than American Fusion.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>📲 Scope Creep and Personal Projects</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 22:13:38 -0800</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/scopecreep/</guid>
			<description>Some viewers (especially programmers) may find the following image disturbing:
 Charitably, software gore
  Ouch. Is that Python or Javascript? And do I spy inline CSS styling? To quote The Talking Heads, &amp;ldquo;How did I get here?&amp;quot; After all, no one ever sets out to write bad code. While bad code can result from laziness or inexperience, I want to spend this article discussing a third source: Scope Creep.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some viewers (especially programmers) may find the following image disturbing:</p>
<figure><img src="images/GrossMultiLanguage2.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Charitably, software gore</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Ouch. Is that Python or Javascript? And do I spy inline CSS styling? To quote The Talking Heads, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fR0jgT9UX0Q">&ldquo;How did I get here?&quot;</a> After all, no one ever sets out to write bad code. While bad code can result from laziness or inexperience, I want to spend this article discussing a third source: Scope Creep.</p>
<p>Scope Creep is what results from changing a project&rsquo;s goals while still in active development. Normally, this looks like adding new features without fully understanding how difficult implementation will be. More often than not, the project&rsquo;s existing codebase has to be hacked into supporting these features, resulting in clunky and non-optimized code. My most recent project, <a href="http://cafematrix.net/">CafeMatrix</a>, is definitely guilty of this! So I thought it&rsquo;d be cool to write an article deconstructing CafeMatrix&rsquo;s code quirks and mapping them to scope creep I encountered during development. This post will be a bit programming-heavy, but I&rsquo;ll try to throw some lifelines to non-technical audience members along the way. Let&rsquo;s get started!</p>
<h2 id="scope-creep-instance-1-cafematrixs-original-inspiration">Scope Creep, Instance 1: CafeMatrix&rsquo;s original inspiration</h2>
<figure><img src="images/class.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>The ShopReview class, which handles review processing.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>CafeMatrix was originally inspired by the &ldquo;coffee spreadsheet&rdquo;. Many of my friends track details on their favorite cafes in a spreadsheet. After parsing a few, I noticed each of these (independently developed) spreadsheets were ranking cafes on the same general set of criteria. Coffee taste and cost were obvious, but more abstract fields like &ldquo;cafe vibe&rdquo; and &ldquo;good study spot&rdquo; were well represented too.</p>
<p>This got me thinking - if there were an agreed-upon set of criteria to rated cafes, it would be much easier to share and compare recommendations with friends! But how to compare cafes? After all, some are great for hanging out, others are geared towards studying, and so on. My solution was the 3-axis system, where every cafe is rated on three separate axes: Study Suitability, Ambiance, and Value (which includes taste). This spikes out each location&rsquo;s strong suits, giving a better indication of what each cafe is all about.</p>
<figure><img src="images/spreadsheetBackend.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>CafeMatrix&rsquo;s original spreadsheet &ldquo;database&rdquo;</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>What did this look like on the code side? I initially wanted CafeMatrix to aggregate reviews from different users, each of which would be stored on a central database. But implementing an entire database is a boring first step - I decided to start writing the backend in Python, substituting a spreadsheet for the database in the interim.</p>
<p>CafeMatrix didn&rsquo;t end up evolving in this direction, and a central database was never added. But the hooks for this initial plan are obvious in the codebase. For example, in the ShopReview class, reviews have both a Shop ID and a Review ID. But CafeMatrix only allows one review per shop - why aren&rsquo;t they the same? The original intent here was to allow multiple reviews be assigned to one shop, from which the shop&rsquo;s final score could be calculated. This class is overkill for it&rsquo;s current purpose,  but it was meant for so much more!</p>
<p>So, what killed the database idea? I read a <a href="https://apenwarr.ca/log/?m=202312">very interesting article</a> about inaccuracies in emotion-based rating on a 10-point scale. My takeaway was that most people can&rsquo;t be bothered to granularly rate each criteria with any level of consistency. Plus, I would never get a large volume of data with how (admittedly) niche this program is. While the database idea died, it&rsquo;s legacy lives on as another quirk in CafeMatrix&rsquo;s codebase.</p>
<h2 id="scope-creep-instance-2-how-cafematrix-became-a-webapp">Scope Creep, Instance 2: How CafeMatrix became a Webapp</h2>
<figure><img src="images/generateMatrix.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>generateMatrix, the method that builds the 3D ratings matrix.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As the backend took shape, another problem crystallized - How was I going to represent this data-dense information to the end user? With nine separate rating indices and user comments, displaying &ldquo;just enough&rdquo; information would be critical. But how to define &ldquo;just enough&rdquo;?</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/blueEngineTempLight.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/engineTempGauge.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>The blue engine temperature light in question (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BHBjNo1i7MY">source</a>)</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>A typical engine temperature gauge (<a href="https://www.lincolncustomauto.com/blog/things-to-know-about-your-car-s-temperature-gauge">source</a>)</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Like all good questions, the answer here is &ldquo;it depends&rdquo; - let&rsquo;s look at an extended example. My sister&rsquo;s 2018 Mazda3 is somewhat unusual due to it&rsquo;s engine temperature <em>light</em> - blue if the engine is cold, red if it&rsquo;s hot, and off at normal temperatures. A racing driver would be appalled. On the track, these three options aren&rsquo;t enough to make any meaningful decisions. But my sister isn&rsquo;t lapping <a href="https://weathertechraceway.com/">Laguna Seca</a> in her free time. For her, a full temp readout would just clutter the dashboard. What I&rsquo;m getting at here is that <em>the end usecase establishes information relevancy</em>. Define your usecase clearly (&ldquo;vehicle is not a racecar&rdquo;), and you can cut a lot of info that previously appeared essential (&ldquo;full-fledged temperature gauge&rdquo;).</p>
<p>With this background, I landed on the following &ldquo;clearly defined end usecase for CafeMatrix&rdquo;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>CafeMatrix exists to <em>track and compare</em> different cafes in common areas like taste, cost, and ambiance. It does so by defining a detailed, shared criteria by which all cafes are rated and contrasted.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After answering this fundamental question, designing CafeMatrix&rsquo;s UI became a lot easier. Each cafe already has a ranking (1-10) for the three axes of Study Suitability, Ambiance, and Value (which includes taste). So each cafe could be a unique point on a scatter plot, like in the example below. The twist here is that, with 3 axes, CafeMatrix would need to be a <strong>3-dimensional</strong> scatter plot. Now I had to find a way to plot pretty 3D scatter plots in Python.</p>
<figure><img src="images/cafeMatrix.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>The final result!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <a href="https://community.plotly.com/t/big-data-plotply-js-vs-plotply-py/40446">Plotly.py</a> library seemed a perfect fit, but picking it inadvertently and massively increased this project&rsquo;s scope. As it turns out, Plotly plots are packaged in a website with a fully interactive 3D scatter plot. There was too much meat on the bone to refuse, and the idea of a fully local &ldquo;<a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2004/06/13/how-microsoft-lost-the-api-war/">rich client</a>&rdquo; CafeMatrix died. My minimum viable product was now a webapp with a collision course for the internet.</p>
<h2 id="scope-creep-instance-3-how-i-ended-up-writing-javascript-in-python">Scope Creep, Instance 3: How I ended up writing Javascript in Python</h2>
<p>Now that CafeMatrix was a capital-W Website, I suddenly found myself having to care about smartphones. A brief test confirmed the bad news - my UI was beautiful on laptop displays, but marred by disgusting horizontal scrollbars on mobile. I&rsquo;d used the <a href="https://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap toolkit</a> to solve similar problems before, but that only works for websites written in HTML. Surely there wasn&rsquo;t a distribution of Bootstrap for my specific flavor of Python, right?</p>
<figure><img src="images/GrossMultiLanguage2.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Writing HTML in Python. Square peg, meet round hole.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As it turns out, there was! Thanks to the kind souls at Faculty.ai, I added Bootstrap functionality to Python using the <a href="https://dash-bootstrap-components.opensource.faculty.ai/docs/components/">DBC library</a> - but with caveats. As mentioned, Bootstrap was always intended for websites written in HTML. In HTML, you first add in UI elements (paragraphs, buttons, etc.), then assign Bootstrap &ldquo;classes&rdquo; to each one.
These classes are what make buttons act like buttons and paragraphs like paragraphs. To replicate this behavior in Python, each Bootstrap class is instead a Python function that you call. This is really clunky, since Python functions don&rsquo;t naturally nest in the way HTML elements do. DBC has to cram sub-elements in as arguments to the function call alongside the actual function arguments themselves. I&rsquo;m impressed by the amount of polish on this library, but this is the programming equivalent of jamming a square peg in a round hole.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion-and-whats-next">Conclusion (and What&rsquo;s Next)</h2>
<p>But you know what? <em>It works!</em> If I had known CafeMatrix would grow into an interactive app on the world wide web, I absolutely would have started with HTML/Javascript. But that&rsquo;s the thing with personal projects - they <em>evolve</em>. Sure, scope creep leads to some really clunky code. But the <a href="/posts/echo-matic_special2/">best way to murder a project momentum</a> is to go the opposite route and overoptimize before you&rsquo;ve even started. If I tried to tackle this project&rsquo;s whole scope (webapp, hosting, etc.) from the get-go, I&rsquo;m confident CafeMatrix wouldn&rsquo;t be here today.</p>
<p>So here&rsquo;s my humble takeaway. Just start something. Start working on a big idea and stick with it. It won&rsquo;t always be clean, but the details will work themselves out and you&rsquo;ll learn a lot in the process! CafeMatrix was my first time self-hosting a website, and it was <em>way</em> harder than I was expecting. But I came out the other end with a much better understanding of project management and the internet as a whole. So maybe, for personal projects, scope creep isn&rsquo;t so bad!</p>
<p>This type of article naturally begs a question - am I going to rewrite CafeMatrix in Javascript to fix all of it&rsquo;s flaws? Resoundingly, no. I try to avoid whatever StackOverflow&rsquo;s creator lists as <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/04/06/things-you-should-never-do-part-i/">Things You Should Never Do</a>. That being said - imagine if you could cram an entire matrix into an easily shareable 3KB QR code. Hmm&hellip; And so, Scope Creep continues!</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🏙️ Is Nagoya Boring?</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 19:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</guid>
			<description>Recently, it seems like everyone I talk to is either visiting or returning from Japan. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just my observation - according to multiple sources, Japan&amp;rsquo;s post-covid tourism numbers are through the roof. While many plan their trips around the glitz and glamor of Tokyo or the rich culture of Kyoto, there&amp;rsquo;s another city that I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to see on any itinerary - Nagoya.
Despite being it&amp;rsquo;s third largest metro area, Nagoya is nationally renowned as &amp;ldquo;Japan&amp;rsquo;s most boring city&amp;rdquo;.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="big"><img src="images/topshot.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>Recently, it seems like everyone I talk to is either visiting or returning from Japan. This isn&rsquo;t just my observation - according to <a href="https://ceias.eu/whats-behind-japans-post-pandemic-tourism-surge/">multiple</a> <a href="https://asia.nikkei.com/Business/Travel-Leisure/Hotel-stays-in-Japan-hit-record-651m-on-inbound-tourism-surge">sources</a>, Japan&rsquo;s post-covid tourism numbers are through the roof. While many plan their trips around the glitz and glamor of Tokyo or the rich culture of Kyoto, there&rsquo;s another city that I&rsquo;ve yet to see on any itinerary - Nagoya.</p>
<p>Despite being it&rsquo;s third largest metro area, Nagoya is nationally renowned as &ldquo;Japan&rsquo;s most boring city&rdquo;. A famous poll found that <a href="https://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2016/10/08/national/media-national/nagoya-boring-city-japan/#.V_ktjLh95E4">even Nagoya&rsquo;s locals think Tokyo and Kyoto are &ldquo;more appealing&rdquo; than their own hometown</a>. But is this a fair assessment? Is Nagoya really that boring? I spent three months as an expat in Nagoya with the goal of finding out. So join me in this half-article, half-guidebook as we weigh in on whether Nagoya deserves it&rsquo;s ho-hum reputation.</p>
<h1 id="nagoya-station-area--toyota-industry-museum">Nagoya Station Area / Toyota Industry Museum</h1>
<p>Nagoya Station will likely be your gateway to Nagoya proper, so it&rsquo;s probably the best place to start this guide. There&rsquo;s already a lot to do right next to the station! I&rsquo;ve summarized these locations in a <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/yr1yqAj7j5w6FQhb7">Nagoya Station area Google maps guide</a>.</p>
<h2 id="nagoya-station">Nagoya Station</h2>
<figure><img src="images/stationGoldClock.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Nagoya Station&rsquo;s Gold Clock</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><figure class="right"><img src="images/stationSilverClock.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Nagoya Station&rsquo;s Silver Clock (ft. my copycat Seiko)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

Leaving the Shinkansen platform, the first thing to catch your eye will likely be the oversized Seiko station clock. Due to it&rsquo;s proximity to the station platforms, you&rsquo;ll often see groups of people waiting to greet friends / family arriving by train. I guess Citizen wanted to upstage Seiko, since they built another clock on the other side of the station - way taller, and gold instead of silver! But if the pictures didn&rsquo;t make it clear, I like the Seiko better&hellip;</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re at the gold clock, one of my favorite views of the whole city is just a few steps away. If you ride the Gate Tower elevator to the 15th floor, you&rsquo;ll stumble upon an airy rooftop terrace with a view of the whole city. It&rsquo;s a great place to relax after a long train ride. There&rsquo;s a <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/iJhXJxLpj9R84g3V8">Starbucks attached to the terrace</a> - If you get the Nagoya &ldquo;been there&rdquo; mug as a souvenir, they&rsquo;ll give you a free drink!</p>
<figure><img src="images/sbuxGateTower.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the Starbucks Gate Tower terrace (<a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g298106-d12309834-Reviews-Starbucks_Coffee_Nagoya_JR_Gate_Tower-Nagoya_Aichi_Prefecture_Tokai_Chubu.html">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure class="right"><img src="images/stationNana.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Nana-chan&rsquo;s watermelon-smashing fit</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Before leaving the station, be sure to check out <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/VCSkoNiMXLQM4pyP7">Nana-chan</a> the 18-foot tall statue! Her dress changes to fit the current season - when I was there last June, she sported a summery watermelon getup. There&rsquo;s a fair amount of Nana-chan lore, too! According to <a href="http://kikuko-nagoya.com/html/nana-chan.html">official (sounding) sources</a>, she was born in Switzerland on April 28, 1973, and has a blood type of A-positive. Huh.</p>
<p>If you like your shopping chaotic, I&rsquo;ve got just the place for you - <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/1rv6HqaAuiTLRdc98">Village Vanguard &ldquo;exciting bookstore&rdquo;</a>. Entering Village Vanguard immediately assaults all of your senses: anime music blares from bluetooth speakers, and narrow aisles overflow with precarious stacks of plushes. While technically a &ldquo;bookstore&rdquo;, Village Vanguard is a one-stop shop for character goods (i.e. Ghibli, Mario, Minions), manga, knockoff streetwear, Japanese snacks, stationary&hellip; You get the idea. It&rsquo;s worth a visit even if you&rsquo;re not planning on buying!</p>
<figure><img src="images/villageVanguard.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>One of the more organized aisles in Village Vanguard. (<a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/S7G3e7Nd25zXp4R89">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="toyota-industry-museum">Toyota Industry Museum</h2>
<p>Most tourists don&rsquo;t interact much with the industrial history of Japan, which is a shame because it&rsquo;s really cool!
If you want a front-seat into Japan&rsquo;s development from rural backwater to industrial juggernaut, look no further than <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/xYp2jqSVMr2xPTmg7">The Toyota Commemorative Museum of Industry and Technology</a>! It&rsquo;s chock-full of interactive exhibits and machines straight from the factory floor, making you a participant in Toyota&rsquo;s industrial evolution from tiny textile firm to automotive megacorp.</p>
<figure><img src="images/industryHybridManga.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Toyota hybrid development, told via Manga</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The grand finale is a whole vehicle production line, motorized to assemble a car <em>right in front of you!</em> Then <em><strong>you</strong></em> get to run a mini-production line and injection-mold your own toy Toyota! If you have a mechanical bone in your body, this is a must-visit.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0Yj7uZaVGL8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="A prius being assembled in real-time! Color commentary by yours truly."></iframe>
</div>

<p>Finally, there&rsquo;s a showroom of Toyota&rsquo;s automotive &ldquo;greatest hits&rdquo;. I hear they&rsquo;ll even fire up the cars for visitors that ask nicely.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/industryLFA.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/industryCelica.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/industryGRYaris.jpeg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Lexus LFA</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Toyota Celica</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>GR Yaris (WRC car)</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>I enjoyed the factory without a tour, but in hindsight I&rsquo;d check out the English-speaking tours to really make the most of being there. While you&rsquo;re in the area, check out the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/j9shDiPwhVHuWsNY9">Noritake Garden</a> - it&rsquo;s another former factory, transformed into a serene urban garden.</p>
<figure><img src="images/industryRobotBand.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>No caption I could write will do this robot band justice.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="nagoya-station-food">Nagoya Station Food</h2>
<p>There are plenty of places to eat in and around Nagoya Station. Here are some of my favorites, and a link to the aforementioned <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/yr1yqAj7j5w6FQhb7">Nagoya Station area Google maps guide</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/7Fqp5jEBJTz5bfp1A">Shinya Ramen</a>
<ul>
<li>Look no further for authentic, no-frills ramen. There are only three things on the menu, and they&rsquo;re all some permutation of rich broth, thick noodles, and flavorful pork!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/pYSUUtQXrFG6dbJ8A">Masamune Fish</a>
<ul>
<li>Right next to Nagoya Station, this place has some great sashimi. If you come later at night, it&rsquo;s much more of an izakaya (pub) vibe, with beer and sake aplenty.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/g3BWoqWXUYxNVmoH6">Tsukemen TETSU</a>
<ul>
<li>Tsukemen tastes a lot like Ramen, but with more concentrated broth to dip noodles and pork into. Tsukemen Tetsu in Nagoya station was always packed, and for good reason! It&rsquo;s right next to the Starbucks overlook, so they pair well together.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/5B2PkMs9b6wJ2Fck9">The Tower Tavern</a>
<ul>
<li>Sometimes, nothing hits quite like a burger. Not a Samurai Mac or a <a href="https://tokyotreat.com/blog/8-of-the-weirdest-yet-delicious-burgers-in-japan">Burger King abomination</a>, just a normal, 100% beef hamburger. The Tower Tavern was my go-to in times like these.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/AUU2QsH5DaJJSmPB7">Gaburi Chicken</a>
<ul>
<li>Founded in Nagoya, this fried chicken restaurant is famous for its massive portion sizes and beer pairings.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/oQL5QMPEpn1PQ11t7">Sako Station Vending Machine</a>
<ul>
<li>This subway station is noteworthy because it was the only place I could consistently find canned Dr. Pepper. The more you know!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="downtown-nagoya-nagoya-castle-and-sakae">Downtown Nagoya (Nagoya Castle and Sakae)</h1>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve been to other Japanese cities, you&rsquo;ll immediately notice a different vibe in Nagoya&rsquo;s downtown. Here&rsquo;s the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/dSyWngmSJMxF2ssw9">downtown Nagoya Google maps guide</a>, so you can follow along!</p>
<h2 id="nagoya-castle">Nagoya Castle</h2>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/hommaruCastle.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Nagoya castle. In the Edo period, a thief apparently <a href="http://kikuko-nagoya.com/html/nagoya-castle.html">stole the golden Shachihoko statues using a giant kite.</a> Unknown whether this is legend or fact.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/xfxhRFMsbQyXMqJA7">Nagoya Castle</a> and the surrounding grounds are so gorgeous, it&rsquo;s hard to believe it was once a cutting-edge fortification. The flowering, tree-lined moats were to slow opposing forces, and the castle&rsquo;s coppery green hue comes from it&rsquo;s flame-resistant roofing. Even the gold Shachihoko (tiger-fish) statues, now a priceless symbol of Nagoya, would be re-cast into coins if money became tight. Samurai still roam the castle grounds today, but they&rsquo;re more the &ldquo;take your picture for 100 yen&rdquo; type.</p>
<p>As of my most recent visit, (Summer 2024) the castle itself is closed for an <a href="https://www.nagoyajo.city.nagoya.jp/en/tenshu/">extremely ambitious project</a> - to rebuild it from scratch, using only materials and techniques from the castle&rsquo;s original time period. Though the castle is closed for now, the <a href="https://www.nagoyajo.city.nagoya.jp/en/nagoyajo/honmarugoten/about/">Hommaru Palace</a> next door is still one of the most stunning pieces of traditional architecture in Japan. Hommaru is home to some amazing artwork and some pretty interesting quirks. Hommaru was the shogun&rsquo;s personal headquarters, so every room other than his is set at a lower elevation to show subordination. Not low enough - at 6'4 I definitely had a few close encounters with exquisitely crafted doorframes.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/hommaru.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/hommaruInterior.jpeg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Hommaru Palace (ft. Nagoya Castle)</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Hommaru Palace Interior</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>There&rsquo;s also an outdoor dining area near Nagoya Castle. At <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/jbtiqKRKjQtQbcMw8">Fujuyama 55</a>; you can munch Mazesoba (brothless ramen with extra beef) with a great view of the castle itself. Japanese shaved ice (kakigori) also goes great with Nagoya&rsquo;s hot summer days!</p>
<h2 id="sakae">Sakae</h2>
<figure><img src="images/sakaeFromOasis.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Sakae as seen from Oasis 21</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a chronic shopper or just love hustle and bustle, Sakae is your place. But Sakae is actually pretty unusual as far as Japanese downtowns go. Aboveground, there&rsquo;s a vibrant park spanning four city blocks. Hisaya-Odori park is dominated by Japan&rsquo;s oldest TV tower (and newest hotel), the Chubu Electric Mirai Tower. Non-guests can take an elevator to the top, but don&rsquo;t waste your money - my favorite view is right next door! Head over to the top of <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/YaeKKscGVS4rmsqX6">Oasis 21</a>, and take in the view from the Spaceship Aqua platform. The massive fountain spanning the length of the building isn&rsquo;t just artistic - it actually cools the open-air shopping mall directly below!</p>
<figure><img src="images/sakaeOasis21.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Oasis 21 from below.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Speaking of shops, where are they? A simple question with a surprisingly historic answer. Like other cities in Japan, Nagoya was pretty much leveled by firebombs in WWII. But unlike the other cities, automotive companies (<a href="#toyota-industry-museum">like Toyota!</a>) had some serious influence on the reconstruction effort. As a result, Nagoya was rebuilt from the ground up with vehicle traffic in mind. Since cars and people don&rsquo;t mix, a majority of the shops moved underground, into <a href="https://morethanrelo.com/en/lets-tour-nagoyas-underground-labyrinth/">Japan&rsquo;s oldest chikagai</a> (underground shopping center)!</p>
<figure><img src="images/crystalPlaza.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Sakae&rsquo;s underground Crystal Plaza (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/heiwa4126/404462298">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>While some may be quick to dismiss Sakae&rsquo;s underground shopping mall as car-pandering urbanism, it&rsquo;s actually pretty effective! Sakae is well-connected to Nagoya&rsquo;s extensive subway and bus system, and offers an air-conditioned respite from Aichi&rsquo;s hot, humid summers. It&rsquo;s just another way Nagoya zigs when other Japanese cities zag.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p>Here are a few of my favorite stores to visit in Sakae:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/kzxgNpyVHybZhM43A">Book-Off Super Bazaar</a>
<ul>
<li>Book-Off is Japan&rsquo;s premier used books, games, and music store - but Nagoya&rsquo;s Super Bazaar throws musical instruments, clothing, jewelry, and toys into the mix. Most used products from Japan are still in pretty good condition, and you can find a lot of retro games and rare records for discount prices!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/NfgqZFmscfxC6Z126">Tower Records</a>
<ul>
<li>Long-dead stateside, Tower Records still thrives in physical-media obsessed Japan. I was surprised at the depth of selection: <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/0hrb5WRiNlj8vh3WnCgXFq?si=XWB3_MWFSKOHFUbBrUBcwg">Kikagaku Moyo</a>, a psychedelic rock band with under 300k listeners? Every <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/2Ex4vjQ6mSh5woTlDWto6d?si=tYvRcieQQFGM6BMvOUD0DA">Masayoshi Takanaka</a> studio album? It&rsquo;s all here! Audiophiles take note: Japanese LPs are well regarded as higher-quality than the equivalent US pressings.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/RGoG2xQXVcdiSsHo7">Donguri Kyowakoku (Ghibli Store)</a>
<ul>
<li>The official store for all things Studio Ghibli. Definitely worth a look if you can&rsquo;t make it to <a href="#ghibli-park--aichi-expo-park--toyota-vehicle-museum">Ghibli Park</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/U7jjvRfTczKu3Wi88">Shonen Jump Store</a>
<ul>
<li>If you love shonen anime (think One Piece, Jujutsu Kaisen, Bleach, etc.) this is a must-visit. Nearly everything sold here can&rsquo;t be found in the US, so stock up!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/m7MTaay8WXR2qWxv7">Pokemon Center Nagoya</a>
<ul>
<li>Like Tokyo and Kyoto, Nagoya also has a Pokemon center gift shop. It&rsquo;s worth checking out, as the products differ by store - your favorite &lsquo;mon may only be here in Nagoya!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/Sq1L5rho5BhJDvtH9">T4 Nagoya (Ping Pong Bar)</a>
<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;s a bit pricey, but you can play ping-pong and sip craft beer right under the TV tower in Hisaya-Odori park!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<figure><img src="images/pokemonCenter.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Nagoya&rsquo;s Pokemon Center. The Magikarp is a play on Nagoya Castle&rsquo;s golden Shachihoko statues! (<a href="https://www.facebook.com/pokemonpickupjapan/posts/pok%C3%A9mon-center-nagoya-has-finished-its-transformation-the-pok%C3%A9mon-center-nagoya-/534813862641995/">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="downtown-nagoya-food">Downtown Nagoya Food:</h2>
<figure class="right"><img src="images/yabatonMascot.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Yabaton&rsquo;s pig mascot (<a href="https://www.pinterest.com/pin/123356477268765205/">image credit</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/txXQqtXsEYTs8XJq8">Misen &ldquo;Taiwan Ramen&rdquo;</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Neither from Taiwan nor ramen, Misen&rsquo;s famous &ldquo;Taiwan Ramen&rdquo; dish is a Nagoya must-have. As the legend goes, Taiwan Ramen was originally a cheap staff-only meal, but customers saw cooks chowing down on their lunch breaks and demanded the dish! Taiwan Ramen comes spicy, so order &ldquo;American flavor&rdquo; for some more tolerable heat. Fun fact - in Taiwan, this style of ramen is called &ldquo;Nagoya Ramen&rdquo;!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/RXwFfVWW2Wvi3qJM6">Miso Katsu Yabaton</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Of Nagoya&rsquo;s local dishes, Miso Katsu is probably the most famous. It&rsquo;s essentially tonkatsu (fried and breaded porkchop) with a generous helping of savory red miso sauce on top. Plenty of places serve it, but Yabaton is my favorite. (plus, they have the coolest mascot)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/uaFdBh2WDPwXWTrj9">Morning Service Breakfast</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Nearly every cafe in Nagoya has &ldquo;morning service&rdquo; - before 11:00 AM, any drink comes with small sandwich for free! My favorite was Tully&rsquo;s - they have a great location in the middle of Hisaya-Odori Park. Komeda&rsquo;s is great too!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/jVVY6fihJX8FtvQGA">Eggs &lsquo;n Things</a></p>
<ul>
<li>As expected from a Hawaiian place, every menu item with Spam is phenomenal. My favorite is the Spam Eggs Benedict! Also, it&rsquo;s the only place in Nagoya (that I found) that serves chocolate milk. Good to know.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="day-trips-and-other-activities">Day Trips and Other Activities</h1>
<p>Nagoya is a great jumping-off point for day trips. Here are a few of my favorites (and the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/igCakbRGqYuEiebi8">Nagoya day trips Google maps guide.</a>)</p>
<h2 id="ghibli-park--aichi-expo-park--toyota-vehicle-museum">Ghibli Park / Aichi Expo Park / Toyota Vehicle Museum</h2>
<p>Head east from Nagoya proper, and you&rsquo;ll eventually reach hallowed ground for any Studio Ghibli fan - <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/cY31MAtXPYGJQU2S6">Ghibli Park</a>.</p>
<figure><img src="images/ghibliTopshot.jpeg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>Designed by Hayao Miyazaki himself, Ghibli Park famously eschews rides for hyper-detailed environments that fully immerse visitors in the world of Ghibli. You can watch original short films that are only shown at the park - no photo or video is allowed. Tickets sell out months in advance, and I unfortunately wasn&rsquo;t able to get any ahead of my trip. If you&rsquo;re forgetful (like me), you can still get glimpses inside from the surrounding public park, like this <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/E6rMvVtDbWFsnsRL9">view of Satsuki and Mei&rsquo;s house from My Neighbor Totoro.</a> <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/kF7PrV9byavYudFv5">The local convenience store</a> even sells Ghibli merch, so you don&rsquo;t miss that side of the park either!</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/ghibliElevator.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/ghibliHowl.jpeg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Elevator inspired by Castle in the Sky (apparently&hellip;)</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Distant view of Howl&rsquo;s Moving Castle</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>But honestly, the surrounding park is pretty cool too! It was built to host world Expo 2005 to demonstrate cutting-edge green technology of the time, and the entire complex oozes that <a href="/posts/japanarch/">early-2000&rsquo;s architectural optimism</a> I&rsquo;ve written about before. If you&rsquo;re a transit fan, this park is a must-visit for exactly one reason - <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/umkskMGrphvvnVk4A">the Maglev</a>! That&rsquo;s right, this is the only place (outside of China and Korea) where you can ride a <em>levitating train</em>! The Linimo line may top out at only 62 mph, but it&rsquo;s still quieter and more compact than a conventional train.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/linimoAboveground.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/linimoTrain.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/linimoUnderground.jpeg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Aboveground portion of the Linimo Line</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Linimo&rsquo;s mascot</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Underground portion of the Linimo Line</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The tech in the Linimo line will be used in Japan&rsquo;s next generation SCMaglev, a bullet train that will max out at 375 miles per hour! Nagoya has a <a href="https://www.japan-guide.com/e/e3314.html">museum dedicated to the in-progress maglev project</a>, which I unfortunately haven&rsquo;t had the chance to visit. But I&rsquo;ve heard it&rsquo;s great!</p>
<p>One more stop on this line is the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/bH6PhoAqhuFABvez6">Toyota Automobile Museum</a>. Unlike the industry museum downtown, this museum is laser-focused on the history of the automobile. From the Model T to the Tesla Roadster, witness the evolution of the car through some of the best-restored and most beautiful vehicles I&rsquo;ve ever seen. It&rsquo;s not just Japanese cars, either! Another must-visit for car nuts like myself.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/automotiveMerc.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/automotiveGT.jpeg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="images/automotiveInsight.jpeg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>~1957 Mercedes-Benz 300 SL</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>~1970 Toyota 2000GT</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>~1999 Honda Insight</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="traditional-mountain-village-tsumago-juku">Traditional Mountain Village, Tsumago-juku</h2>
<figure><img src="images/countryTown.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>The sleepy town of Tsumago-juku.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure class="right"><img src="images/countryBridge.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Tsumago-juku&rsquo;s suspension bridge.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>What if you want to tread a little further from the beaten path? My favorite day trip from Nagoya is the sleepy town of <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/5zJ656AGp6wgn1o3A">Tsumago-juku</a>. Step off of the bus, and you&rsquo;ll find yourself 400 years back in time. Every building on the main drag has been painstakingly restored to Edo Period architecture and style.</p>
<p>Tsumago-Juku is Japan at a slower pace. It&rsquo;s the kind of place to take a scenic <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/aeSnF7JVtMWrSKN66">hike through some castle ruins</a>, sip tea in a mom-and-pop cafe, and chat with friendly locals. Once you&rsquo;re done for the day, I&rsquo;d recommend finishing up at one of Nagoya&rsquo;s many Onsen, or spa-like public hot springs. My fav was <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/dtHsXZevsJXa5UwMA">Sanno Onsen Kita-no-Yu</a> - it&rsquo;s massive and has everything from massage chairs to a food court. If you&rsquo;re worried about etiquette, this <a href="https://tokyocheapo.com/entertainment/how-to-onsen-in-japan/">Tokyo Cheapo article</a> has just about everything you need to know.</p>
<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h2>
<p>Whenever I recommend visiting Nagoya, the question always arises: &ldquo;OK, but what should I do there?&rdquo; My answer is always hard to articulate. To me, Nagoya is a collection of small but significant experiences - ogura toast in Hisaya-Odori park, riding a maglev to Ghibli Park, and sampling street food on Osu shopping street. If you&rsquo;re the type of tourist to blitz through a city&rsquo;s landmarks in a day, you won&rsquo;t get much out of Nagoya. But if you want to experience the quirks and idiosyncracies of daily life in Japan, Nagoya delivers in a way tourist-curated cities can&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>But back to the question this article set out to answer - Is Nagoya Boring? Don&rsquo;t let me tell you - next time you&rsquo;re in Japan, pay Nagoya a visit and decide for yourself!<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
<p><figure><img src="images/baseballMatsuri.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>With some friends at Atsuta Matsuri (festival)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="images/baseballMeNagoyaSign.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>When I asked some Nagoyans to take my picture here, they actually laughed at me. Worth it!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My hometown of Dallas is <a href="https://omny.fm/shows/north-texas-wants-to-know/everything-you-never-knew-about-dallas-underground">infamous for a similar downtown tunnel network</a>. Sakae is a lot better!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>If Nagoya&rsquo;s already made your itinerary, I cannot recommend <a href="http://kikuko-nagoya.com/html/festivals-in-Nagoya.html">Kikuko-san&rsquo;s Nagoya Homepage</a> enough! She&rsquo;s compiled an exhaustive list of every festival, matsuri, and event in Nagoya - definitely worth checking out if your trip aligns with the schedule! My favorite was Atsuta Matsuri, which is on June 5th every year. There&rsquo;s also a Sumo tournament every year in the summer, and plenty of baseball games to check out as well.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>☕ Introducing CafeMatrix</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cafematrix/</link>
			<pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 21:55:31 -0800</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cafematrix/</guid>
			<description>The internet has undoubtedly anxiously awaited this next installment of my personal blog. Having revolutionized the spheres of architecture and education alike, what worlds are left to conquer? The answer is the flashy, cutthroat realm of restaurant ranking. A world that as of December 28, 2024, will never be the same. Introducing the new, paradigm-shifting CafeMatrix!
Note: please read the above paragraph with a heavy dose of sarcasm
The Problem  Sweet Eugene&amp;rsquo;s (image from Yelp)</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The internet has undoubtedly anxiously awaited this next installment of my personal blog. Having revolutionized the spheres of <a href="/posts/japanarch/">architecture</a> and <a href="/posts/auto-grader-update/">education</a> alike, what worlds are left to conquer? The answer is the flashy, cutthroat realm of restaurant ranking. A world that as of December 28, 2024, will never be the same. Introducing the new, paradigm-shifting <a href="http://cafematrix.net">CafeMatrix</a>!</p>
<p><em>Note: please read the above paragraph with a heavy dose of sarcasm</em></p>
<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>
<figure class="right"><img src="eugenes.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Sweet Eugene&rsquo;s (image from <a href="https://www.yelp.com/biz/sweet-eugenes-house-of-java-college-station">Yelp</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Where I went to college, there was (and likely still is) a cafe called <em>Sweet Eugene&rsquo;s</em>. <em>Sweet&rsquo;s</em> was an otherwise normal cafe, but with an interior like a garage sale on acid. Couches and tables shared floor space with renaissance busts and industrial equipment. Throw in a closing time of 2:00 AM and plenty of seating, and you have a seemingly perfect cafe. And yet, Sweet Eugene&rsquo;s had an Achilles heel: their WiFi was abysmal. After yet another unsuccessful attempt to study at Sweet&rsquo;s, I came to a revelation - <strong>the 0-5 star scale is woefully inadequate for reviewing this (or any) cafe.</strong></p>
<p>Think about it: depending on a variety of factors, a cafe may be perfect for studying but horrible for hanging out! Or the opposite, or neither, or both! But what if we identified these individual factors (i.e. seating availability, Wi-Fi, coffee cost, etc.) and used them to calculate a cafe&rsquo;s &ldquo;study rating&rdquo; or a &ldquo;hangout rating&rdquo;? This was the seed that eventually grew into my newest and nerdiest project, <a href="http://cafematrix.net/">CafeMatrix</a> (repo <a href="https://github.com/ethan-cope/CafeMatrix">here</a>).</p>
<h2 id="common-criteria--usage-for-cafematrix">Common Criteria / Usage for CafeMatrix</h2>
<p>How <em>can</em> we rate a cafe, then? I normally go to a cafe for 2 reasons - to get work done, or to hang out with friends. My third decision factor is <em>value for money</em> - whether the experience is worth what I&rsquo;m paying for or not.
And wouldn&rsquo;t you know it, CafeMatrix ranks each cafe on 3 criteria - <em>Ambiance</em>, <em>Study Suitability</em>, and <em>Value / Money</em>. Then, each criteria (or in CafeMatrix lingo, <em>index</em>) is plotted as an axis of a 3d plot, giving you an at-a-glance rating of that cafe&rsquo;s rating.</p>
<figure class="small"><img src="cafeMatrix.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>CafeMatrix landing page!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure class="right"><img src="SubMatrixBars.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>SubMatrix breakdown for one of my favs, Water &amp; Coffee Lab</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>But let&rsquo;s get more granular! How do we know <em>why</em> a cafe scored what it did? Every index&rsquo;s score is calculated from 3 sub-indices, which describe specific pros and cons of each cafe (i.e. internet speed, menu). So three factors will contribute to a cafe&rsquo;s ambiance score, another three for Value, and a final three for Study Suitability. See a description of these below:</p>
<h3 id="1-ambiance-index">1. Ambiance Index</h3>
<ul>
<li>Vibe - Is the decor / vibe good?</li>
<li>Seating Availability - Are seats easy to find and the cafe generally non-crowded?</li>
<li>Spark - Anything special about this place? Nice baristas? tabletop games? Becomes a bar at night? Active part of community?</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-value-index">2. Value Index</h3>
<ul>
<li>Taste - How good are the drinks here?</li>
<li>Cost - How expensive are the drinks here?</li>
<li>Menu - Do they have cool specials? Do they roast or sell their own beans? Good food / cocktails too? All that goes here.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-study-index">3. Study Index</h3>
<ul>
<li>Space Suitability - How good is the space for studying? Big tables with room to spread out?</li>
<li>Tech-Friendliness - How fast is the inte here? Are there lots of charging outlets?</li>
<li>Accessibility - How long does it stay open? Is it easy to park at or get to?</li>
</ul>
<p>SubMatricies are probably the coolest thing CafeMatrix does. With SubMatrices, users can rate cafes however they like, and use those ratings to make intelligent decisions beyond a 1-5 star rating. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<figure class="left"><img src="SubMatrixHitsMisses.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>At-a-glance pros/cons on the home screen!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-making-of-cafematrix">The Making of CafeMatrix</h2>
<p>As the longest-running project I&rsquo;ve worked on (about a year, off and on!), CafeMatrix has evolved a LOT since it&rsquo;s initial concept. As with all of my projects, the end goal is to learn something new while solving a real problem. But since the beginning, CafeMatrix three philosophical foundations:</p>
<h3 id="foundation-1-cafematrix-should-be-easy-to-use">Foundation 1. CafeMatrix <strong>should be easy to use</strong></h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure this project is too nerdy to every attain mass appeal. But one of my goals for CafeMatrix was a radically simple user experience. So many websites accidentally (<a href="https://www.mobilespoon/2019/06/20-dark-patterns-to-avoid-in-products.html">or even purposefully</a>!) kneecap user experience. The fun part of CafeMatrix was building a webapp as they should be - simple, intuitive, and user-respecting.</p>
<h3 id="foundation-2-cafematrix-should-not-use-a-login-system--database-backend">Foundation 2. CafeMatrix <strong>should not use a login system / database backend</strong></h3>
<p>Quick backstory on this one: The browser game <em><a href="https://www.coolmathgames.com/0-blacksmith-lab">Blacksmith Lab</a></em> blew my mind as a kid, simply because it remembered my progress after I closed the tab! No logins, no two-factor authentication, just good ol' cookies! I knew I had to do something similar with CafeMatrix. In an age where every site you visit needs your email, phone number, and social security number to provide basic functionality, I wanted CafeMatrix to be a breath of fresh air. <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
<h3 id="foundation-3-cafematrix-should-be-mobile-first">Foundation 3. CafeMatrix <strong>should be mobile-first</strong></h3>
<p>As the project evolved, I found myself using CafeMatrix on my phone far more than on my laptop. This eventually led to an entire UI redesign around <a href="https://dash-bootstrap-components.opensource.faculty.ai/">bootstrap</a>, allowing dynamic re-sizing of windows to prioritize mobile without inconveniencing laptop users.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next-for-cafematrix">What&rsquo;s next for CafeMatrix?</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m writing another article about CafeMatrix soon, about all of the things I learned from this project. After all, this is the first time I&rsquo;ve self-hosted a website! It&rsquo;s also the first time I&rsquo;ve built a website purely for public usage. I don&rsquo;t have any current plans to update CafeMatrix beyond it&rsquo;s current state, but if there&rsquo;s enough interest I may add HTTPS. I put that &ldquo;buy me a coffee&rdquo; link on as a joke, but if there&rsquo;s enough interest, who knows what will happen! 🙃</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Anticipated Question: How can we possibly rate something on criteria subjective as &ldquo;vibe&rdquo; or &ldquo;spark&rdquo;? The short answer is, embrace the subjectivity! Does Starbucks taste like a 1 to you? Is your favorite coffee joint a 5? Then put that in the matrix! These rankings aren&rsquo;t meant to be objective truth - they&rsquo;re meant to be a resource to help decide where <em>you</em> want to study / hang out. Go wild!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>The clunkiest part of CafeMatrix is undoubtedly the .tsv backup process, but this is a direct result of the internet&rsquo;s evolution path. <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2004/06/13/how-microsoft-lost-the-api-war/">Joel Spolsky predicted this back in in 2004</a>: an increasing number of programs people use aren&rsquo;t installed onto their PC, they&rsquo;re on the web. Webapps typically store user data in the cloud, historically for security (good) and more recently for ad tracking and targeting (bad). The alternative to this is storing user data on the user&rsquo;s computer (CafeMatrix&rsquo;s approach), which has potential to be even more convenient than the cloud approach (imagine - no passwords!). Local storage access for web apps is improving (see the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/File_System_API">File System API</a> - maybe more websites will move this direction in the future!&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🚝 Exploring Las Colinas&#39; Mothballed Monorail</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 16:32:24 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/irvingapt/</guid>
			<description>Sign at the entrance of the APT
  On the surface, Dallas looks like just another cookie-cutter commuter city. Compared to Austin&amp;rsquo;s booming tech industry and laid-back vibe, Dallas&#39; historic hyperfocus on sprawling office parks has always felt a bit clinical. But the combination of this all-work all-the-time culture and a early 80&amp;rsquo;s real-estate boom led to some crazy planning experiments, and none were as crazy as the Irving&amp;rsquo;s Las Colinas district.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center"><img src="APTSign.jpg"
         alt="Sign for the entrance of the APT"/><figcaption>
            <p>Sign at the entrance of the APT</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On the surface, Dallas looks like just another cookie-cutter commuter city. Compared to Austin&rsquo;s booming tech industry and laid-back vibe, Dallas' historic hyperfocus on sprawling office parks has always felt a bit clinical. But the combination of this all-work all-the-time culture and a early 80&rsquo;s real-estate boom led to some crazy planning experiments, and none were as crazy as the Irving&rsquo;s Las Colinas district. Real estate mogul Ben Carpenter&rsquo;s original plan was to transform his family&rsquo;s ranch (<em>El Ranchito de Las Colinas</em>) into a master-planned community. No expense was spared - Las Colinas was a place where (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220712160053/https://www.dmagazine.com/publications/d-magazine/1987/august/magnificent-obsession/">as D Magazine put it in 1987</a>): <em>&ldquo;you could gaze out your office window past a sparkling Lake Carolyn&hellip; watch shoppers take a water taxi down the canals to lunch; where you could walk out of your office and be on one of four championship golf courses in ten minutes&hellip; never leaving the manicured environs of Las Colinas.&quot;</em> But Las Colinas' boldest stroke was indisputably its <strong>Area Personal Transit</strong> system.</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="APTTrainImage.png"
         alt="Two APT cars near Bell Tower Station."/><figcaption>
            <p>Two APT cars near Bell Tower Station. Image from <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160220151818/https://dcurd.org/pdfs/APT%20Brochure%205-31-13.pdf">APT renovation brochure</a>, circa 2013.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="how-how-it-started">How how it started</h1>
<p>Emphasis on <em>Personal</em>, especially in contrast to <em>Mass</em> transit. You see, the urban planners of Las Colinas didn&rsquo;t want some plebeian subway system. No, they needed a bleeding-edge solution that could zip commuters from skyscraper to skyscraper in climate-controlled comfort. They needed an APT.</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="APTCommandCenter.png"
         alt="The APT&#39;s futuristic command center"/><figcaption>
            <p>The APT&rsquo;s futuristic (for 1980) <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160220151818/https://dcurd.org/pdfs/APT%20Brochure%205-31-13.pdf">command center</a>. Note the system map on the wall, with room for line extensions that never came.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So in the summer of 1989 the much-awaited APT system opened to an eager public. The stars of the show were AEG-Westinghouse&rsquo;s cutting-edge transit vehicles. The APT shuttles looked straight off a Star Wars soundstage - all sharp creases and aggressive angles. Despite the radwood rocketship styling, the APT wasn&rsquo;t fast. But it was entirely automated - an impressive feat given the level of technology available in 1986! Pressing a button on the platform would summon an APT shuttle to whisk you to one of 3 other stations on the line, all entirely driverless!</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="JohnBellMap.gif"
         alt="Map of present and future APT system from Jon Bell&#39;s excellent blog."/><figcaption>
            <p>Map of present and future APT system from <a href="http://www.jtbell.net/transit/Irving/">Jon Bell&rsquo;s excellent blog.</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Of course, more stations were originally planned. What exists today is just a small subset of the intended 5.5 mile loop. But around the time APT started rolling, things in Las Colinas took a turn for the worse. <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2023-12-06/at-50-the-texas-business-hub-of-las-colinas-looks-beyond-office-space">Oil prices dropped and investment dried up</a>, turning Las Colinas' densest office complexes into a ghost towns. Without commuters to move, the APT was deemed &ldquo;too expensive&rdquo; and mothballed in 1993. In 2013, the Dallas Area Rapid Transit (DART) Orange Line opened nearby, giving the APT a second lease on life. While the automation system didn&rsquo;t survive, the APT saw decent utilization until Covid-19 gave the city an excuse to kill the project again.</p>
<figure class="center"><img src="StonehengeSupports.jpg"
         alt="Stonehenge-like guideway supports for the cancelled red line expansion. (Photo credit: Jon Bell&amp;rsquo;s transit blog)"/><figcaption>
            <p>Stonehenge-like guideway supports for the cancelled red line expansion. (Photo credit: <a href="http://www.jtbell.net/transit/images/Irving/Supports.jpg">Jon Bell&rsquo;s transit blog</a>)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="how-its-going">How it&rsquo;s going</h1>
<p>So, what&rsquo;s left of the APT system in May 2024? Quite a lot! When I had some time to kill in Irving, I found that many stations and supporting infrastructure is still open to the public! Let&rsquo;s start with the crown jewel of the system: Bell Tower Station.</p>
<h2 id="bell-tower-station">Bell Tower Station</h2>
<figure class="center"><img src="BellTower.jpg"
         alt="The APT&#39;s Bell Tower Station in 2024"/><figcaption>
            <p>The APT&rsquo;s Bell Tower Station in 2024. Note the glassed-off passenger platform peeking through the yellow columns directly right of the bell tower.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure class="center"><img src="BellTowerCanalOverhead.jpg"
         alt="APT guideway, weaving between skyscrapers above Las Colinas&#39; faux-Venice canals"/><figcaption>
            <p>APT guideway, weaving between skyscrapers above Las Colinas' faux-Venice canals</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I was even able to enter Bell Tower Station, which looks pretty good (considering its technically been closed for 4 years)!</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="BellTowerStaircase.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="BellTowerHallway.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Bell Tower Station&rsquo;s ground-level staircase</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Platform access hallway. The slightly raised tile flooring on the right likely hosted ticket machines.</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>I got as far as the former turnstile station, where access to the platform was blocked by foreboding steel shutters.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="BellTowerInteriorEthan.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="BellTowerInteriorJONBELL.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Platform waiting area, sadly blocked off since the system&rsquo;s closure in 2020</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Platform waiting area circa 2002 (<a href="http://www.jtbell.net/transit/Irving/">from Jon Bell&rsquo;s blog</a>)</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Bell Tower Station was a sort of central station for the APT, handling traffic from both the red and blue lines.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="Downline.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="Upline.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Downline from Bell Tower Station, towards 600 Las Colinas Blvd. (Previously Cigna Tower)</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Upline towards DART connection and Urban Towers, through another Venice-inspired canal</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="tower-909-and-dart-connection">Tower 909 and DART Connection</h2>
<figure class="center"><img src="Tower909.jpg"
         alt="The APT&#39;s 2012 Tower 909 expansion."/><figcaption>
            <p>The APT&rsquo;s 2012 Tower 909 expansion. The APT station itself is behind the trees on the far left.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In 2013, the Tower 909 APT station added a pedestrian bridge and elevator service to the then-new DART orange line. According to Jon Bell, this led to <a href="http://www.jtbell.net/transit/Irving/">an increase in &ldquo;commuter-type riders&rdquo;</a>, improving ridership numbers. Today, the pedestrian bridge is still open, but the platform is once again fenced off.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="BridgePlusDart.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="DartAptSign.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Another view of the pedestrian bridge, flanked by DART&rsquo;s Urban Center station.</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Even the DART&rsquo;s artwork (Dartwork?) references the APT!</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>This seems like a massive oversight; DART built their elevator tower right in the path of the APT tracks, <strong>actively blocking</strong> any further extension of the blue line! Was Las Colinas really that pessimistic about post-renovation ridership?</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="909Platform1.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="909Platform2.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Tower 909&rsquo;s APT platform. It didn&rsquo;t even run on weekends!</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>APT tracks to nowhere. The footbridge this picture was taken from blocks the blue line from expanding further east</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="urban-towers">Urban Towers</h2>
<figure class="center"><img src="UrbanTowers.jpg"
         alt="The APT guideway entering Urban Towers."/><figcaption>
            <p>The APT guideway entering Urban Towers.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>One company was so invested in the APT that they built a station at the heart of their headquarters! That company was <a href="https://www.dallasnews.com/business/real-estate/2013/09/03/california-investor-buys-las-colinas-tower-complex/">Xerox</a>, who abandoned the complex sometime after its construction in 1984. Their former Xerox Center is now called &ldquo;Urban Towers&rdquo;, which still <a href="http://urban-towers.com/home.axis">advertises the APT</a> as an amenity despite the system&rsquo;s 2020 closure.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="UrbanTowersExpansion.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="UrbanTowersApt.png" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>The APT planned on expanding north of Urban Towers, too. (Photo credit: <a href="http://www.jtbell.net/transit/Irving/">Jon Bell&rsquo;s Blog</a>)</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>Interior of Urban Towers' APT station, from <a href="http://urban-towers.com/home.axis">Urban Towers' marketing vid</a>.</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="the-future-of-the-apt">The Future of the APT?</h2>
<p>Will the APT reopen? I&rsquo;d love to be optimistic, but things look pretty bleak. A <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2023-12-06/at-50-the-texas-business-hub-of-las-colinas-looks-beyond-office-space">flurry of new development</a> has been built over the planned APT right-of-way. New tracks could be added, but would never be as organically integrated as the first-gen sections. Besides, any expansion seems unthinkable to the city. In their eyes, the APT is an eyesore, a footnote. As it stands, the APT is <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210422164803/https://dcurd.org/apt-system/">closed indefinitely</a>.</p>
<p>So, did the APT even matter? I think so. The very existence of the APT exemplifies a certain militant optimism; this belief that cutting-edge technology can reshape the way business is done and life is lived. Even if transit-integrated communities didn&rsquo;t change the world, the APT stands as a reminder to continue seeking creative solutions to everyday problems. Maybe that&rsquo;s a wildly idealistic takeaway to draw from a mothballed monorail. But hey, Las Colinas still operates <a href="https://irving.gondola.com/about/">Venetian gondola cruises</a> in landlocked North Texas. The place oozes optimism; so sue me if some of it rubbed off!</p>
<p>More APT Resources:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KtABnF158Gg">Las Colinas' video about the APT</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Las-Colinas-Americas-Premier-Development/dp/0960935037">Las Colinas: The Inside Story of America&rsquo;s Premier Urban Development (book)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.jtbell.net/transit/Irving/">Jon Bell&rsquo;s transit blog</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nycsubway.org/wiki/Las_Colinas_Area_Personal_Transit">NYCSubway.org (transit wiki with APT info)</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>On Personal Projects and Giving Up (Echo-Matic Deluxe Update)</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 15:39:53 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</guid>
			<description>Personal projects often feel like a weird limbo between work and play. Starting a project motivated by nothing but passion and a willingness to learn is great. Even if the initial enthusiasm fades, it&amp;rsquo;s still worth it to power through. A finished project is often its own satisfaction. But when all personal interest in the project evaporates, even the most simple tasks become tedious. Every time I think about my gutted Marantz tape deck project, I find myself caring less and less.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Personal projects often feel like a weird limbo between work and play.
Starting a project motivated by nothing but passion and a willingness to learn is great.
Even if the initial enthusiasm fades, it&rsquo;s still worth it to power through. A finished project is often its own satisfaction.
But when all personal interest in the project evaporates, even the most simple tasks become tedious.
Every time I think about my gutted Marantz tape deck project, I find myself caring less and less.
My recent move to Santa Clara was the final excuse I needed; I&rsquo;m no longer working on the DIY tape echo project.</p>
<figure><img src="IMG_0630.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Rest In Peace, Echo-Matic Deluxe!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Maybe some context would help.
When I started this project, I thought that analog circuit design, specifically for audio applications, would be my <em>calling</em> in life.
I loved music, and my major was EE. What more needed to be said?
As it turns out, quite a bit.
Sure, I passed my analog classes, but all of the cool stuff I wanted to do seemed locked behind a barrier of pedantic prerequisite knowledge.
At the same time, I realized I was perfectly fine with my existing tape echo simulator, which had luxuries like functional knobs and a power supply that wasn&rsquo;t a fire hazard.
But hey, at least the prototype worked, right?</p>
<p>Well, that was the final nail in the project&rsquo;s coffin: even when the deck was working, it <em>didn&rsquo;t even sound that great</em>.
Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, it did this cool distorted slapback sound really well. But other than that, it was a one-trick pony.
The delay rate wasn&rsquo;t variable, so I couldn&rsquo;t get rhythmic, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/76JhicgPtW4zbN72tpnMyA?si=a73821ccbcc14400">Slowdive-style</a> tones out of it.
Self-oscillation was inevitable, and the feedback knob did almost nothing to curb it.
By the time these problems manifested, my passion for the Echo-Matic Deluxe was entirely spent.
I just wanted to move on.</p>
<p>So even though it pains me to give up, I&rsquo;m pulling the plug on my Echo-Matic Deluxe project. I hope that any of the resources I&rsquo;ve created are helpful to those tackling the same project. Happy Debugging!</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Aa0K1hSIZt8" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="The only remaining demo of the Echo-Matic Special"></iframe>
</div>

]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Japan&#39;s Early-2000&#39;s Architectural Nostalgia</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 01:00:07 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</guid>
			<description>The architectural definition of &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;1 has always been a moving target. Every year, once &amp;ldquo;stylistically cutting-edge&amp;rdquo; buildings slip into the realm of &amp;ldquo;dated&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cliche&amp;rdquo;. And the other day, I finally stumbled on across a building that proved this point. Nagoya&amp;rsquo;s Sasashima-Ribu station is totally representative of a particular architectural style; one that, at the time of it&amp;rsquo;s construction, was synonymous with &amp;ldquo;modern architecture&amp;rdquo;. But a quarter of a century has separated innovation from trend, revealing a slew of early 2000&amp;rsquo;s quintessential quirks.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The architectural definition of &ldquo;modern&rdquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> has always been a moving target.
Every year, once &ldquo;stylistically cutting-edge&rdquo; buildings slip into the realm of &ldquo;dated&rdquo; and &ldquo;cliche&rdquo;.
And the other day, I finally stumbled on across a building that proved this point.
Nagoya&rsquo;s Sasashima-Ribu station is totally representative of a particular architectural style; one that, at the time of it&rsquo;s construction, was synonymous with &ldquo;modern architecture&rdquo;.
But a quarter of a century has separated innovation from trend, revealing a slew of early 2000&rsquo;s quintessential quirks.
So let&rsquo;s examine a building that the &ldquo;architecturally modern&rdquo; has since evolved past.</p>
<p><em>Note: This post is written from a total lack of qualified architectural training. I&rsquo;m just a big fan of this architectural style, and I was surprised that I couldn&rsquo;t find a name or movement associated with it aside from catch-all &ldquo;postmodernism&rdquo;. As such, I humbly propose some interim nomenclature: &ldquo;00&rsquo;s geometric&rdquo;.</em></p>
<figure><img src="ExteriorShot.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Exterior view from Aichi Daigakou</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As a case study, let&rsquo;s take a look at the <em>Sasashima-Raibu Station</em>. At the time of it&rsquo;s construction, Aichi was hosting the environmentally-themed <em>World Expo 2005</em>.
The station itself was constructed in 2005 along with the rest of the Aonami line, which served as a transportation link to the expo&rsquo;s campus. Being built for such a high-profile event, The station&rsquo;s architecture is truly a &ldquo;greatest hits&rdquo; of 00&rsquo;s geometric themes.
Simple shapes define the station&rsquo;s facade. A shed-style roof covers the main station building, which complements the symmetrical, arched walkway coverings.
Only the elevator shaft is square; the rest of the design is dominated by swooping contours and shallow angles, evoking (to me) themes of rolling waves.
Gentle curves are a common theme that starkly contrasts to the imposing, rigid facades of modernist or brutalist buildings.
In fact, 00&rsquo;s geometric structures often seem friendly and inviting, despite being built with similar materials as their modernist counterparts.</p>
<figure><img src="platformWithBuilding.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>View from platform 1</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Let&rsquo;s dig a little further into these materials. 00&rsquo;s geometric buildings mainly utilize plate glass and steel, but in unexpected ways.
You see, gentle curves are very difficult to achieve using plate glass, because it doesn&rsquo;t bend easily. For this reason, modernist structures are often massive boxes of steel and glass.
00&rsquo;s Geometric buildings, on the other hand, seek to defy the limitations of their medium.
Smaller panels of glass are arranged to create low-resolution curves. Steel is bowed into gentle arcs, purely for the sake of adornment.
There is a sense of techno-utopianism in these structures: we have the technology to bend steel and glass to our will: not to improve function, but for form alone.
While Sasashima-raibu&rsquo;s view from platform 1 sports numerous examples of this, I think this style is best exhibited by Itsuko Hasegawa&rsquo;s work.
For example, <em>Ryutopia Performing Arts Center</em> utilizes segments of floor-to-ceiling plate glass to create a (some would argue superfluously) circular arena.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
<figure><img src="ryutopia.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Hasegawa&rsquo;s Ryutopia Performing Arts Center</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>While undoubtedly striking, steel and plate glass aren&rsquo;t particularly &ldquo;welcoming&rdquo;. Using these materials alone, buildings could come off as clinical or intimidating.
To compensate, 00&rsquo;s Geometric structures utilize vibrant, bold hues on seemingly normal objects.
Just take a look at the elevator passageway at Sasashima-raibu station: the entire elevator shaft is painted a royal blue, which complements the purple of the right-hand lighting nicely. Even the subway line&rsquo;s trademark color is a shade of deep teal. Imagine this hallway without those splashes of color!  Beautiful, sure, but nonetheless bleak and lifeless. Primary-school pigmentation gives the station a sense of openness and friendliness, which can make an otherwise unfamiliar subway station feel less intimidating.</p>
<figure><img src="ElevatorColorSplash.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Outdoor elevator passageway</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>All of the above points stand in direct contrast with Modernism. Where Modernist buildings seek to impose, 00&rsquo;s Geometrics seek to invite. Stoic, rigid materials are bent and stretched beyond their limits to create simple geometric shapes. Splashes of color invite people to engage with the building&rsquo;s space, while simultaneously rejecting the stodgy shackles of Modernism. This is the architecture of the early 2000&rsquo;s, where change was right around the corner. The Cold War was over, and large-scale peace seemed to be working. The internet was promising to connect everyone and everything. All of the world&rsquo;s problems seemed to be imminently solvable by technology, which would accelerate humanity&rsquo;s progress towards a brighter tomorrow.
We built the buildings of this imminent, techno-utopian future, and 00&rsquo;s Geometric was the result.
While that future never came, these silly, optimistic buildings remain a testament of the era&rsquo;s bright-eyed enthusiasm.
Every time I see one, I&rsquo;m reminded that the future doesn&rsquo;t have to be bleak. Not too long ago, the sky wasn&rsquo;t falling.</p>
<h2 id="more-examples">More Examples</h2>
<p><figure><img src="BuildingInterior.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Sasashima-raibu Station (2005. Nagoya, JP)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="jeb.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Jack E. Brown building (2005. College Station, TX)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="o21.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Oasis21 Bus Terminal (2002. Nagoya, JP)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure><img src="bdome.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Battle Dome (2002. Fictional, Pokemon Ruby/Sapphire)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Note: Here, I&rsquo;m using the word &ldquo;modern&rdquo; to refer to buildings that the average person would consider high-tech or new. This is unrelated to the architectural movement of Modernism.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Image credit <a href="https://alg.jp/en/work/ryutopia/">here</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Japan&#39;s Most Iconic Model Cars Come Out Of Vending Machines</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 01:00:15 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</guid>
			<description>Remember those 25-cent gumball machines? The ones where you could trade a quarter for a gumball older than the dotcom crash? Imagine that, but instead of a chunk of crusty candy, you win a random 1/64th scale model car. That&amp;rsquo;s essentially Gachapon!
 Bandai Namco&amp;rsquo;s toy vending machines are addictively simple. Insert cash (1), twist dial (2), and collect model (3). Since the 1970&amp;rsquo;s, Gachapon machines have dispensed billions of anime figurines, sushi keychains, and (most notably), tiny scale vehicles.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Remember those 25-cent gumball machines?
The ones where you could trade a quarter for a gumball older than the dotcom crash?
Imagine that, but instead of a chunk of crusty candy, you win a random 1/64th scale model car.
That&rsquo;s essentially Gachapon!</p>
<figure class="left"><img src="machExample.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>Bandai Namco&rsquo;s toy vending machines are addictively simple.
Insert cash <strong>(1)</strong>, twist dial <strong>(2)</strong>, and collect model <strong>(3)</strong>.
Since the 1970&rsquo;s, Gachapon machines have dispensed billions of anime figurines, sushi keychains, and (most notably), tiny scale vehicles.
For vehicle Gacha, each machine is dedicated to a specific make and model.
Certain things are randomized: you may win one with a body kit, rare paint color, or a specific trim level.
Whole subcultures exist around the trading and collecting of these tiny models.
When I first came to Japan, it didn&rsquo;t take long for these miniature machines to steal my heart - I was hooked!</p>
<p>I was most surprised by the sheer variety of models offered in the Gacha parlors.
Of course, sports cars and big trucks were well represented.
But some of the most popular machines were stocked with weirder, less well-known vehicles.
I started to wonder: what made those cars special enough to warrant a dedicated Gacha machine?
Was there really that much demand for a toy machine that only dispenses minivans?
The more I dove down the rabbit hole of fan sites and forums, the more I learned about the unique history of each of these cars.
In one way or another, each of these vehicles are icons of Japanese car culture &ndash; not because of their performance or styling, but because of their <em>stories</em>.
So here are the stories behind Japan&rsquo;s most iconic cars, and why they&rsquo;re worth your gumball money.</p>
<h2 id="nissan-cima-1988-1990">Nissan Cima (1988-1990)</h2>
<figure class="right"><img src="cimamach.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>Why did no one tell me about Nissan&rsquo;s late-80&rsquo;s rear-wheel-drive luxobarge?
At a colossal (for Japan) 193 in long, the Nissan Cedric/Gloria Cima was almost as big as a Lincoln Continental!
Why did Nissan only sell this tank in Japan, where big vehicles are taxed to oblivion?</p>
<p>Given it&rsquo;s economic context, the Cima starts to make sense.
In the late 80&rsquo;s, Japan was in a period known as the <em>baburu keiki</em> (bubble economy).
During this time, the yen was strong and interest rates were low.
Many used this opportunity to invest in real estate, which <a href="https://internationalbanker.com/history-of-financial-crises/japans-lost-decade-1992/">drove investment asset prices up nationwide.</a>
More growth meant more disposable income, and what better way to flex your wealth than an absurdly expensive car?
Investors with newfound cash flocked to the Cima: over 35,000 found a home in it&rsquo;s first model year alone!
The Cima&rsquo;s popularity was so shocking that period media invented the term <a href="https://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2022/03/31/business/corporate-business/nissan-cima-discontinued/">&ldquo;Cima Phenomenon&rdquo;</a> to describe Japan&rsquo;s increasing obsession with luxury autos.</p>
<p>The Cima was the ultimate JDM baller car for a few reasons.
In Japan, wheelbase and displacement taxes make it expensive to own anything larger than a kei car.
As a result, big vehicles carry some <em>serious</em> clout.
To capitalize on this, the Cima was built <a href="https://www.curbsideclassic.com/curbside-classics-asian/curbside-classic-1988-nissan-gloria-cima-fpy31-type-ii-limited-an-infinitely-better-version-of-the-infiniti-beta-version/">as large as legislation would allow</a>, making it one of the first Japanese &ldquo;super-sedans&rdquo;.
The Cima complimented this imposing size with cutting-edge tech.
Features like a <a href="https://www.nissan-global.com/EN/HERITAGE/cedric_cimatype_ii_limited.html">twin-cam turbo V6, an integrated CRT television, and electronic air suspension</a> all added to the Cima&rsquo;s hyper-luxury image.
Technology was the Cima&rsquo;s main selling point against it&rsquo;s bitter rival, the Toyota Crown.
While the Crown&rsquo;s legacy far outstrips the Cima&rsquo;s, Nissan&rsquo;s first super-sedan carries clout even today.
Otherwise there wouldn&rsquo;t be a gacha machine dedicated to it!</p>
<h2 id="autozam-az-1-1992-1994">Autozam AZ-1 (1992-1994)</h2>
<figure class="left"><img src="az1mach.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>Let&rsquo;s set the scene: It&rsquo;s 1992. You&rsquo;re a middle-class Japanese salaryman who just got a bonus. What subcompact sports car do you buy?
Autozam aimed to answer this question with the absolutely insane, no-holds-barred AZ-1.</p>
<p>Unveiled at the 1989 Tokyo Motor Show, the production AZ-1 was originally a Suzuki project, abandoned and sold to Mazda.
The AZ-1&rsquo;s design was nuts, even for the time.
The original prototype <a href="https://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~LE9S-ICKW/e/e_histry_2.html">even had pop-up headlights</a>, which were only removed for structural reasons.
All the more surprising that the designer, Toshihiko Hirai, was designing the (comparatively reserved) MX-5 around the same time.
Imagine a world with a crazy gull-wing doored, mid-engine Miata!</p>
<p>This design wasn&rsquo;t just for weirdness' sake: it was the AZ-1&rsquo;s biggest selling point.
In the <em>baburu keki</em> period, kei-class sports cars were set to become <a href="https://www.hagerty.com/media/market-trends/with-quirky-kei-cars-its-easy-as-a-b-c/">a major battlefield</a> for automakers.
Average people finally had enough money to own a car, and automakers wanted in on that budget-conscious-ballin' money.
But when your competitors are also limited to 66 horsepower, your vehicle needs a way to distinguish itself.
The Honda Beat was the first kei sportscar to market, and it was a mid-engine drop-top making almost 100 hp / liter. <em>naturally aspirated, in 1991!</em>
Five months later, Suzuki unveiled the Cappuccino, which one-upped the Beat with <strong>double</strong> the number of roof configurations.
The Cappuccino could switch between a T-top, targa, hardtop, or convertible at the owners' whim!
Between these two pint-sized sportscars, the AZ-1 had some stiff competition in the quirkiness department.</p>
<p>Sadly the AZ-1&rsquo;s weridness wasn&rsquo;t enough to sell.
The bubble economy popped in late 1991, when Tokyo real estate prices collapsed from their record highs.
By 1992, the average person could barely afford <em>any</em> car, much less an impractical one.
The same quirks that made the AZ-1 so desirable as a fun car made it nigh-unsellable as a daily driver.
Critics derided the gull doors for eating into an already cramped interior.
It&rsquo;s mid-engine layout meant no trunk, and the tiny frunk could barely fit a donut spare.
Mazda didn&rsquo;t even come close to it&rsquo;s sales target of 800 units per month, and by 1994, the AZ-1 was dead.
And yet, it&rsquo;s legacy lives on in Gashapon machines and the hearts of short-statured enthusiasts everywhere!</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="az1frontquarter.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="az1front.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>front quarter view</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>front view</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="subaru-360-1958-1971">Subaru 360 (1958-1971)</h2>
<figure class="left"><img src="subarumach.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>Often compared to the VW beetle, the Subaru 360 was the first true &ldquo;people&rsquo;s car&rdquo; of Japan.
After World War 2, Japan wanted to incentivize people and small businesses to get on the road.
In 1949 it created the Kei segment - a special class of subcompact car with small engines and smaller dimensions, all encouraged by lenient tax breaks.
While many automakers tried, the first successful vehicle in the kei segment was <a href="https://www.autoevolution.com/news/history-of-the-japanese-kei-car-49720.html">none other than the Subaru 360</a>.
On paper, the 360 was nothing special.
It&rsquo;s two-stroke, rear mounted engine only put out a 25 hp, and weighed only <a href="https://www.hemmings.com/stories/article/a-small-start-for-something-big-1969-subaru-360">925 lbs</a>.
But a combination of radical efficiency (66 mpg advertised!) and distinctive styling made the 360 a success in its home market.
But stateside, the 360 had an entirely different reception.</p>
<p>You may know Malcom Bricklin from his <a href="https://www.petersen.org/blog/bricklin">Yugo-importing</a> and safety-centric-sport-coupe designing fame.
But in the late 60&rsquo;s, he also founded Subaru of America to compete with the VW-dominated budget segment.
Cheaper and more efficient than the VW Beetle, the 360 seemed destined for success in the US.
But a jaded review from Consumer Reports unfairly derided the 360 for slow acceleration and lackluster safety.
One quote <a href="https://www.mysubaru360.com/manuals_and_documents/Subaru_360_Consumer_Reports_April_69.pdf">reads</a>: <em>&ldquo;The Subaru ate up almost half a minute in accelerating for 30 mph to 50 mph. That&rsquo;s a lot of time to spend on the wrong side of a two-lane road, should one ever try to pass another car.&quot;</em>
As if any sane 360 driver would try passing in an oncoming lane!
Unfortunately, this short-sighted review irreparably damaged public perception of the Subaru.
360s languished on dealer lots, until years of slow sales eventually killed Bricklin&rsquo;s licensing deal in 1971.
Maligned in the States, the Subaru 360 is nonetheless celebrated across the Pacific.
Today, &ldquo;the ladybug&rdquo; is still seen as a symbol of Japan&rsquo;s technical and societal reconstruction after the destruction of WWII.
$3.50 was a steal for this replica of Japanese car culture&rsquo;s roots!</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="subaruparts.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="subarufront.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="subaruback.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>parts assembly</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>front quarter view</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>rear view</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="nissan-s-cargo-1989-1991">Nissan S-Cargo (1989-1991)</h2>
<figure class="left"><img src="scargomach.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>If you thought retro-styling was a uniquely 21st century trend, think again.
At the height of the bubble era, Nissan unveiled not one, not two, but <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160703050240/http://www.nissan-global.com/EN/HERITAGE/s_cargo_230.html"><em>FOUR</em> retro-styled cars.</a>
Of these, two were regular compacts, one was a roadster, and one, the S-Cargo, was a <strong>delivery van</strong>!
When it went out of production in 1991, retro-styled work van enthusiasts had to wait seventeen years for HHR Panel to pick up the torch!
Predicting the retro-styling trend by multiple years, the S-Cargo&rsquo;s success proved that style sometimes trumps substance.</p>
<p>While their appearance sometimes inspires laughter, Nissan&rsquo;s Pike cars always seemed in on the joke to me.
Even the name &ldquo;Pike Car&rdquo; is a pun, as the venture was meant to &ldquo;<a href="https://www.nissan.ph/experience-nissan/design/nissan-pike-cars.html">spearhead new, cutting edge design</a>&rdquo;.
But instead of looking to the future for inspiration, Nissan turned to the past.
Their search brought them to Naoki Sakai, a Japanese designer with a background in fashion.
Sakai described his design mentality as follows, &ldquo;car designers are highly elite and only look at the future and evolution of cars&hellip; [but] Fashion design goes back and forth freely&rdquo;.
Nissan applied this philosophy to car design, resulting in the first pike car &ndash; the Be-1.</p>
<p>The Be-1&rsquo;s popularity could not be overstated.
At the car&rsquo;s public unveiling, Sakai recalled hearing the same two words over and over: <a href="https://www.figaroownersclub.com/naoki-sakai-figaro-designer/"><em>kawaii</em> (cute) and <em>hoshii</em> (I want it).</a>
Nissan stirred the pot further by announcing that the Be-1 would only be sold for one year.
This hype translated directly into sales success - Nissan had to implement a lottery system since demand outstripped supply by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20181224092117/http://autozine.org/Archive/Nissan/classic/Be1.html">10 to 1</a>.
This unexpected success led to more Pike cars - the safari-styled Pao, the retro roadster Figaro, and of course, the mollusk motorcar S-Cargo.</p>
<p>Unlike the Be-1, I can guarantee that there was no prior demand for a snail-themed delivery van.
No one was beating down the doors of Nissan&rsquo;s corporate HQ, bemoaning the absence of invertibrate-themed work vehicles.
But Nissan built the S-cargo anyway, and they didn&rsquo;t mail it in.
The S-Cargo was available with a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160322051842/http://www.nissan-global.com/EN/HERITAGE/s_cargo_120.html">canvas folding roof</a>, presumably for those extra-tall deliveries.
It also featured a removable sushi tray and snail-themed mud flaps.
Powertrain-wise, it was essentially a Nissan Pulsar, which meant a wheezy <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20181224092117/http://autozine.org/Archive/Nissan/classic/Be1.html">1.5L inline-4 and a 3-speed automatic.</a>
I also can&rsquo;t imagine that the downward-sloping roofline helped cargo capacity, but Nissan claims<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160703050240/http://www.nissan-global.com/EN/HERITAGE/s_cargo_230.html"> &ldquo;the high roof of the cargo area was especially popular&rdquo;.</a>
Maybe I don&rsquo;t get the hype - if you want an iconic Japanese delivery vehicle, there&rsquo;s a much more obvious choice&hellip;</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="scargoparts.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="scargofront.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="scargoback.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>parts assembly</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>front quarter view</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>side view</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="honorable-mention-ae86-corolla">Honorable Mention: AE86 Corolla</h2>
<figure class="right"><img src="ae86mach.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p>If there&rsquo;s a single vehicle that <em>had</em> to be on this list, it&rsquo;s this one.
The AE86 Toyota Sprinter Trueno is an uncontested motorsports icon.
You may know it as Le Mans victor Keiichi Tsuchiya&rsquo;s vehicle of choice.
Or maybe <a href="http://www.tunedph.com/thanks-initial-d-elements-car-culture-influenced-cartoon">Initial D</a> was your gateway drug to the world of auto enthusiasm.
From these sources, the 86 has gained a reputation for being the ultimate drift machine.</p>
<p>But even in it&rsquo;s time, AE86 Trueno Sprinter was&rsquo;t the most powerful or best handling car.
Before the drifting scene took off, it was seen as &ldquo;<a href="https://www.motorbiscuit.com/tofu-eurobeat-and-drifting-how-the-toyota-ae86-corolla-inspired-the-86/">just another used cheap, reliable &hellip; car</a>&rdquo;.
But these pedestrian origins actually <em>contributed</em> to the 86&rsquo;s popularity.
Intended for fuel savings, the lightweight body and near 50/50 weight distribution also gave the 86 superb handling characteristics.
While it&rsquo;s 1.6 liter 4-cylinder was underpowered, especially compared to other drift machines, this forced AE86 drivers to learn good driving technique.
Because of these characteristics, &ldquo;Drift King&rdquo; Keiichi Tsuchiya famously stated, &ldquo;[t]he 86 helps you become a better driver.&rdquo;
The 86 may not have been the most performant drift car, but it was the right car at the right time.</p>
<h2 id="suzuki-jimny-2018-present">Suzuki Jimny (2018-Present)</h2>
<figure class="left"><img src="jimnymach.jpg"
         alt="image"/>
</figure>

<p><strong>&ldquo;LIFE IS JIMNY&rdquo;</strong> Boldly proclaims this Gachapon machine. Who am I to argue?
I had assumed that displacement and wheelbase taxes would make off-roaders a rare sight in Japan.
But I&rsquo;ve been pleasantly surprised by the number of Land Cruisers, Wranglers, and overlanding Tacomas I&rsquo;ve seen here!
And of course, Jimnys. Lots of Jimnys.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s back up for a second, though. What is a Jimny? Where did the name come from?
The most popular hypothesis claims that Jimny is a <a href="https://www.masterclass.com/articles/spoonerism-explained">spoonerism</a> of &ldquo;Jeep&rdquo; and &ldquo;mini&rdquo;.
While Suzuki themselves apparently <a href="https://www.news24.com/life/motoring/bakkies-suvs/bakkie_and_suv/at-last-the-truth-behind-the-suzuki-jimny-name-tag-20201210-2">support this view</a>, many believe other theories.
Some claim that Jimny is a reference to Jiminy Cricket, Pinocchio&rsquo;s upbeat, insectoid conscience.
Still others argue that Jimny stems from translating &ldquo;Gemini&rdquo; to Japanese phonetics.
Just like the Willys Jeep, the Jimny name debate has been raging for decades, and shows no sign of stopping now.</p>
<p>Name controversy aside, the story of what would become the Jimny begins in the late 1960&rsquo;s.
Cars like the Subaru 360 made driving accessible for more people, but only in places with good infrastructure.
Suzuki saw a gap in the market for a kei-class car focused solely on off-road capability.
Such a vehicle would have the utility of a much larger truck, but be cheaper to own and run.
The first Jimny was built in 1970 to take a chance on this promising market.
As it turned out, demand for capable, budget vehicles was massive!
Since it&rsquo;s release the 70&rsquo;s, Jimnys flew off of (metaphorical) shelves, kickstarting the popular of 4WD kei car segment in Japan.</p>
<p>The spirit of the budget off-roader continues in the modern, fourth generation Jimny.
The 2018 model has a relatively simple mechanical part-time 4WD system, a feature of the Jimny since the first generation.
Clever parts sharing also keeps the costs down.
The JDM Jimny is offered in both the kei class and the larger &ldquo;compact&rdquo; class.
But if you look closely at <a href="https://www.suzuki.co.jp/release/a/2022/0620/">Suzuki&rsquo;s press photos</a>, it&rsquo;s obvious that the compact is just the kei model with a larger engine and bigger fender flares.
This modularity makes the Jimny a common choice for overlanding builds, which seem just as popular in Japan as in the states.
The Gacha model actually came with multiple bumpers, so you can choose whether you want a bone-stock Jimny or a rock-crawling powerhouse!</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="jimnyparts.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="jimnyfront.jpg" alt=""></th>
<th style="text-align:center"><img src="jimnyback.jpg" alt=""></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>parts assembly</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>front quarter view</em></td>
<td style="text-align:center"><em>rear 3/4 view</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>That&rsquo;s it for the roundup! There were a few more vehicles I wanted to get to - but if I don&rsquo;t end this somewhere I never will.
Thanks for bearing with the diversion from my usual format, and let me know if you&rsquo;re interested in more articles like this!</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🏆 Battery Recycling: The Dark Side of an All-EV Future (2nd place, Problems Worth Solving Competition 2023)</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 17:30:30 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</guid>
			<description>You&amp;rsquo;ve got to start with the customer experience and work back toward the technology, not the other way around. ~ Steve Jobs
 Last weekend I had the opportunity to participate in Problems Worth Solving: Texas A&amp;amp;M&amp;rsquo;s first and only entrepreneurship competition that outright bans solutions.
Great businesses arise from an intimate understanding of your customers&#39; needs. PWS emphasizes this critical step of entrepreneurship by focusing entrepreneurs on the problem, not the solution.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>You&rsquo;ve got to start with the customer experience and work back toward the technology, not the other way around. ~ Steve Jobs</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Last weekend I had the opportunity to participate in <a href="https://engineering.tamu.edu/student-life/eep/problems-worth-solving-competition.html">Problems Worth Solving</a>:
Texas A&amp;M&rsquo;s first and only entrepreneurship competition that outright <em>bans</em> solutions.</p>
<p>Great businesses arise from an intimate understanding of your customers' needs.
PWS emphasizes this critical step of entrepreneurship by focusing entrepreneurs on the problem, <strong>not</strong> the solution.
The competition was 5 minutes of presenting in-depth on an important problem that many face, and 5 minutes of Q&amp;A with industry judges.</p>
<p>I chose to present on EV battery recycling. Current legislation aims to get more people into Electric Vehicles for the good of the climate and the environment.
But our current solutions to recycle EV batteries are inefficient, expensive, and environmentally detrimental.
I emphasized the need solutions for battery supply chains, recycling processes, and repairability that are cost-effective and scalable.</p>
<p>The whole experience was great! I ended up getting second place with this presentation.
If you want to watch the presentation, check it out below!</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/i1K0a1xEk7c" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="My PWS Presentation!"></iframe>
</div>

]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>A sane mini-tutorial for the Jenkins Javascript API</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jenkinsapi/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 14:51:34 -0600</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jenkinsapi/</guid>
			<description>Holy moly, the Jenkins documentation is bad. At the very least, it isn&amp;rsquo;t very user-friendly, especially for beginners. For someone who has little-to-no experience in web development, doing something as simple as getting some job data from a Node program is the equivalent of pulling teeth. After spending hours in rabbit holes, I finally stumbled on a configuration that works. This mini-writeup will hopefully help those webdev-challenged folks such as myself in the quest for Jenkins API usage.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Holy moly, the Jenkins documentation is bad. At the very least, it isn&rsquo;t very user-friendly, especially for beginners.
For someone who has little-to-no experience in web development, doing something as simple as getting some job data from a Node program is the equivalent of pulling teeth. After spending hours in rabbit holes, I finally stumbled on a configuration that works. This mini-writeup will hopefully help those webdev-challenged folks such as myself in the quest for Jenkins API usage.</p>
<p>My goal for this project was pulling real-time job data from Jenkins, so I won&rsquo;t dive into more advanced stuff like creating jobs and triggering builds. But the Jenkins API does support those actions, so keep that in mind.</p>
<h2 id="api-points-of-interest">API Points of Interest</h2>
<p>The Jenkins API is REST-like: information about what data you want to fetch is encoded directly into the url the fetch request is sent to. Since Jenkins doesn&rsquo;t have a list of which URLs actually contain useful data, I&rsquo;ve <del>copied</del> <strong>compiled and expanded upon</strong> <a href="https://gist.github.com/justlaputa/5634984">justlaputa&rsquo;s Github gist</a> of useful api URLs.</p>
<p><em>Note</em> that <code>jenkins_url</code> is the link to your Jenkins controller instance: it may need to include a port number as well.</p>
<ul>
<li>List all jobs on Jenkins: <code>jenkins_url</code>+<code>/api/json?tree=jobs[name,color]</code></li>
<li>List all builds for a job named <code>${job_name}</code>: <code>jenkins_url</code>+<code>/job/${job_name}/lastBuild/api/json?tree=builds[number,status,timestamp,id,result]</code></li>
<li>List last build info for a job named <code>${job_name}</code>: <code>jenkins_url</code>+<code>/job/${job_name}/lastBuild/api/json</code></li>
<li>List build progress for a job named <code>${job_name}</code>: <code>jenkins_url</code>+<code>/job/${job_name}/lastBuild/api/json?tree=result,timestamp,estimatedDuration</code></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="authentication">Authentication</h2>
<p>The Jenkins API states that it uses BASIC authentication to allow API access. There are exactly 0 examples about using BASIC authentication in the API, so I&rsquo;ve taken it upon myself to provide some sample code.</p>
<h3 id="the-api-token">The API Token</h3>
<p>To access Jenkins from an API, you&rsquo;ll have to generate an API token. To do so, click the <em>Configure</em> button under the username in the top right corner.
<figure class="big"><img src="TokenGen1.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Configure option under username</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

Then click <em>Add new Token</em> under the <em>API Token</em> heading.
<figure class="big"><img src="TokenGen2.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Add token Button</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>This will generate a new token, which looks like a string of random text. Copy it somewhere safe, because you won&rsquo;t be able to see it again!</p>
<h3 id="the-code">The Code</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m not a Javascript programmer, so I can&rsquo;t go in-depth and explain how this authentication works. But I <em>can</em> tell you that this code does work.</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>let JENKINS_URL = &quot;localhost:8080&quot; // replace with url of your Jenkins server
let JENKINS_UNAME = &quot;Jenkins-User&quot; // replace with username you generated token for
let JENKINS_JOB = &quot;BuildWebsite&quot;   // replace with name of job you want to pull data from
let API_TOKEN   = &quot;gobbedygook000000letters00000and0000numbers&quot; // replace with API token you generated above

function JobData(jobName){
    // fill this string with the information found in API Points of Interest
    // here, I pull information on the most recently run job.
	const url = `http://${JENKINS_URL}/job/${jobName}/lastBuild/api/json?pretty=true`

	return fetch ( url, {
        // authorization for fetch request
		method: &quot;GET&quot;,
		headers:{
			Authorization :
			&quot;Basic &quot; + 
			Buffer.from(`${JENKINS_UNAME}:${API_TOKEN}`).toString(&quot;base64&quot;)
		},

	}).then((res, req) =&gt; {
		return res.json()
        //this function returns the job information.
	})
}

</code></pre><h2 id="cross-site-request-forgery">Cross Site Request Forgery</h2>
<p>It is important to note that while Javascript can be run from both the frontend or the backend, API calls must be made from a backend to prevent <em>Cross-Site Request Forgeries.</em> So, there&rsquo;s really no way to make API calls from <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags embedded in an HTML file. You&rsquo;ll need to make a backend that serves the Jenkins data to the frontend, and host it on the internet (with something like <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>) or locally (with <a href="https://www.phusionpassenger.com/library/walkthroughs/deploy/nodejs/">Passenger</a> or something similar).</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s pretty much it. This is a super short article, but something like this would have saved me about 10 hours of googling. Hopefully this will help some of you aspiring Jenkins-wranglers learn something new!</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Boss Pedal Switching Issues? Try This! (Boss GE-7 Modding)</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</link>
			<pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 15:06:31 -0600</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/ge7/</guid>
			<description>Post-Mod GE-7
  The Mod If you just want to skip to the fix, head to this section.
At the advice of Brian Wampler, I caved and bought a minty used Boss GE-7. Imagine my surprise after moving any of the EQ sliders introduced very noticeable noise! How could you, Boss? Apparently, when the GE-7 was first designed, battery life and price point were more important considerations than audio fidelity.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="ge7pic.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Post-Mod GE-7</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="the-mod">The Mod</h1>
<p>If you just want to skip to the fix, head to <a href="#the-fix">this section</a>.</p>
<p>At the advice of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hypn6uA6RPs">Brian Wampler</a>, I caved and bought a minty used Boss GE-7.
Imagine my surprise after moving any of the EQ sliders introduced very noticeable noise! How could you, Boss? Apparently, when the GE-7 was first designed, battery life and price point were more important considerations than audio fidelity.
As a result, any GE-7s made from 1981 to 2017 use the <code>TL022</code> dual op-amp chips. These outdated chips are surpassed in every aspect of audio performance by the more recent <code>NE5532</code> dual op-amps, despite drawing more current.
<em>(<a href="https://www.ti.com/lit/ds/symlink/ne5532.pdf">38 mA</a> vs <a href="https://www.ti.com/lit/ds/symlink/tl022.pdf?ts=1672127917081">6 mA</a> in output short-circuit condition. <a href="https://www.physics.unlv.edu/~bill/PHYS483/op_amp_datasheet.pdf">This is a good read</a> if you need a refresher on op-amp datasheet deciphering)</em>.</p>
<p>Boss also used cheapo-ceramic capacitors in the signal path of the GE-7. Ceramics can be microphonic due to the piezoelectric effect: this is possibly the worst type of non-ideality an audio component can have. Subsitituting these for film capacitors would drastically improve audio fidelity. Since my pedal was an older model, I decided to replace all of the electrolytic capacitors as well. These caps have most likely dried out after 40+ years of use.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>Not in the mood to source parts for myself in the middle of a rabid chip market (Even through-hole parts are getting hard to find!), I opted for the <a href="https://fromelelectronics.com/products/ge7-mods">Fromel mod kit</a>.</p>
<p>This pedal was made back when manufacturers cared about repairability, and it shows. The GE-7 was very easy to disassemble. After socketing and soldering the new op-amps, I tried to fire the pedal up. There was no sound.</p>
<h1 id="the-problem">The Problem</h1>
<p>The broken pedal behaved as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>If the switch was held down, the clean (bypass) signal could be heard clearly</li>
<li>If the switch wasn&rsquo;t held down, an extremely loud buzzing could be heard</li>
<li>The wet (equalized) signal could not be heard, regardless of switch position</li>
<li>The LED never turned on</li>
</ul>
<figure class="left"><img src="inside1.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>GE-7 Gutshot</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The buzzing noise sounded a bit like a ground loop, which is often caused by grounding issues. Using a continuity checker, I discovered that the switch ground wasn&rsquo;t connected to the power jack&rsquo;s ground. But the pedal worked before I took it apart: what could have changed??</p>
<h1 id="the-fix">The Fix</h1>
<p>Taking a closer look at the switch grounding revealed all! See how the switch&rsquo;s ground (black wire) is attached to the output jack, and nothing else? The switch will only be grounded if output jack is attached to the enclosure. The enclosure itself needs to be grounded as well: The ground output from the 9v input connection to the input jack handles this. All this means that the pedal will only switch properly if the input and output jacks are electrically connected to (or screwed into) the enclosure! After alligator-clipping the switch ground and power jack ground together, and plugging my guitar in, it worked like a charm!</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve been having this issue, check 2 things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Use a continuity checker (most multimeters should have one) to see if all of the grounds are connected</li>
<li>Make sure a 1/4&quot; cable is plugged into the pedal&rsquo;s <em>input</em> jack. If nothing is plugged in, the pedal won&rsquo;t activate.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-takeaway">The Takeaway</h1>
<p>While I&rsquo;ve been told to <a href="https://www.coda-effects.com/2017/07/ground-loops-and-guitar-pedals.html">always ground the enclosure</a>, this is the first time I&rsquo;ve seen an entire pedal&rsquo;s functionality rely on this rule of thumb. Doing so saves exactly two, but those are two wires to potentially break, and two wires to pay for.
But there&rsquo;s a pretty cool reason behind all of this.
In 1981, Boss couldn&rsquo;t rest on the laurels of being a legendary effects manufacturer: it had to build a reputation, which it did by offering invincible pedals at an unbeatable price point.
Even using the enclosure as a ground plane speaks to the dual priorities of build quality and cost that continue to make Boss pedals so ubiquitous, even today.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>💡 SignalBox: DIY Connected Lanterns with MQTT, Adafruit Feather</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 19:04:34 -0600</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/thinking-of-you/</guid>
			<description>Faced with the tradition of family Christmas gift giving, I was thoroughly stumped. I knew I wanted to do something maker-related: I&amp;rsquo;m the only engineer in the family, which tends to amplify the wow factor of any techncal projects :)
After my fallback plan (a Chemex coffee maker) fell through, I knew I had to build these!
 the finished product!
  These are long-distance friendship lanterns. The idea is, sometimes you want to let a distant friend or family member know that you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of them, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily want to shoot them a text.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Faced with the tradition of family Christmas gift giving, I was thoroughly stumped.
I knew I wanted to do something maker-related: I&rsquo;m the only engineer in the family, which tends to amplify the wow factor of any techncal projects :)</p>
<p>After my fallback plan (a Chemex coffee maker) fell through, I knew I had to build these!</p>
<figure><img src="boximg.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>the finished product!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>These are <a href="https://www.instructables.com/DIY-Long-Distance-Best-Friend-Lights/">long-distance friendship lanterns</a>. The idea is, sometimes you want to let a distant friend or family member know that you&rsquo;re thinking of them, even if you don&rsquo;t necessarily want to shoot them a text. The lanterns couldn&rsquo;t be simpler to use: turning on your lantern also turns on your friends' lantern, no matter where they are in the world.</p>
<h2 id="logic">Logic</h2>
<p>This project has multiple boxes (one for each family member), all of which can send &ldquo;thinking of you&rdquo; messages to each other. For example, if I&rsquo;m currently thinking about my dad, I can make his box light up from my box! But how does he know it&rsquo;s me that&rsquo;s thinking of him, and not someone else? To solve this, each box is assigned a color, which is associated with the box owner. So when I send a message to my dad, his box will become my color. To send a message, I can press the push button, which cycles through all the possible colors to send to. Not pressing the button for 2 seconds will send the message, lighting up the senders' and receivers' box for 2 hours. Confusing? I made a diagram.</p>
<figure><img src="box.drawio.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Feather Board (image credit to Adafruit)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-code">The Code</h2>
<h3 id="mqtt">MQTT</h3>
<p>I knew that <a href="https://mqtt.org/">MQTT</a> would be a great fit for this project: it even bills itself as &ldquo;The standard for IoT messaging&rdquo;. It&rsquo;s lightweight, bidirectional, and requires minimal infrastructure.  Without getting too into the weeds, every message, or <strong>post</strong>, is published to a <strong>topic</strong>. Once a message is published to a topic, all other devices subscribed to the same topic receive the new message. By making a topic for each box, (i.e. the <em>green</em> box will receive any posts sent to the <em>green</em> topic), anyone&rsquo;s post to that box&rsquo;s topic will be interpreted as a message to turn that box on.</p>
<p>Of course, this system still requires a central server, called a broker, to make sure messages get to where they&rsquo;re sent. Luckily, <a href="https://console.hivemq.cloud/">HiveMQ</a> is one such server with a generous free tier that this project&rsquo;s constraints fall well within. It also <em>HAD</em> a <a href="https://console.hivemq.cloud/clients/arduino-esp8266?uuid=c689cd9ab0cf406bbc142988277304d9">super neat tutorial</a> for getting started on an Arduino, but the page seems to be broken. Either way, my implementation is based on their sample publish-receive code.</p>
<h3 id="arduino">Arduino</h3>
<p>Everyone and their mother knows that Arduino is the way to go for simple MCU programming. Abundant libraries handle all of the hard stuff, all you have to do is bring the logic. Besides some Linux issues (Manjaro didn&rsquo;t seem to like my UDEV rules, solution <a href="https://playground.arduino.cc/Linux/All/#Permission">here</a>), everything was simple to set up.</p>
<p>As for libraries, I utilized <a href="https://github.com/FastLED/FastLED/wiki/Basic-usage">FastLED</a> to program simple light animations in the Neopixel strip. ESP8266WiFi is obviously needed to connect the device to the network, and other boilerplate libraries such as <a href="">PubSubClient</a> and <a href="https://www.arduino.cc/reference/en/libraries/littlefs_esp32/">LittleFS</a> were used to authenticate with the HiveMQ server.</p>
<h2 id="parts-selection">Parts Selection</h2>
<figure><img src="feather.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Feather Board (image credit to Adafruit)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I am blessed to live within driving distance of Micro Center, a legendary PC superstore with a sizeable DIY/maker section.
I knew I needed an Arduino board with wifi support, and Micro Center had the <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/2821">Adafruit Feather Huzzah</a> in stock.
This board&rsquo;s specs are overkill for this application, but it definitely does the job.
Also from the Micro Center haul was a strip of NeoPixels, and some push-button switches for control.
Add in a clear case from the container store, and we&rsquo;re ready to rock!</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/2821">Adafruit Feather Huzzah ESP8266</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.microcenter.com/product/459723/adafruit-industries-neopixel-digital-rgb-led-strip-white-60-led">Adafruit NeoPixel RGB LED Strip</a></li>
<li>Any momentary push-button switches</li>
<li><a href="https://www.containerstore.com/s/gift-packaging/gift-boxes/clear-amac-boxes/12d?productId=10003497">Clear AMAC enclosure</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="does-it-work">Does it work?</h2>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nyXzglq0ATc" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="Quick Demo of Signalbox"></iframe>
</div>

<p>In short, yeah! The only issues I&rsquo;ve run into are logging related. When I rolled these boxes out, I didn&rsquo;t include any method of logging messages. This makes it very difficult to troubleshoot the boxes, since I simply don&rsquo;t know what&rsquo;s happening at any given time. Throw in the fact that I have no method of remotely updating the boxes, even small logic bugs are difficult to fix. But after being rolled out for 3 months, all the reported issues can be fixed just by power cycling the device, so I&rsquo;d call this a win! If you find any issues with my programming, don&rsquo;t hesitate to hit me with a pull request!</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Spelling Test Grader [UPDATE]</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader-update/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 15:36:55 -0600</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader-update/</guid>
			<description>One in six children who are not reading proficiently in third grade fail to graduate from high school on time, four times the rate for children with proficient third-grade reading skills. &amp;ndash; &amp;quot;Double Jeopardy&amp;quot;, Annie E. Casey Foundation Since rolling out my spelling test grader, Catch Up and Read (CAR) has asked for more grading automation! Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick update on the new grader, the Phonics Survey.
What is a Phonics Survey?</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>One in six children who are not reading proficiently in third grade fail to graduate from high school on time, four times the rate for children with proficient third-grade reading skills. &ndash; <!-- raw HTML omitted -->&quot;<a href="https://www.aecf.org/resources/double-jeopardy">Double Jeopardy</a>&quot;, Annie E. Casey Foundation<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Since rolling out my spelling test grader, Catch Up and Read (CAR) has asked for more grading automation!
Here&rsquo;s a quick update on the new grader, the <em>Phonics Survey</em>.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-phonics-survey">What is a Phonics Survey?</h2>
<p>Throughout the span of the CAR program, students need to be benchmarked. The phonics survey determines which consonant-vowel blend types a student struggles with. By asking students to read words aloud, teachers mark down which words they struggle with, and tally up the number of incorrect words per section. They then use this data to plan their lessons around words that students have trouble with.</p>
<figure class="middle"><img src="PhonicsSurveyExample.png"
         alt="phonics survey example section"/><figcaption>
            <p>phonics survey example section</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Phonics surveys were historically administered through paper tests: a teacher would manually tally incorrect words, identify problem sections, and enter student information into a spreadsheet. Phonics surveys aren&rsquo;t particularly labor-intensive, but as CAR began supporting more schools, it became obvious that this solution wouldn&rsquo;t scale. Hence, automation!</p>
<h2 id="getting-online">Getting Online</h2>
<p>The biggest annoyance with the first iteration of the auto-grader was that it was a locally-saved HTML file. This worked fine from an implementation standpoint, but many users complained. To non-tech people, the concept of a local file also being an interactable webpage is a bit obtuse, so I decided to bite the bullet and roll it out to the World Wide Web. <a href="https://www.netlify.com/">Netlify</a> made this easier than it had any right being: if any changes have been pushed to the main branch of the project&rsquo;s Github, Netlify rolls these changes out to the production website. Their free tier offers <strong>more</strong> than enough bandwidth (100 GB!) for this project&rsquo;s use case.</p>
<h2 id="phonics-survey-implementation">Phonics Survey Implementation</h2>
<p>I wish I could make this glorified matching form sound sexy, but I can&rsquo;t. There&rsquo;s no algorithm, like the previous test. It just tallies the number of words that the user clicks, does a little formatting magic, and prints the page as a PDF. Regardless, there are still some interesting details I&rsquo;d like to point out.</p>
<figure class="middle"><img src="WebsiteUsage.png"
         alt="website example"/><figcaption>
            <p>website example</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>A PDF can&rsquo;t be saved unless the student&rsquo;s name, grade, and school are entered. This plaintext goes in the filename for easy recollection of data.</li>
<li>By pulling the current date, the program can automatically mark each test as <code>[Beginning, Middle, or End of Year]</code>. This is also referenced in the filename, easing recordkeeping.</li>
<li>The Save button automatically saves the webpage as a PDF <em>with</em> the colors encoded.</li>
</ul>
<figure class="middle"><img src="PDFexample.png"
         alt="generated PDF example"/><figcaption>
            <p>generated PDF example</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="so-what">So What?</h2>
<p>Look, this isn&rsquo;t rocket surgery. In truth, even posting something something this trivial feels a bit juvenile, especially in comparison to how much cool stuff goes down on <a href="https://hackaday.com/2022/11/21/reverse-engineering-the-seven-words-and-more-you-cant-say-on-tv/">Hackaday</a>. But instead of focusing on the technology, I&rsquo;d like to focus on the application and outcome.</p>
<p>Engineers love efficient solutions. But in pursuit of this efficiency, usability can be the first thing to go by the wayside. If a user doesn&rsquo;t use your tool because they can&rsquo;t figure it out, then it&rsquo;s not a good tool. My first version of this program was an objectively better solution: It used less memory, the data integrated with Excel, and it had a login system planned that allowed it to store student information to a MongoDB backend. When I showed it to users, all time-crunched and technically-challenged teachers, it was obvious over-optimization was holding back widespread adoption.</p>
<p>Around this time, I read a lot of posts from user-experience blog <a href="https://www.mobilespoon.net/2022/12/forms-completion-rates-statistics-and-takeaways.html">The Mobile Spoon</a> when working on this project, which led to an epiphany of user-central design. So I rebuilt the form, creating what amounted to an online version of the existing paper tests. I nixed the integrations, opting to instead generate a PDF which would be saved locally. I made the PDF generation idiot-proof: hitting &ldquo;Save&rdquo; names the PDF with the student&rsquo;s information and date, skips all dialog boxes, and automatically downloads to the Downloads folder.</p>
<h2 id="outcomes">Outcomes</h2>
<p>This updated program immediately began pulling it&rsquo;s weight: tests that used to take 30 minutes to grade were cut down to 5. Since CAR just hit 1000 students this year, this program (conservatively!) saved over 400 man-hours of manual test grading. Nearly every literacy coach organically mentioned this tool as a massive improvement in their end-of-year reflections. With the new consistency of data gathered, teachers were able to better identify student gaps, plan data-driven lessons, and push students to read on grade level.</p>
<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>
<ol>
<li>Keep It Simple, Stupid! (KISS) This mantra has continued to ring true throughout every project I&rsquo;ve undertaken. Complexity has it&rsquo;s place, but it&rsquo;s better to have something bulletproof and simple than something flashy but unreliable.</li>
<li>Think of the user: Users won&rsquo;t necessarily appreciate that your program has O(n) space complexity. But they do appreciate being able to use your tools without an instruction manual or a degree in compsci.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>MGMT&#39;s Anti-Breakout Album: Congratulations</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 10:20:53 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/congratulations/</guid>
			<description>We are absolutely dead serious about music-making, and that’s what we want people to understand, that there’s no joke in it. We’re not intentionally trying to f*ck with people, we’re actually making this music that we love and we want people to hear it.1 ~ Ben Goldwasser
 You may not be familiar with MGMT, but anyone who had a pulse in the late 2000&amp;rsquo;s has most likely heard their work.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>We are absolutely dead serious about music-making, and that’s what we want people to understand, that there’s no joke in it. We’re not intentionally trying to f*ck with people, we’re actually making this music that we love and we want people to hear it.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> ~ Ben Goldwasser</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You may not be familiar with MGMT, but anyone who had a pulse in the late 2000&rsquo;s has most likely heard their work.
Don&rsquo;t believe me? Give this a listen and tell me it doesn&rsquo;t ring a bell.</p>

<iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1jJci4qxiYcOHhQR247rEU"
    width="100%"
    height="250"
    frameborder="0"
    allowtransparency="true"
    allow="encrypted-media"></iframe>


<p>Widely considered a two-hit-wonder by the radio-listening public (the other being <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B9dSYgd5Elk">Time to Pretend</a>),
MGMT seemed destined to a fate of former-pop-star obscurity.
So two years after their smash-hit album Oracular Spectacular,
MGMT released their sprawling, hook-less sophomore effort Congratulations to unanimous critical &hellip; confusion.
But, Contratulations wasn&rsquo;t an intentional career suicide attempt (as many critics quickly branded it); it was the album that MGMT <em>needed</em> to make.</p>
<p>MGMT was on top of the world in 2008, and they didn&rsquo;t know what to do about it.
Their debut album had just gone gold in the US and double platinum in the UK. They headlined at music festivals and toured with Radiohead and Paul McCartney.
Not too bad for a project that Ben Goldwasser and Andrew VanWyngarden never intended to be any more than a joke.
At Wesleyan University, MGMT was known as the band that performed the Ghostbusters theme for 45 minutes straight in snowman costumes.
Even their name, MGMT, was a sardonic reference to their goal to &ldquo;sell out as quickly as possible&rdquo; to the &ldquo;Management&rdquo; of the corporate music conglomerate.
VanWyngarden puts it best:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When we wrote <em>Time to Pretend</em>, we were totally taking the piss out of the rock star thing. And all of a sudden that song was, like, a single, and we had to play it every day for … two … years.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As an artist, what do you do when your entire career is built on totally disingenuous work?</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re MGMT, you release Congratulations.</p>
<figure class="small"><img src="AlbumCover.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Anthony Ausgang&rsquo;s excellent lowbrow album art</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The ascending, reverb-soaked guitar prepending <em>It&rsquo;s Working</em> signals that MGMT has changed dramatically since 2008.
Lyrics dreaming of hyper-stardom are traded for a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yu9ykgGUm1w">Yes</a>-adjacent nonsense.
Gone are the rudimentary-yet-addictive synth hooks and bombastic Fridmann drums.
In their place are surf guitars, 60&rsquo;s organs, and harpsichords (???).
Producer Sonic Boom (of Spacemen 3 fame) earns his pay: this is a well, albeit strangely, produced album.
Production quirks like the beater-less kick drum in <em>Song for Dan Treacy</em> and massive, &lsquo;verbed out snare in <em>Siberian Breaks</em> utilize familiar instruments in offbeat ways, seemingly for strangeness&rsquo; sake alone.
The album is lush at times, and at others jarring and oblique.
But this instrumentation is just a jumping-off point for Congratulations' most notable and interesting aspect: it&rsquo;s songwriting.</p>
<p>Congratulations is crazy and yet, it&rsquo;s also strangely addictive.
In many ways, Congratulations is an anti-Tame Impala album.
Instead of meticulously crafting buildups to emotional peaks of payoff, Congratulations opts to chase rabbit trails and go off the beaten path.
Lead-off track <em>It&rsquo;s Working</em> places half-second pauses between its distinct segments, seemingly acknowledging the musical incompatibility of each idea.
It&rsquo;s as if MGMT themselves don&rsquo;t even know how to string them together and ask you, the listener, to fill in the gaps.
Each song contains up to six or seven of these separate ideas, held together only by the common thread of instrumentation.
At times, it&rsquo;s confusing and dense and claustrophobic.
But in doing this, MGMT create their own brand of buildup.
The chaos of the first two verses in standout track <em>Flash Delirium</em> is used to greater multiply the spectacle of the bombastic, Spector-esque outro.
This songwriting method allows MGMT to build towards payoff without making these peaks feel cheap or manufactured.
On this musical journey, MGMT are enthusiastic local guides instead of corporate tour coordinators.</p>
<p>This album can best be described as isolated, consistent flashes of greatness.
Interestingly, this description mirrors MGMT&rsquo;s response to the dilemma of to pop-stardom in the first place.
A joke band that broke up and re-formed after being headhunted by Columbia Records, their fame only lasted as long as their songs remained on the top 40.
But instead of clinging desperately to relevance, MGMT took a bold step away from financial and career security in favor of their own artistic integrity.
This album stands as a musical reminder that but it takes real boldness to step away from fame and success, but the rewards of artistic freedom are much sweeter than the bitterness of being chained to other peoples' expectations.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>From <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/mgmt-on-aliens-drugs-and-congratulations-205423/">Rolling Stone&rsquo;s 2010 Interview</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>From <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/music/2010/apr/08/mgmt-congratulations-oracular-spectacular">The Guardian&rsquo;s 2010 Interview</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>🏆 MyMirror: a Google-integrated Smart Mirror</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 13:28:52 -0600</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</guid>
			<description>Note: More information about myMirror can be found on the project&amp;rsquo;s devpost. Check there for other peoples&#39; contributions!
Why myMirror? When I wake up in the morning, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot I know I probably should do. For example, I should probably prepare for the day ahead by checking the weather and my daily calendar. But often times, I just don&amp;rsquo;t. For situations like this, myMirror is here to help.
myMirror solves the above dilemma by integrating this crucial information into your everyday bathroom mirror.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Note: More information about myMirror can be found on <a href="https://devpost.com/software/mymirror">the project&rsquo;s devpost</a>.</em>
<em>Check there for other peoples' contributions!</em></p>
<h2 id="why-mymirror">Why myMirror?</h2>
<p>When I wake up in the morning, there&rsquo;s a lot I know I probably should do.
For example, I should probably prepare for the day ahead by checking the weather and my daily calendar.
But often times, <strong>I just don&rsquo;t</strong>. For situations like this, myMirror is here to help.</p>
<p>myMirror solves the above dilemma by integrating this crucial information into your everyday bathroom mirror.
myMirror is a <em>smart mirror</em> with an embedded display screen,
displaying the current time and date, weather for your area, and personal Google Calendar reminders.
It even features a motion sensor, turning off the display to save power when a user isn&rsquo;t detected.</p>
<h2 id="how-does-it-work">How does it work?</h2>
<figure class="middle"><img src="Software.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>The software side of myMirror</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On the software side, myMirror is essentially a specialized website. It&rsquo;s written in pure Javascript, HTML, and CSS.
It utilizes the Open Weather Maps and Google Calendar APIs to display this information to the user.
The mirror itself is a pane of one-way glass with a 3.5&quot; display is mounted behind it.
A modified Raspberry Pi drives the display and handles the power management alongside the motion sensor.</p>
<h3 id="what-did-you-do">What did you do?</h3>
<p>myMirror was my idea, so I ended up leading the charge to get this project finished in 24 hours.
As the team lead, I had to check in with others, keep morale up, and delegate tasks where I wasn&rsquo;t the best person for the job.
But I did quite a bit of programming myself! I handled the hardware side of myMirror.
This included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Modifying the pi to drive a display with non-standard resolution and aspect ratios</li>
<li>Programming a daemon that interfaces with xScreenSaver to unblank the screen when motion is detected</li>
<li>Automating the execution of the program in case of power loss or a hard reboot</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="whats-next-for-mymirror">What&rsquo;s next for myMirror?</h2>
<p>There are a few upgrades we&rsquo;re considering implementing.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>First off, we want a serious codebase refresh. Anything written in 24 hours could stand to be written again in a cleaner, more concise way.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next, a bigger display. 3.5&quot;x2&quot; is just too small for any sizeable mirror.
The next step will most likely be the Raspberry Pi Foundation&rsquo;s own official 7&quot; display.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>More Information! With great display space comes great responsibility: to fill that space with relevant data!
Some ideas:</p>
<ul>
<li>Texas A&amp;M Bus Schedule - Either using code swiped from Buswarn or the Texas A&amp;M Transport website.
myMirror could display what time the next bus arrives at your stop, or it the transport map itself!</li>
<li>Spotify - This could be as simple as a progress bar with information about the current song you&rsquo;re listening to.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<figure class="middle"><img src="demo.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>myMirror in action! (feat: me)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="who-contributed">Who contributed?</h2>
<ul>
<li>Me! (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ethancope">Ethan Cope</a>) - Director, hardware, and scripting</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexander-anderson43d/">Alex Anderson</a> - Frontend and weather integration</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/claytonkristiansen/">Clayton Kristiansen</a> - Google Calendar integration</li>
<li><a href="">Alexandria Garcia</a> - API integration and documentation</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Notably: none of these guys are computer science majors! We learned most of this Web Development stuff on the fly!</em></p>
<h2 id="where--when">Where / When?</h2>
<p>TamuHack 2022, Jan 29-30 2022.
TamuHack is a Hackathon, a contest where teams of 4 engineers have 24 hours to design, implement, and present a product to industry judges.</p>
<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>
<p>myMirror won first place in the novice division at TamuHack 2022.
But I walked away from this competition with more than just newfound pride and acute sleep deprivation.
As the team lead, I didn&rsquo;t really have time to hunker down and work on my own thing, which was a new experience for me.
But through this process I learned to sit back and trust people to do their work well.
When a small team of skilled people all play to their strengths, crazy ideas like myMirror can actually come to life!</p>
<p>Thanks for tuning in!</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Spelling Test Auto-Grader for Catch Up and Read</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 18:21:31 -0600</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/auto-grader/</guid>
			<description>&amp;ldquo;Automation is good, so long as you know exactly where to put the machine.&amp;rdquo;
~ Eliyahu Goldratt
 One perk of being a programmer is the ability to automate boring, repetitive tasks to ease my workload. But what&amp;rsquo;s even more rewarding is the opportunity to help non-programmers with their data analysis drudgery. Such is the case with this project.
The Problem My mom works for Catch Up and Read, a Dallas non-profit that helps below-reading-level students catch up before third grade.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Automation is good, so long as you know exactly where to put the machine.&rdquo;<br>
~ Eliyahu Goldratt</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One perk of being a programmer is the ability to automate boring, repetitive tasks to ease my workload.
But what&rsquo;s even more rewarding is the opportunity to help non-programmers with their data analysis drudgery.
Such is the case with this project.</p>
<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>
<p>My mom works for <a href="https://www.catchupandread.org/">Catch Up and Read</a>, a Dallas non-profit that helps below-reading-level
students catch up before third grade.
Their problem was quickly and easily grading third-grade spelling tests.
By analyzing patterns of how a student misspells words,
a smart teacher can determine what concepts that student struggles with and modify their lesson plan accordingly.
This analysis is tedious, requires a fair amount of calculation, and if you&rsquo;ve made it this far you know where this is going.
<strong>Automation!!</strong></p>
<h2 id="constraints">Constraints</h2>
<p>This program had an interesting soup of additional constraints that made it especially fun to write:</p>
<ul>
<li>The program must be intuitive - Any teacher should be able to walk up and use it without training. This means the program needs to be extremely robust and have a very pretty user interface.</li>
<li>The program must be easily distributable - It can&rsquo;t require installing a program or programming language onto the user&rsquo;s computer</li>
<li>The program has to be accessible through public school wifi - no easy feat with archaic whitelist-based firewalls.</li>
</ul>
<p>Given these constraints, I decided to commit a cardinal sin of web development - combining css, javascript, and HTML on a single file.
Doing so would allow me to distribute an HTML file containing the program to teachers, bypassing the firewall issue entirely.</p>
<h2 id="implementation">Implementation</h2>
<figure class="middle"><img src="chunks.png"
         alt="the many chunks of the English language"/><figcaption>
            <p>the many chunks of the English language</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Jumping right in: each word on the test can be split up into chunks, all of which are seen above.
Teachers normally go through each word the child has misspelled and determine which chunks have been missed.
They then tally up each of these incorrect chunks and highlight the most missed chunks on the sheet seen above.</p>
<p>In order to mimic this behavior, my program splits the word into &ldquo;runs&rdquo; of vowels and consonants.
English also has more complex chunks made up of vowels and consonants: the program uses Regex to handle these special cases.
For the intents and purposes of this program (and the English language, for that matter) these special-case chunks are vowels.</p>
<h3 id="an-example">An example</h3>
<p>Let&rsquo;s consider the word <strong>fright</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The first match is <strong>fr</strong>, a run of 2 consonants</li>
<li>Next, it matches <strong>igh</strong>, a special case chunk called a Long Vowel</li>
<li>Finally, the program matches t, a single consonant</li>
</ul>
<p>So, this word chunked up is <code>['fr', 'igh', 't']</code>
Below is an example of how the program grades a student who entered &lsquo;freit&rsquo; instead of fright.</p>
<figure class="middle"><img src="diagram.png"
         alt="grading &amp;lsquo;freit&amp;rsquo;"/><figcaption>
            <p>grading &lsquo;freit&rsquo;</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In order to grade the incorrect word, we need to chunk-ify the correct word and compare the two.
We first (1) determine the vowel-consonant pattern of the valid word: for &lsquo;fright&rsquo;, this pattern is <code>[consonant, vowel, consonant]</code>.
Then, we (2) split each word&rsquo;s chunks into two queues: one for vowels, and the other for consonants. (step 2)
We then use this pattern to (3) dequeue the vowels and consonants in the correct order
and determine if they match. Finally, we (4) count up every incorrect chunk and display it back to the user.</p>
<figure class="middle"><img src="ChunkExample.png"
         alt="word analysis section of program"/><figcaption>
            <p>word analysis section of program</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><em>Word Analysis</em></p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;blayde&rdquo; marks both &lsquo;a&rsquo; and &lsquo;e&rsquo; incorrect because together they form an incorrect long vowel.</li>
<li>when the program doesn&rsquo;t have enough chunks to work with, as is the case with &ldquo;kat&rdquo; being entered for the word &ldquo;camped&rdquo;, it marks these extra chunks as incorrect.</li>
</ul>
<p><figure class="right"><img src="ChunkAnalysis.png"
         alt="chunk analysis program section"/><figcaption>
            <p>chunk analysis program section</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<em>Chunk Analysis</em></p>
<ul>
<li>The analysis section displays which chunks a student has had repeated issues with.</li>
<li>If the student&rsquo;s answer differs greatly from the vowel-consonant pattern of the correct word,
the program can mark chunks as wrong, even if they were correct in their own context.
By clicking on these wrongly-marked chunks, they can be factored out of the calculations.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>
<p>Outside of the core program, the difficulty of this this project lay in the sheer number of edge cases.
Word endings, long vowels, and unmatching vowel-consonant patterns all had to be handled gracefully.
<del>While it would have been great to deploy this to a website to show it off, saving the file locally just made more sense.</del>
The webapp is now up and running, hosted on <a href="https://www.netlify.com/">Netlify</a>! See the <a href="">update</a> here.</p>
<p>In the future, I&rsquo;d love to expand this program to work with the Spanish-language tests as well.
Doing so would be a slog (mo chunks, mo problems). If anyone wants to take a crack at decoding Spanish, here&rsquo;s the
<a href="https://github.com/ethan-cope/ChunkGrader">Github Repo</a>.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Professional CD Crafting with CDRDAO</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</link>
			<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 13:55:04 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/cdrdao/</guid>
			<description>All digital music listeners are equal. Acquisition is painless. Taste is irrelevant. It is pointless to boast about your iTunes collection, or the quality of your playlists on a streaming service. Music became data, one more set of 1&amp;rsquo;s and 0&amp;rsquo;s lurking in your hard drive, invisible to see and impossible to touch. Nothing is less cool than data. ~ David Sax
 Physical media is back. vinyl and cassette sales are through the roof, and why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t they be?</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>All digital music listeners are equal. Acquisition is painless. Taste is irrelevant. It is pointless to boast about your iTunes collection, or the quality of your playlists on a streaming service. Music became data, one more set of 1&rsquo;s and 0&rsquo;s lurking in your hard drive, invisible to see and impossible to touch. Nothing is less cool than data. ~ David Sax</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Physical media is back. vinyl and cassette sales are through the roof, and why shouldn&rsquo;t they be? Digital music services have deprived us of that tactile feel of dropping a needle onto a well-worn album, and the intimate experience of pulling a record from its sleeve.<br>
But today I&rsquo;m focusing on the least flashy member of the physical media family: CDs.</p>
<h2 id="why-cds">Why CDs?</h2>
<p>Everyone loves CDs. Seriously, even though it&rsquo;s been a decade since anyone&rsquo;s used a CD player,
popping open a jewel case brings warm nostalgic memories to the forefront of our minds.
But besides the nostalgia factor, why bother with CDs?</p>
<ul>
<li>First off, CDs are highly customizable. Don&rsquo;t like the ending of a song? Wish the crossfade was smoother between a few tracks on a playlist? Spend half an hour with editing software such as <a href="https://www.audacityteam.org/">Audacity</a>, and you can turn your digital playlists into mixtapes that rival albums and surpass playlists in musicality and momentum.</li>
<li>CD players are cheap, and most modern vehicles still have them. Unlike a phone, your favorite mixtape won&rsquo;t run out of battery!</li>
<li>If you have an artistic bent, you can make CD art with nothing more than a few sharpie markers, like this!</li>
</ul>
<figure class="middle"><img src="https://i.redd.it/mnz4x8mxc5iz.jpg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>Note: not my art, belongs to reddit user <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/themurlocs/comments/6w8470/sometimes_i_get_carried_away_with_my_burnt_cd/">mddecker</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve ever tried to burn your own CDs using Windows Media Player or similar software, you know the results are much less than ideal.
Because WMP burns the entire tracklist track-by-track, the CD player needs a half-second gap between <strong>each track</strong>.
While an eloquent solution to be sure, this understandably kills an album&rsquo;s flow, it&rsquo;s momentum.</p>
<p>So why do retail CDs not have this issue?
Well, instead of burning track by track, retail CDs are burned in DAO, or Disk-At-Once mode.
Doing so encodes the track boundaries in the CD&rsquo;s metadata, which in turn tells the CD player <em>exactly</em> where each track starts and ends. No gaps!
Burning discs in DAO mode gives other benefits as well. Want track names that are visible on the CD Player? Want secret tracks akin to runout grooves on old records? All these are possible with DAO burning.</p>
<p>DAO burning software was once exorbitantly expensive and hard to track down.
But luckily, our friends in the open-source community have a solution: <a href="http://cdrdao.sourceforge.net/">cdrdao</a>.</p>
<h1 id="using-cdrdao">Using CDRDAO</h1>
<p>CDRDAO is a command-line only program. but don&rsquo;t be scared!
Dear reader, I&rsquo;ve done just about everything I can to make using this powerful program as easy as possible!
However, you&rsquo;ll need a few things first.</p>
<ul>
<li>a computer that <strong>has A DVD RW Drive</strong> and is running some distribution of <strong>Linux</strong>.</li>
<li>my <a href="https://github.com/ethan-cope/cdrdao-tools">code</a> from github</li>
<li>music files to be burned to a CD: .wav, m4a, or mp3 files</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="downloading-needed-programs">Downloading needed programs</h2>
<p>here, you need cdrdao and ffmpeg. both can be acquired from your friendly neighborhood package manager.</p>
<p>On Arch Linux:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>sudo pacman -S cdrdao ffmpeg 
</code></pre><h2 id="converting-files-to-wav">Converting files to .wav</h2>
<p>Cdrdao only works with .wav files. If your tracks are pulled from iTunes, they might be .m4a, or possibly .mp3 files.
ffmpeg makes converting them relatively easy, but I also wrote a script that makes this process even more simple!
This script quickly converts all the files in a directory of a given extension to .wav files, which can work with cdrdao!
Here&rsquo;s how to use it:</p>
<ol>
<li>in <code>convertToWav.sh</code>, modify the <code>FILES</code> variable to reflect the file type you&rsquo;re converting from. For example:</li>
</ol>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span class="nv">FILES</span><span class="o">=</span>*.m4a <span class="c1"># this will convert all .m4a files in the directory to .wav files</span>

<span class="nv">FILES</span><span class="o">=</span>*.mp3 <span class="c1"># this will convert all .mp3 files in the directory to .wav files</span>

<span class="nv">FILES</span><span class="o">=</span>*.&lt;extension type&gt; 
<span class="c1"># this will convert all .&lt;extension type&gt; files in the directory to .wav files</span>
</code></pre></div><ol start="2">
<li>Run the program specifying the source directory as follows below:</li>
</ol>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">convertToWav.sh ../Music/Crime_of_the_Century 
<span class="c1">#this will convert all audio files in ../Music/Crime_of_the_Century into .wav files</span>

convertToWav.sh &lt;path to <span class="nb">source</span> directory&gt; 
<span class="c1">#this will convert all audio files in &lt;source directory&gt; to .wav files</span>
</code></pre></div><p><strong>NOTE:</strong> Not all .wav files are created equal! Some don&rsquo;t work with cdrdao due to encoding issues.
to work around this, change the extension to <code>.wav</code>, and run the conversion program!</p>
<h2 id="song-number-shifting">Song Number Shifting</h2>
<p>When burning with CDRDAO, all your tracks need to be in the same directory.
In order to preserve song order, each track is numbered like so: <code>'01 In This State.wav'</code>
If you&rsquo;re building a mixtape song-by-song, manually re-numbering tracks is no problem.
But if you&rsquo;re putting multiple songs from the same source on a disc, this gets tedious. enter <code>songShift.sh</code>.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s use an example for this one. I have 3 directories: <code>Album1</code>, <code>Album2</code>, which contain songs I want to combine into one CD,
and <code>Mixtape</code>, which will hold the final album .wav files in the correct order.
Let&rsquo;s say we want to put Album2 after Album1, and Album1 is 8 tracks long.
Then we&rsquo;ll run the program like this.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">songShift.sh &lt;path to Album2&gt; <span class="m">8</span> <span class="c1">#shifting all track numbers by 8</span>
cp &lt;path to Album2&gt;/*.wav &lt;path to Mixtape&gt; <span class="c1"># copying all the shifted songs to the Mixtape dir.</span>
</code></pre></div><h2 id="generating-toc">Generating TOC</h2>
<p>Cdrdao uses a TOC (or Table Of Contents) file as a template for the contents of the CD. This file contains the track listings, and is used to burn the CD with pretty track names.
Full documentation for TOC files is found <a href="https://tldp.org/HOWTO/MP3-CD-Burning/dao-burning.html">here</a>.
I wrote a script to take some of the tedium out of generating these TOC files.
Simply run the program as follows!</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">genToc.sh &lt;path to directory with .tracks&gt;
</code></pre></div><h2 id="burning-cd">Burning CD</h2>
<p>The next step is simulating the CD burn, which allows you to catch any errors before actually burning the CD.
Just run <code>cdrdao simulate</code> in the same directory as the TOC file and .wav files. If this doesn&rsquo;t spit out any errors, you&rsquo;re ready to burn!
Run the following command to burn the CD!</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>cdrdao write --driver generic-mmc-raw --eject (toc file name) 
</code></pre><h2 id="future-improvements">Future Improvements</h2>
<ul>
<li>I was really interested in doing all of this from the Linux command line, so there are no instructions for Windows. I know a Windows version of CDRDAO exists, so best of luck translating these instructions to Microsoft-ese, Windows users!</li>
<li>I also eventually want to modify the wav converter to work with files other than m4a.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="small-aside">Small Aside</h3>
<p>A few people claim that CD sound quality is bad, 44.1 kHz music isn&rsquo;t high-res enough,
and that <em>they</em> can hear the difference between low and high bitrate music.
While this indeed used to be the case (with <em>extremely</em> low bitrate music), it is no longer true.
Don&rsquo;t believe me? Check out <a href="https://www.soundguys.com/high-bitrate-audio-is-overkill-cd-quality-is-still-great-16518/">this article</a>!</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Echo-Matic Deluxe (Part 1): Marantz-based DIY Tape Echo</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 13:07:50 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</guid>
			<description>Back in 2019, I saw the influential space-rock group Wand live. It was an amazing set of mostly new tunes, but I was a tad distracted by their lead guitarist. He was fiddling with a battered green box for the whole set, and doing so sent his guitar part soaring over the rest of the band in the most atmospheric, gooey wash imaginable. This was my first introduction to the weird, wonderful world of tape echo, and I wanted one!</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://img.audiofanzine.com/images/u/product/normal/roland-re-201-space-echo-6085.jpg" alt="thing"></p>
<p>Back in 2019, I saw the influential space-rock group <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h9PcHA5Ievk">Wand</a> live.
It was an amazing set of mostly new tunes, but I was a tad distracted by their lead guitarist.
He was fiddling with a battered green box for the whole set, and doing so sent his guitar part soaring over the rest of the band in the most atmospheric, gooey wash imaginable.
This was my first introduction to the weird, wonderful world of tape echo, and I wanted one!</p>
<p>Sadly, vintage tape echoes (such as the Roland RE201 Cory was using that night) go for
<em><strong><a href="https://reverb.com/p/roland-space-echo-re-201">thousands</a></strong></em>
on the used market, and are notoriously finnicky to maintain.
Cheaper digital emulations unsurprisingly fail to capture the warm, fuzzy magic of these complex analog devices.
But one day I stumbled on a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ABU-psBnmxk">youtube video</a> demonstrating a DIY tape echo built from nothing more than a few analog components and a tape deck, and I knew I had to make one!</p>
<h2 id="the-theory">The Theory</h2>
<p>Conceptually, tape echo is pretty simple. Consider a tape deck with 3 heads: a record head, a monitor head, and an erase head.
When recording on a 3-head deck, the signal that&rsquo;s just been recorded to the tape by the record head is captured and sent out via the playback head.
But when you send this monitor output signal directly back into the line-in jack, a feedback loop is created,
and your original sound is repeated.
From there, all you need are controls!</p>
<ul>
<li>Varying the speed of the tape deck motor changes the speed of the tape, which in turn controls the delay time.</li>
<li>Adding a resistance in the feedback loop controls the amount of signal fed back into the unit, which in turn varies the number of delay repeats.</li>
<li>Add a potentiometer to control the wet/dry mix and a volume output knob, and you have a tape delay!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-circuit">The Circuit</h2>
<p>The circuit I&rsquo;m utilizing is a modified version of <a href="https://proto-schlock.blogspot.com/2015/04/echo-matic-diy-tape-delay.html">Proto-Schlock&rsquo;s</a>, who in turn got it from Boscorelli&rsquo;s <em>the StompBox Cookbook</em>.</p>
<ul>
<li>My most notable modification is the addition of a reverb module from BYOC, to simulate the orginal RE201 unit&rsquo;s spring reverb. If you don&rsquo;t want to do this, just connect <code>TO_RV</code> and <code>FROM_RV</code> with a jumper wire.</li>
<li>I also added a low-pass filter to the feedback loop, since high frequencies tend to make my unit self-oscillate.
you should experiment with different filters and filter designs here!</li>
</ul>
<figure class="big"><img src="schematic.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>the modified schematic</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-materials">The Materials</h2>
<p>Ebay is a wonderful place. One where you can get a late 70&rsquo;s 3-head stereo tape recorder for $40 + shipping.
These old Marantz 3-head decks still have a pretty devoted following, so this unit was an absolute steal!
I already had a DIY spring reverb pedal from <a href="https://buildyourownclone.com/">BYOC</a> lying around, which would emulate the gooey reverb of the original unit without having to buy a separate reverb tank.
The rest of the parts for this project were relatively easy to source at <a href="https://smallbear-electronics.mybigcommerce.com/">Small Bear</a>, my go-to for quality guitar pedal components. I&rsquo;ve included a BOM for the project in the Github Repo.</p>
<h2 id="the-build">The Build</h2>
<h3 id="prototyping">Prototyping</h3>
<p>After acquiring all the parts, it was prototyping time!</p>
<figure><img src="breadboard1.jpeg"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>not the cleanest, I&rsquo;ll be the first to admit</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Despite the circuit&rsquo;s complexity, breadboarding wasn&rsquo;t all that bad.
I hooked it up to the tape deck and&hellip; it worked! In retrospect, I&rsquo;m really glad I tested this on the breadboard first.
Doing so let me experiment with a few different high-pass filter designs before I decided on the one in the schematic.</p>
<h3 id="motor-control">Motor Control</h3>
<p>Next step: modifying the motor controller. Some tape units have this functionality built-in, but mine didn&rsquo;t. to work around this, I coupled the motor to it&rsquo;s power source via a PWM controller.
It&rsquo;s ideal to have this PWM frequency above the audio range (greater than 20 kHz).</p>
<p>or&hellip; at least it would. For some reason, my PWM controllers didn&rsquo;t want to play nice with the tape deck&rsquo;s motor.
I ended up going the analog route of putting a potentiometer inline with the motor to control the motor speed.
Every motor is different, but mine stalled at any resistance over 50 Ohms.</p>
<figure class="right"><img src="board.png"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>the finished board</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="manufacturing">Manufacturing</h3>
<p>Finally, it was time to manufacture.
If you want to make this project yourself, I&rsquo;ve provided the Autodesk Eagle .brd files in the Github repo. Note that this is the first time I&rsquo;ve designed a pcb, so it may not be perfect! I manufactured it with <a href="https://aisler.net/">Aisler</a>,
and only paid $10 for 3 boards!</p>
<h2 id="part-1-thoughts">Part 1 Thoughts</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s going to be a while before I get back on this project.
Aisler takes about a month to manufacture, and junior year is starting up. Stay tuned for a part 2!</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Buswarn: RasPi-based Transit Bus Tracking</title>
			<link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 12:53:34 -0500</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</guid>
			<description>Public transportation is like a magnifying glass that shows you civilization up close. ~ Chris Gethard
 What is Buswarn? During the COVID year, I moved off-campus. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize at the time, but my only lifeline to my in-person classes, study rooms, and meals would be the Texas A&amp;amp;M Bus Transit System. Problems manifested themselves quickly. Buses ran at seemingly random intervals, and the website that displayed the schedule often had errors rendering on my mobile phone.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Public transportation is like a magnifying glass that shows you civilization up close. ~ Chris Gethard</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="what-is-buswarn">What is Buswarn?</h2>
<p>During the COVID year, I moved off-campus. I didn&rsquo;t realize at the time, but my only lifeline to my in-person classes, study rooms, and meals would be the Texas A&amp;M Bus Transit System.
Problems manifested themselves quickly. Buses ran at seemingly random intervals, and the website that displayed the schedule often had errors rendering on my mobile phone.
What I needed was a simple device that displayed how many minutes I had to wait until the next bus arrived at my apartment.
This device wouldn&rsquo;t require me to have the foresight of googling the schedule and doing mental math to determine what time to leave my apartment in order to make the next bus.
Armed with these design goals, I set to work with a Raspberry Pi and few 7-segment displays I had lying around.</p>
<h2 id="design">Design</h2>
<p>Here&rsquo;s the birds-eye view of how the code works.</p>
<ol>
<li>Download the schedule website for the desired route from the internet every morning</li>
<li>Process the timetable, and generate a list of times buses will arrive at my bus stop</li>
<li>Compare the current time with next bus arrival time, and print the difference to a 7-segment display</li>
<li>Gracefully handle website outages and power cycles to the pi.</li>
<li>Turn the pi off at the end of the day and repeat</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="implementation">Implementation</h2>
<p>Buswarn was written in Python, and I have bits of it written in C in case I want to implement it on a Arduino later down the road.</p>
<ul>
<li>I wanted to use this as an opportunity to bone up on my HTML skills, and ended up using the BeautifulSoup library to parse the HTML table into a Python array.</li>
<li>The LCD is controlled by a custom Python library that can be used on using on future projects.</li>
<li>This is the first project I&rsquo;ve developed entirely remotely through SSH on a headless machine.</li>
</ul>
<figure class="big"><img src="operation.gif"
         alt="image"/><figcaption>
            <p>prototype working fine!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="constraints-and-challenges">Constraints and Challenges</h2>
<p>This project&rsquo;s main challenge was writing an extremely resilient program that could be left to run without breaking for extended periods of time.
In practice, this meant handling a <strong>LOT</strong> of edge cases.
For example, on football game days the website I pulled information from was essentially offline.
Handling these edge cases individually offered me total control over the program&rsquo;s stability. It&rsquo;s been running for a few months now with no errors whatsoever!
Here&rsquo;s the <a href="https://github.com/ethan-cope/pybuswarn">Github Repo</a>.</p>
<h2 id="future-changes">Future Changes</h2>
<p><em>in order from least to most difficult to implement</em></p>
<ul>
<li>The Nokia 5110 display suits this project much better than 7-segments.
The 5110 is a 84x48 px lcd display with a backlight, which consumes less power and is much more visible in high-brightness environments.
I&rsquo;ve been having problems getting it to work on the Pi, so it&rsquo;s currently on the drawing board.</li>
<li>A classic engineering problem: it works, but it&rsquo;s not exactly pretty. even a 3d printed enclosure would go a long way to make it more presentable.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;d love to eventually build these as low-power self-contained nodes in a LORA mesh. This would allow these stations to be installed at any bus station that has sunlight, no internet or power required.
I&rsquo;ll explore this possibility when I delve more into my self-contained LORA mesh project.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="final-words">Final Words</h2>
<p>This project taught me loads about building a program to an incredibly high reliability standard, and directly influenced my development mindset when tackling programming challenges at Stanley Black &amp; Decker.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
