<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>raspberryPi on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/raspberrypi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in raspberryPi on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 13:28:52 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/raspberrypi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🏆 MyMirror: a Google-integrated Smart Mirror</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 13:28:52 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</guid>
      <description>Note: More information about myMirror can be found on the project&amp;rsquo;s devpost. Check there for other peoples&#39; contributions!
Why myMirror? When I wake up in the morning, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot I know I probably should do. For example, I should probably prepare for the day ahead by checking the weather and my daily calendar. But often times, I just don&amp;rsquo;t. For situations like this, myMirror is here to help.
myMirror solves the above dilemma by integrating this crucial information into your everyday bathroom mirror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buswarn: RasPi-based Transit Bus Tracking</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 12:53:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/buswarn/</guid>
      <description>Public transportation is like a magnifying glass that shows you civilization up close. ~ Chris Gethard
 What is Buswarn? During the COVID year, I moved off-campus. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize at the time, but my only lifeline to my in-person classes, study rooms, and meals would be the Texas A&amp;amp;M Bus Transit System. Problems manifested themselves quickly. Buses ran at seemingly random intervals, and the website that displayed the schedule often had errors rendering on my mobile phone.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
