<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Japan on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/japan/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Japan on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 19:41:09 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/japan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🚫🚆(I rode) Everything *but* the trains in Japan</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jptransit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 19:41:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/jptransit/</guid>
      <description>Shonan Monorail (image credit)
  As an engineer, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to visit Japan and not be obsessed with its trains. From record-breaking bullet trains to spaghetti-like subway networks, Japan does trains better than anywhere else I&amp;rsquo;ve been. But even the most train-obsessed nations acknowledge that heavy rail isn&amp;rsquo;t a catch-all solution. So as a bit of a curveball, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this transit post about everything but the trains in Japan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏙️ Is Nagoya Boring?</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 19:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/twodaysinnagoya/</guid>
      <description>Recently, it seems like everyone I talk to is either visiting or returning from Japan. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just my observation - according to multiple sources, Japan&amp;rsquo;s post-covid tourism numbers are through the roof. While many plan their trips around the glitz and glamor of Tokyo or the rich culture of Kyoto, there&amp;rsquo;s another city that I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to see on any itinerary - Nagoya.
Despite being it&amp;rsquo;s third largest metro area, Nagoya is nationally renowned as &amp;ldquo;Japan&amp;rsquo;s most boring city&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Japan&#39;s Early-2000&#39;s Architectural Nostalgia</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 01:00:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/japanarch/</guid>
      <description>The architectural definition of &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;1 has always been a moving target. Every year, once &amp;ldquo;stylistically cutting-edge&amp;rdquo; buildings slip into the realm of &amp;ldquo;dated&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cliche&amp;rdquo;. And the other day, I finally stumbled on across a building that proved this point. Nagoya&amp;rsquo;s Sasashima-Ribu station is totally representative of a particular architectural style; one that, at the time of it&amp;rsquo;s construction, was synonymous with &amp;ldquo;modern architecture&amp;rdquo;. But a quarter of a century has separated innovation from trend, revealing a slew of early 2000&amp;rsquo;s quintessential quirks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Japan&#39;s Most Iconic Model Cars Come Out Of Vending Machines</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 01:00:15 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/gacha/</guid>
      <description>Remember those 25-cent gumball machines? The ones where you could trade a quarter for a gumball older than the dotcom crash? Imagine that, but instead of a chunk of crusty candy, you win a random 1/64th scale model car. That&amp;rsquo;s essentially Gachapon!
 Bandai Namco&amp;rsquo;s toy vending machines are addictively simple. Insert cash (1), twist dial (2), and collect model (3). Since the 1970&amp;rsquo;s, Gachapon machines have dispensed billions of anime figurines, sushi keychains, and (most notably), tiny scale vehicles.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
