<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>project on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in project on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 18:54:22 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🎧 Why I replaced Spotify with a Playstation Portable for a month</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 18:54:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/psp/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with my previous essay, you know I have mixed feelings on music streaming. Spotify, with its algorithmic recommendations and &amp;ldquo;gamification&amp;rdquo; of listening hours, seems purpose-built for constant, mindless music consumption. I was sick of it. Would I enjoy music more if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the Spotify ecosystem at all? This October, I set out to answer this question - the hard way. I blocked Spotify for the whole month and moved my music over to&amp;hellip; A Playstation Portable!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🍅⏰ Using the Pomodoro Technique to make a Pomodoro Timer (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pomodorotimer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 18:52:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pomodorotimer/</guid>
      <description>first prototype!
  Using the Pomodoro Technique to make a Pomodoro Timer (Part 1) A famous Henry Ford quote goes: &amp;ldquo;Nothing is particularly hard, if you divide it into small [enough] jobs&amp;rdquo;. One popular way to practically implement this advice is something called the &amp;ldquo;Pomodoro Technique&amp;rdquo;. 1
The Pomodoro Technique aims to divide the day into bite-sized, productive time chunks. The idea is to set some kind of timer for 25 minutes before you start working.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
