<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PCB on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/pcb/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PCB on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 15:39:53 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/pcb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On Personal Projects and Giving Up (Echo-Matic Deluxe Update)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 15:39:53 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special2/</guid>
      <description>Personal projects often feel like a weird limbo between work and play. Starting a project motivated by nothing but passion and a willingness to learn is great. Even if the initial enthusiasm fades, it&amp;rsquo;s still worth it to power through. A finished project is often its own satisfaction. But when all personal interest in the project evaporates, even the most simple tasks become tedious. Every time I think about my gutted Marantz tape deck project, I find myself caring less and less.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Echo-Matic Deluxe (Part 1): Marantz-based DIY Tape Echo</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 13:07:50 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/echo-matic_special/</guid>
      <description>Back in 2019, I saw the influential space-rock group Wand live. It was an amazing set of mostly new tunes, but I was a tad distracted by their lead guitarist. He was fiddling with a battered green box for the whole set, and doing so sent his guitar part soaring over the rest of the band in the most atmospheric, gooey wash imaginable. This was my first introduction to the weird, wonderful world of tape echo, and I wanted one!</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
