<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Winner on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</title>
    <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/winner/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Winner on Hey, I&#39;m Ethan.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 17:30:30 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ethan-cope.github.io/tags/winner/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🏆 Battery Recycling: The Dark Side of an All-EV Future (2nd place, Problems Worth Solving Competition 2023)</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 17:30:30 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/pws/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;ve got to start with the customer experience and work back toward the technology, not the other way around. ~ Steve Jobs&#xA;Last weekend I had the opportunity to participate in Problems Worth Solving: Texas A&amp;amp;M&amp;rsquo;s first and only entrepreneurship competition that outright bans solutions.&#xA;Great businesses arise from an intimate understanding of your customers&amp;rsquo; needs. PWS emphasizes this critical step of entrepreneurship by focusing entrepreneurs on the problem, not the solution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>🏆 MyMirror: a Google-integrated Smart Mirror</title>
      <link>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 13:28:52 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ethan-cope.github.io/posts/mymirror/</guid>
      <description>Note: More information about myMirror can be found on the project&amp;rsquo;s devpost. Check there for other peoples&amp;rsquo; contributions!&#xA;Why myMirror? When I wake up in the morning, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot I know I probably should do. For example, I should probably prepare for the day ahead by checking the weather and my daily calendar. But often times, I just don&amp;rsquo;t. For situations like this, myMirror is here to help.&#xA;myMirror solves the above dilemma by integrating this crucial information into your everyday bathroom mirror.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
